{"test_questions": [[{"question": "ENORMOUS", "opta": "Soft", "optb": "Average", "optc": "Tiny", "optd": "Weak", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "COMMISSIONED", "opta": "Started", "optb": "Closed", "optc": "Finished", "optd": "Terminated", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ARTIFICIAL", "opta": "Red", "optb": "Natural", "optc": "Truthful", "optd": "Solid", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EXODUS", "opta": "Influx", "optb": "Home-coming", "optc": "Return", "optd": "Restoration", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RELINQUISH", "opta": "Abdicate", "optb": "Renounce", "optc": "Possess", "optd": "Deny", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EXPAND", "opta": "Convert", "optb": "Condense", "optc": "Congest", "optd": "Conclude", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MORTAL", "opta": "Divine", "optb": "Immortal", "optc": "Spiritual", "optd": "Eternal", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "QUIESCENT", "opta": "ACTIVE", "optb": "Dormant", "optc": "Weak", "optd": "Unconcerned", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "OBEYING", "opta": "Ordering", "optb": "Following", "optc": "Refusing", "optd": "Contradicting", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FRAUDULENT", "opta": "Candid", "optb": "Direct", "optc": "Forthright", "optd": "Genuine", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FLAGITIOUS", "opta": "Innocent", "optb": "Vapid", "optc": "Ignorant", "optd": "Frivolous", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BELITTLE", "opta": "Criticize", "optb": "Flatter", "optc": "Exaggerate", "optd": "Adore", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Main Entry: belittle\nPart of Speech: verb\nDefinition: detract\nSynonyms: bad-mouth, blister, criticize, cut down to size, cut to the quick, decry, deprecate, depreciate, deride, derogate, diminish, discount, discredit, disparage, dispraise, downgrade, downplay, dump on, knock*, lower, minimize, pan, pooh pooh, poor mouth, put down, rip*, roast, run down, scoff at, scorch*, scorn, shoot down, shoot full of holes, slam*, smear, sneer at, sour grapes, squash, squelch, take a swipe at, take down, take down a peg, tear down, underestimate, underrate, undervalue, write off.\nAntonyms: build up, exaggerate, praise, value"}, {"question": "STARTLED", "opta": "Amused", "optb": "Relaxed", "optc": "Endless", "optd": "Astonished", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BUSY", "opta": "Occupied", "optb": "Engrossed", "optc": "Relaxed", "optd": "Engaged", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FRESH", "opta": "Faulty", "optb": "Sluggish", "optc": "Disgraceful", "optd": "Stale", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CULPABLE", "opta": "Defendable", "optb": "Blameless", "optc": "Careless", "optd": "Irresponsible", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EVASIVE", "opta": "Free", "optb": "Honest", "optc": "Liberal", "optd": "Frank", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GREGARIOUS", "opta": "Antisocial", "optb": "Glorious", "optc": "Horrendous", "optd": "Similar", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "AWARE", "opta": "Uncertain", "optb": "Ignorant", "optc": "Sure", "optd": "Doubtful", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HIRSUTE", "opta": "Scaly", "optb": "Bald", "optc": "Erudite", "optd": "Quiet", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SHRINK", "opta": "Contract", "optb": "Spoil", "optc": "Expand", "optd": "Stretch", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "COMMON", "opta": "Rare", "optb": "Small", "optc": "Petty", "optd": "Poor", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "COMFORT", "opta": "Uncomfort", "optb": "Miscomfort", "optc": "Discomfort", "optd": "None Of These", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DEAR", "opta": "Priceless", "optb": "Free", "optc": "Worthless", "optd": "Cheap", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ARROGANT", "opta": "Humble", "optb": "Cowardly", "optc": "Egotistic", "optd": "Gentlemanly", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VICTORIOUS", "opta": "Defeated", "optb": "Annexed", "optc": "Destroyed", "optd": "Vanquished", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GRACEFUL", "opta": "Rough", "optb": "Expert", "optc": "Miserable", "optd": "Awkward", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "NADIR", "opta": "Modernity", "optb": "Zenith", "optc": "Liberty", "optd": "Progress", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EXTRAVAGANCE", "opta": "Luxury", "optb": "Poverty", "optc": "Economical", "optd": "Cheapness", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Main Entry: extravagant\n\nPart of Speech: adjective\n\nDefinition: indulgent, wasteful\n\nSynonyms: absurd, bizarre, costly, crazy, exaggerated, excessive, exorbitant, expensive, extortionate, extreme, fanciful, fancy, fantastic, flamboyant, flashy, foolish, garish, gaudy, grandiose, immoderate, implausible, improvident, imprudent, inordinate, lavish, ludicrous, nonsensical, ornate, ostentatious, outrageous, overpriced, preposterous, pretentious, prodigal, profligate, reckless, ridiculous, showy, silly, spendthrift, steep, unbalanced, unconscionable, unreasonable, unrestrained\n\nAntonyms: close, economical, moderate, provident, reasonable, saving, stingy, thrifty, unpretentious"}, {"question": "PERTINENT", "opta": "Irrational", "optb": "Irregular", "optc": "Insistent", "optd": "Irrelevant", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "OBSCURE", "opta": "Implicit", "optb": "Obnoxious", "optc": "Explicit", "optd": "Pedantic", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "URBANE", "opta": "Illiterate", "optb": "Backward", "optc": "Discourteous", "optd": "Orthodox", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VANITY", "opta": "Pride", "optb": "Humility", "optc": "Conceit", "optd": "Ostentatious", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RARELY", "opta": "Hardly", "optb": "Definately", "optc": "Frequently", "optd": "Periodically", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MALICIOUS", "opta": "Kind", "optb": "Boastful", "optc": "Generous", "optd": "Indifferent", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EPILOGUE", "opta": "Dialogue", "optb": "Prelude", "optc": "Post script", "optd": "Epigram", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CAPACIOUS", "opta": "Limited", "optb": "Caring", "optc": "Foolish", "optd": "Changeable", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CONDENSE", "opta": "Expand", "optb": "Distribute", "optc": "Interpret", "optd": "Lengthen", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ADAPTABLE", "opta": "Adoptable", "optb": "Flexible", "optc": "Yielding", "optd": "Rigid", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SACROSANCT", "opta": "Irreligious", "optb": "Unethical", "optc": "Irreverent", "optd": "Unholy", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INDISCREET", "opta": "Reliable", "optb": "Honest", "optc": "Prudent", "optd": "Stupid", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FAMILIAR", "opta": "Unpleasant", "optb": "Dangerous", "optc": "Friendly", "optd": "Strange", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TANGIBLE", "opta": "Ethereal", "optb": "Concrete", "optc": "Actual", "optd": "Solid", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LOVE", "opta": "Villainy", "optb": "Hatred", "optc": "Compulsion", "optd": "Force", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FAMOUS", "opta": "Disgraced", "optb": "Unknown", "optc": "Evil", "optd": "Popular", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ABSOLUTE", "opta": "Deficient", "optb": "Faulty", "optc": "Limited", "optd": "Scarce", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Word: absolute \n\nPart of Speech: adjective \n\nDefinition: without limit \n\nSynonyms: complete, consummate, downright, entire, flat out, free, full, infinite, no catch, no fine print, no holds barred, no ifs ands or buts, no joke, no strings attached, outright, plenary, pure, sheer, simple, straight out, supreme, thorough, total, unabridged, unadulterated, unconditional, unlimited, unqualified, unrestricted, utter \n\nAntonyms: accountable, circumscribed, limited, restricted, tractable"}, {"question": "FRUGAL", "opta": "Copious", "optb": "Extravagant", "optc": "Generous", "optd": "Ostentatious", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INSIPID", "opta": "Tasty", "optb": "Stupid", "optc": "Discreet", "optd": "Feast", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ABLE", "opta": "Disable", "optb": "Inable", "optc": "Unable", "optd": "Misable", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HOSTILITY", "opta": "Courtesy", "optb": "Hospitality", "optc": "Relationship", "optd": "Friendliness", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CROWDED", "opta": "Busy", "optb": "Congested", "optc": "Quiet", "optd": "Deserted", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "COMIC", "opta": "Emotional", "optb": "Tragic", "optc": "Fearful", "optd": "Painful", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HAPLESS", "opta": "Cheerful", "optb": "Consistent", "optc": "Fortunate", "optd": "Shapely", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FLIMSY", "opta": "Frail", "optb": "Filthy", "optc": "Firm", "optd": "Flippant", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EQUANIMITY", "opta": "Resentment", "optb": "Dubiousness", "optc": "Duplicity", "optd": "Excitement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ADDITION", "opta": "Division", "optb": "Enumeration", "optc": "Subtraction", "optd": "Multiplication", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ZENITH", "opta": "Acme", "optb": "Top", "optc": "Nadir", "optd": "Pinnacle", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DOUBTFUL", "opta": "Famous", "optb": "Certain", "optc": "Fixed", "optd": "Important", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PERENNIAL", "opta": "Frequent", "optb": "Regular", "optc": "Lasting", "optd": "Rare", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BENIGN", "opta": "Malevolent", "optb": "Soft", "optc": "Friendly", "optd": "Unwise", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HINDRANCE", "opta": "Aid", "optb": "Persuasion", "optc": "Cooperation", "optd": "Agreement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EXTRICATE", "opta": "Manifest", "optb": "Palpable", "optc": "Release", "optd": "Entangle", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "REPRESS", "opta": "Inhibit", "optb": "Liberate", "optc": "Curb", "optd": "Quell", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ACQUITTED", "opta": "Freed", "optb": "Burdened", "optc": "Convicted", "optd": "Entrusted", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PROVOCATION", "opta": "Vocation", "optb": "Pacification", "optc": "Peace", "optd": "Destruction", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SUBSERVIENT", "opta": "Aggressive", "optb": "Straightforward", "optc": "Dignified", "optd": "Supercilious", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LEND", "opta": "Borrow", "optb": "Cheat", "optc": "Pawn", "optd": "Hire", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FAINT-HEARTED", "opta": "Warm-hearted", "optb": "Full-blooded", "optc": "Hot-blooded", "optd": "Stout-hearted", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "REMISS", "opta": "Forgetful", "optb": "Watchful", "optc": "Dutiful", "optd": "Harmful", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TRANSPARENT", "opta": "Semi-transparent", "optb": "Muddy", "optc": "Opaque", "optd": "Dark", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HONORARY", "opta": "Dishonorable", "optb": "Reputed", "optc": "Paid", "optd": "Official", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "METICULOUS", "opta": "Mutual", "optb": "Shaggy", "optc": "Meretricious", "optd": "Slovenly", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LOQUACIOUS", "opta": "Reticent", "optb": "Talkative", "optc": "Garrulous", "optd": "Verbose", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CONFESS", "opta": "Deny", "optb": "Refuse", "optc": "Contest", "optd": "Contend", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ANNOY", "opta": "Praise", "optb": "Rejoice", "optc": "Please", "optd": "Reward", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "REPEL", "opta": "Attend", "optb": "Concentrate", "optc": "Continue", "optd": "Attract", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SUPPRESS", "opta": "Encourage", "optb": "Allow", "optc": "Praise", "optd": "Permit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "NIGGARDLY", "opta": "Frugal", "optb": "Thrifty", "optc": "Stingy", "optd": "Generous", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "IMPASSE", "opta": "Resurgence", "optb": "Breakthrough", "optc": "Continuation", "optd": "Combination", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HAPHAZARD", "opta": "Fortuitous", "optb": "Indifferent", "optc": "Deliberate", "optd": "Accidental", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DENSITY", "opta": "Rarity", "optb": "Intelligence", "optc": "Clarity", "optd": "Brightness", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ADHERENT", "opta": "Detractor", "optb": "Enemy", "optc": "Alien", "optd": "Rival", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BASE", "opta": "Climax", "optb": "Height", "optc": "Top", "optd": "Roof", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PATCHY", "opta": "Attractive", "optb": "Uniform", "optc": "Simple", "optd": "Clear", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ENMITY", "opta": "Important", "optb": "Unnecessary", "optc": "Friendship", "optd": "Likeness", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HOLLOW", "opta": "Filled", "optb": "Solid", "optc": "Strong", "optd": "Substantial", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Main Entry: hollow \nPart of Speech: adjective\nDefinition: empty, hollowed out\nSynonyms: alveolate, arched, carved out, cavernous, cleft, concave, cup-shaped, cupped, curved, deep-set, depressed, dimpled, excavated, incurved, indented, infundibular, not solid, notched, pitted, striated, sunken, troughlike, unfilled, vacant, vaulted, void\nAntonyms: convex, full, raised, solid."}, {"question": "VALUABLE", "opta": "Invaluable", "optb": "Worthless", "optc": "Inferior", "optd": "Lowly", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GULLIBLE", "opta": "Incredulous", "optb": "Fickle", "optc": "Easy", "optd": "Stylish", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INDUSTRIOUS", "opta": "Indifferent", "optb": "Indolent", "optc": "Casual", "optd": "Passive", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "AUTONOMY", "opta": "Slavery", "optb": "Subordination", "optc": "Dependence", "optd": "Submissiveness", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ALIEN", "opta": "Native", "optb": "Domiciled", "optc": "Natural", "optd": "Resident", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SYNTHETIC", "opta": "Affable", "optb": "Natural", "optc": "Plastic", "optd": "Cosmetic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BALANCE", "opta": "Disbalance", "optb": "Misbalance", "optc": "Debalance", "optd": "Imbalance", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LIABILITY", "opta": "Property", "optb": "Assets", "optc": "Debt", "optd": "Treasure", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MOUNTAIN", "opta": "Plain", "optb": "Plateau", "optc": "Precipice", "optd": "Valley", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "STATIONARY", "opta": "Active", "optb": "Mobile", "optc": "Rapid", "optd": "Busy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CONCEDE", "opta": "Object", "optb": "Refuse", "optc": "Grant", "optd": "Accede", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VIOLENT", "opta": "Humble", "optb": "Harmless", "optc": "Gentle", "optd": "Tame", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VIRTUOUS", "opta": "Wicked", "optb": "Corrupt", "optc": "Vicious", "optd": "Scandalous", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GAIN", "opta": "Loose", "optb": "Fall", "optc": "Lost", "optd": "Lose", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PRELIMINARY", "opta": "Final", "optb": "First", "optc": "Secondary", "optd": "Initial", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DEFIANCE", "opta": "Anxiety", "optb": "Obedience", "optc": "Suspicion", "optd": "Dismay", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ENCOURAGE", "opta": "Dampen", "optb": "Disapprove", "optc": "Discourage", "optd": "Warn", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LUCID", "opta": "Glory", "optb": "Noisy", "optc": "Obscure", "optd": "Distinct", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "STRINGENT", "opta": "General", "optb": "Vehement", "optc": "Lenient", "optd": "Magnanimous", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MINOR", "opta": "Big", "optb": "Major", "optc": "Tall", "optd": "Heavy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "REVEALED", "opta": "Denied", "optb": "Concealed", "optc": "Ignored", "optd": "Overlooked", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ESSENTIAL", "opta": "Extra", "optb": "Noughts", "optc": "Minors", "optd": "Trivial", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HYPOCRITICAL", "opta": "Gentle", "optb": "Sincere", "optc": "Amiable", "optd": "Dependable", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FICKLE", "opta": "Courageous", "optb": "Sincere", "optc": "Steadfast", "optd": "Humble", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"If you don't keep quiet I shall shoot you\", he said to her in a calm voice.", "opta": "He warned her to shoot if she didn't keep quiet calmly.", "optb": "He said calmly that I shall shoot you if you don't be quiet.", "optc": "He warned her calmly that he would shoot her if she didn't keep quiet.", "optd": "Calmly he warned her that be quiet or else he will have to shoot her.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I told him that he was not working hard.", "opta": "I said to him, \"You are not working hard.\"", "optb": "I told to him, \"You are not working hard.\"", "optc": "I said, \"You are not working hard.\"", "optd": "I said to him, \"He is not working hard.\"", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "His father ordered him to go to his room and study.", "opta": "His father said, \"Go to your room and study.\"", "optb": "His father said to him, \"Go and study in your room.\"", "optc": "His father shouted, \"Go right now to your study room\"", "optd": "His father said firmly, \"Go and study in your room.\"", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He said to his father, \"Please increase my pocket-money.\"", "opta": "He told his father, \"Please increase the pocket-money\"", "optb": "He pleaded his father to please increase my pocket money.", "optc": "He requested his father to increase his pocket-money.", "optd": "He asked his father to increase his pocket-money.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She said that her brother was getting married.", "opta": "She said, \"Her brother is getting married.\"", "optb": "She told, \"Her brother is getting married.\"", "optc": "She said, \"My brother is getting married.\"", "optd": "She said, \"My brother was getting married.\"", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The boy said, \"Who dare call you a thief?\"", "opta": "The boy enquired who dared call him a thief.", "optb": "The boy asked who called him a thief.", "optc": "The boy told that who dared call him a thief.", "optd": "The boy wondered who dared call a thief.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She exclaimed with sorrow that was a very miserable plight.", "opta": "She said with sorrow, \"What a pity it is.\"", "optb": "She said, \"What a mystery it is.\"", "optc": "She said, \"What a miserable sight it is.\"", "optd": "She said, \"What a miserable plight it is.\"", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dhruv said that he was sick and tired of working for that company.", "opta": "Dhruv said, \"I am sick and tired of working for this company.\"", "optb": "Dhruv said, \"He was tired of that company.\"", "optc": "Dhruv said to me, \"I am sick and tired of working for this company.\"", "optd": "Dhruv said, \"I will be tired of working for that company.\"", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Are you alone, my son?\" asked a soft voice close behind me.", "opta": "A soft voice asked that what I was doing there alone.", "optb": "A soft voice said to me are you alone son.", "optc": "A soft voice from my back asked If I was alone.", "optd": "A soft voice behind me asked If I was alone.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She said to him, \"Why don't you go today?\"", "opta": "She asked him why he did not go that day.", "optb": "She said to him why he don't go that day.", "optc": "She asked him not to go that day.", "optd": "She asked him why he did not go today.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He exclaimed with joy that India had won the Sahara Cup.", "opta": "He said, \"India has won the Sahara Cup\"", "optb": "He said, \"India won the Sahara Cup\"", "optc": "He said, \"How! India will win the Sahara Cup\"", "optd": "He said, \"Hurrah! India has won the Sahara Cup\"", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The little girl said to her mother, \"Did the sun rise in the East?\"", "opta": "The little girl said to her mother that the sun rose in the East.", "optb": "The little girl asked her mother if the sun rose in the East.", "optc": "The little girl said to her mother if the sun rises in the East.", "optd": "The little girl asked her mother if the sun is in the East.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The man said, \"No, I refused to confers guilt.\"", "opta": "The man emphatically refused to confers guilt.", "optb": "The man refused to confers his guilt.", "optc": "The man told that he did not confers guilt.", "optd": "The man was stubborn enough to confers guilt.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nita ordered her servant to bring her cup of tea.", "opta": "Nita told her servant, \"Bring a cup of tea.\"", "optb": "Nita said, \"Bring me a cup of tea.\"", "optc": "Nita said to her servant, \"Bring me a cup of tea.\"", "optd": "Nita told her servant, \"Bring her that cup of tea.\"", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My cousin said, \"My room-mate had snored throughout the night.\"", "opta": "my cousin said that her room-mate snored throughout the night.", "optb": "my cousin told me that her room-mate snored throughout the night.", "optc": "my cousin complained to me that her room-mate is snoring throughout the night.", "optd": "my cousin felt that her room-mate may be snoring throughout the night.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Please don't go away\", she said.", "opta": "She said to please her and not go away.", "optb": "She told me to go away.", "optc": "She begged me not to go away.", "optd": "She begged that I not go away.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She said to her friend, \"I know where is everyone\"", "opta": "She told that she knew where was everyone.", "optb": "She told her friend that she knew where was everyone.", "optc": "She told her friend that she knew where is everyone.", "optd": "She told her friend that she knows where was everyone.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "After driving professor Kumar to the museum she dropped him at his hotel.", "opta": "After being driven to the museum, Professor Kumar was dropped at his hotel.", "optb": "Professor Kumar was being driven dropped at his hotel.", "optc": "After she had driven Professor Kumar to the museum she had dropped him at his hotel.", "optd": "After she was driven Professor Kumar to the museum she had dropped him at his hotel.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I remember my sister taking me to the museum.", "opta": "I remember I was taken to the museum by my sister.", "optb": "I remember being taken to the museum by my sister.", "optc": "I remember myself being taken to the museum by my sister.", "optd": "I remember taken to the museum by my sister.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Who is creating this mess?", "opta": "Who has been created this mess?", "optb": "By whom has this mess been created?", "optc": "By whom this mess is being created?", "optd": "By whom is this mess being created?", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They greet me cheerfully every morning.", "opta": "Every morning I was greeted cheerfully.", "optb": "I am greeted cheerfully by them every morning.", "optc": "I am being greeted cheerfully by them every morning.", "optd": "Cheerful greeting is done by them every morning to me.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Darjeeling grows tea.", "opta": "Tea is being grown in Darjeeling.", "optb": "Let the tea be grown in Darjeeling.", "optc": "Tea is grown in Darjeeling.", "optd": "Tea grows in Darjeeling.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They have built a perfect dam across the river.", "opta": "Across the river a perfect dam was built.", "optb": "A perfect dam has been built by them across the river.", "optc": "A perfect dam should have been built by them.", "optd": "Across the river was a perfect dam.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Do you imitate others?", "opta": "Are others being imitated by you?", "optb": "Are others imitated by you?", "optc": "Have others being imitated by you?", "optd": "Were others being imitated by you?", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You need to clean your shoes properly.", "opta": "Your shoes are needed to clean properly.", "optb": "You are needed to clean your shoes properly.", "optc": "Your shoes need to be cleaned properly.", "optd": "Your shoes are needed by you to clean properly.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is said to be very rich.", "opta": "He said he is very rich.", "optb": "People say he is very rich.", "optc": "He said it is very rich.", "optd": "People say it is very rich.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The invigilator was reading out the instructions.", "opta": "The instructions were read by the invigilator.", "optb": "The instructions were being read out by the invigilator.", "optc": "The instructions had been read out by the invigilator.", "optd": "The instructions had been read by the invigilator.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You can play with these kittens quite safely.", "opta": "These kittens can played with quite safely.", "optb": "These kittens can play with you quite safely.", "optc": "These kittens can be played with you quite safely.", "optd": "These kittens can be played with quite safely.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A child could not have done this mischief.", "opta": "This mischief could not be done by a child.", "optb": "This mischief could not been done by a child.", "optc": "This mischief could not have been done by a child.", "optd": "This mischief a child could not have been done.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "James Watt discovered the energy of steam.", "opta": "The energy of steam discovered James Watt.", "optb": "The energy of steam was discovered by James Watt.", "optc": "James Watt was discovered by the energy of steam.", "optd": "James Watt had discovered energy by the steam.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She makes cakes every Sunday.", "opta": "Every Sunday cakes made by her.", "optb": "Cakes are made by her every Sunday.", "optc": "Cakes make her every Sunday.", "optd": "Cakes were made by her every Sunday.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She spoke to the official on duty.", "opta": "The official on duty was spoken to by her", "optb": "The official was spoken to by her on duty.", "optc": "She was spoken to by the official on duty.", "optd": "She was the official to be spoken to on duty.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The doctor advised the patient not to eat rice.", "opta": "The patient was advised by the doctor not to eat rice.", "optb": "The patient was advised by the doctor that he should not eat rice.", "optc": "The patient was being advised by the doctor that he should not rice by the doctor.", "optd": "The patient has been advised not to eat rice by the doctor.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I cannot accept your offer.", "opta": "Your offer cannot be accepted by me.", "optb": "I cannot be accepted by your offer.", "optc": "The offer cannot be accepted by me.", "optd": "Your offer cannot be accepted.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You should open the wine about three hours before you use it.", "opta": "Wine should be opened about three hours before use.", "optb": "Wine should be opened by you three hours before use.", "optc": "Wine should be opened about three hours before you use it.", "optd": "Wine should be opened about three hours before it is used.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They will inform the police.", "opta": "The police will be informed by them.", "optb": "The police will inform them.", "optc": "The police are informed by them.", "optd": "Informed will be the police by them.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "it", "optb": "he", "optc": "they", "optd": "we", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "with", "optb": "by", "optc": "after", "optd": "from", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "buy", "optb": "take", "optc": "pick", "optd": "want", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "hardly", "optb": "easily", "optc": "frequently", "optd": "conveniently", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "costs", "optb": "returns", "optc": "dividend", "optd": "prices", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Despite his best efforts to conceal his anger ......", "opta": "we could detect that he was very happy", "optb": "he failed to give us an impression of his agony", "optc": "he succeeded in camouflaging his emotions", "optd": "he could succeed in doing it easily", "opte": "people came to know that he was annoyed", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Even if it rains I shall come means ......", "opta": "if I come it will not rain", "optb": "if it rains I shall not come", "optc": "I will certainly come whether it rains or not", "optd": "whenever there is rain I shall come", "opte": "I am less likely to come if it rains", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "His appearance is unsmiling but ......", "opta": "his heart is full of compassion for others", "optb": "he looks very serious on most occasions", "optc": "people are afraid of him", "optd": "he is uncompromising on matters of task performance", "opte": "he is full of jealousy towards his colleagues", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She never visits any zoo because she is strong opponent of the idea of ......", "opta": "setting the animals free into forest", "optb": "feeding the animals while others are watching", "optc": "watching the animals in their natural abode", "optd": "going out of the house on a holiday", "opte": "holding the animals in captivity for our joy", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I felt somewhat more relaxed ......", "opta": "but tense as compared to earlier", "optb": "and tense as compared to earlier", "optc": "as there was already no tension at all", "optd": "and tension-free as compared to earlier", "opte": "because the worry had already captured by mind", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is not easy to remain tranquil when those around you ......", "opta": "behave in a socially acceptable manner", "optb": "exhibit pleasant mannerism", "optc": "are losing their heads", "optd": "agree to whatever you say", "opte": "exhibit generous and magnanimous gestures", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"The food in this hotel is no match to what were forced at late hours in Hotel Kohinoor \" means ......", "opta": "The food in this hotel is quite good compared to what we ate at kohinoor", "optb": "Hotel kohinoor served us good quality food than what we get here", "optc": "Both hotels have maintained good quality of food", "optd": "Both hotels serve poor quality of food", "opte": "it is better to eat food than remain hungry", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Although initial investigations pointed towards him ......", "opta": "the preceding events corroborated his involvement in the crime", "optb": "the additional information confirmed his guilt", "optc": "the subsequent events established that he was guilt", "optd": "the subsequent events proved that he was innocent", "opte": "he gave an open confession of his crime", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The weather outside was extremely pleasant and hence we decided to ......", "opta": "utilise our time in watching the television", "optb": "refrain from going out for a morning walk", "optc": "enjoy a morning ride in the open", "optd": "employ this rare opportunity for writing letters", "opte": "remain seated in our rooms in the bungalow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"It is an uphill task but you will have to do it\" means ......", "opta": "The work is above the hill and you will have to do it", "optb": "It is a very easy task but you must do it", "optc": "It is very difficult task but you have to do it", "optd": "This work is not reserved for you but you will have to do it", "opte": "It is almost impossible for others but you can do it", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\" You are thinking very highly about Ravi but he is not so\" means ......", "opta": "Ravi is as good as you think about him", "optb": "You have a good opinion about Ravi but he is not as good as you think", "optc": "Your view about Ravi is philosophical, keep it up", "optd": "Ravi is much better, than what you think of him", "opte": "You have a good opinion about Ravi but he does not have a good opinion about you", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Anand stuck up a friendship with Mahesh in just 2 days\" means ......", "opta": "Anand friendship with Mahesh came to an end recently", "optb": "Anand found out the other friends of Mahesh", "optc": "Anand fixed a deal with Mahesh in 2 days", "optd": "Anand's friendship with Mahesh lasted for 2 years", "opte": "Anand became a friend of Mahesh in less than 2 days", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Although, he is reputed for making very candid statements ......", "opta": "his today speech was not fairly audible", "optb": "his promises had always been realistic", "optc": "his speech was very interesting", "optd": "people follow whatever he instructs to them", "opte": "his today's statements were very ambiguous", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The manager would like you to help Dhiraj, means ......", "opta": "the manager would like you if you help Dhiraj", "optb": "the manager desires you to help Dhiraj", "optc": "the manager likes you because you help Dhiraj", "optd": "Dhiraj expects the manager to tell you to help him", "opte": "it will be a help to the manager if you like Dhiraj", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Owing to the acute power shortage, the people of our locality have decided to ......", "opta": "dispense with other non-conventional energy sources", "optb": "resort to abundant use of electricity for illumination", "optc": "off-switch the electrical appliance while not in use", "optd": "explore other avenues for utilising the excess power", "opte": "resort to use of electricity only when it is inevitable", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He has no money now ......", "opta": "although he was very poor once", "optb": "as he has given up all his wealth", "optc": "because he was very rich once", "optd": "because he has received huge donation", "opte": "because he was very greedy about wealth", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is so lazy that he ......", "opta": "cannot depend on others for getting his work done", "optb": "cannot delay the schedule of completing the work", "optc": "can seldom complete his work on time", "optd": "dislike to postpone the work that he undertakes to do", "opte": "always help others to complete their work", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dinesh is as stupid as he is lazy means ......", "opta": "Dinesh is stupid because he is lazy", "optb": "Dinesh is lazy because he is stupid", "optc": "Dinesh is either stupid or lazy", "optd": "Dinesh is hardly stupid but he is lazy", "opte": "Dinesh is equally stupid and lazy", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Practically, very little work could be completed in the last week as it was ......", "opta": "full of working days", "optb": "a very hectic week", "optc": "full of holidays", "optd": "a very busy week", "opte": "loaded with work", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Because he believes in democratic principles, he always ......", "opta": "decides all the matters himself", "optb": "listen to others views and enforces his own", "optc": "shown respect to others opinions if they match his own", "optd": "reconciles with the majority views and gives us his own", "opte": "imposes his own views on others", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With great efforts his son succeeded in convincing him not to donate his entire wealth to an orphanage ......", "opta": "and lead the life of a wealthy merchant", "optb": "but to a home for the forsaken children", "optc": "and make an orphan of himself", "optd": "as the orphanage needed a lot of donations", "opte": "as the orphanage had been set up by him", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The employer appeared to be in such an affable mood that Rohit ......", "opta": "decided to ask for a raise in his salary", "optb": "was scared to talk to him about his leave", "optc": "felt very guilty for his inadvertent slip", "optd": "promised him that he would not commit mistake again", "opte": "was pained to press his demand for a new flat.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He always stammers in public meetings, but his today's speech ......", "opta": "was fairly audible to everyone present in the hall", "optb": "was not received satisfactorily", "optc": "could not be understood properly", "optd": "was not liked by the audience", "opte": "was free from that defect", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Even though it is very large house, ......", "opta": "there is a lot of space available in it for children", "optb": "there is hardly any space available for children", "optc": "there is no dearth of space for children", "optd": "the servants take a long time to clean it", "opte": "the municipal taxes on it are very happy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was an extremely pleasant surprise for the hutment-dweller when the Government officials told him that ......", "opta": "he had to vacate hutment which he had been unauthorisedly occupying", "optb": "he had been gifted with a furnished apartment in a multi-storeyed  building", "optc": "he would be arrested for wrongfully encroaching on the pavement outside his dwelling", "optd": "they would not accede to his request", "opte": "they had received the orders from the court to take possession of all his belongings", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to help the company attain its goal of enhancing profit, all the employees ......", "opta": "urged the management to grant paid leave", "optb": "appealed the management to implement new welfare schemes", "optc": "voluntarily offered to work overtime with lucrative compensation", "optd": "voluntarily offered to render additional services in lieu of nothing", "opte": "decided to enhance production at the cost of quality of the product", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Whatever Dev uttered was without rhyme or reason\" means ......", "opta": "Dev could not recite any poem or speech", "optb": "Dev said something which has no meaning, it was totally baseless", "optc": "Dev was talking something which was beyond our experience", "optd": "Dev spoke flatly without any emotion or reason", "opte": "Dev did not refer to any poem to support his statements", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He tames animals because he ......", "opta": "is fond of them", "optb": "hates them", "optc": "is afraid of them", "optd": "want to set them free", "opte": "seldom loves them", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mahesh need not have purchased the bag, means ......", "opta": "it was not necessary for Mahesh to purchase the bag but he has purchased it", "optb": "it was necessary for Mahesh to purchase the bag and he has not purchased it", "optc": "it was not necessary for Mahesh to purchase the bag and he has not purchased it", "optd": "it was necessary for Mahesh to purchase the bag but he has not purchased it", "opte": "Mahesh already has a bag but still he purchased another one", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In order to raise company's profit, the employees ......", "opta": "demanded two additional increments", "optb": "decided to go on paid holidays", "optc": "requested the management to implement new welfare schemes", "optd": "offered to work overtime without any compensation", "opte": "decided to raise the cost of raw material", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The officer who had neglected to files his income tax returns had to ......", "opta": "return the files", "optb": "pay a fine", "optc": "be rewarded", "optd": "play mischief", "opte": "give warning", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Unless you work harder you will fail, means ......", "opta": "if you fail you will work harder", "optb": "you must at least plan well than you will not fail", "optc": "hardly you will fail if you do not desire so", "optd": "if you do not put more efforts, then you will fail", "opte": "if you only work and work alone, you will fail", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "His behaviour is so unpredictable that he ......", "opta": "never depends upon others for getting his work done", "optb": "is seldom trusted by others", "optc": "always finds it difficult to keep his word", "optd": "always insists on getting the work completed on time", "opte": "seldom trusts others as far as the work schedule is concerned", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The word 'Command Module' used twice in the given passage indicates perhaps that it deals with", "opta": "an alarming journey", "optb": "a commanding situation", "optc": "a journey into outer space", "optd": "a frightful battle.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following reasons would one consider as more as possible for the warning lights to be on?", "opta": "There was a shower of debris.", "optb": "Jack was yelling.", "optc": "A catastrophe was imminent.", "optd": "The moon was looming close and big.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The statement that the dazzling sunshine was \"for once unfiltered by layers of air\" means", "opta": "that the sun was very hot", "optb": "that there was no strong wind", "optc": "that the air was unpolluted", "optd": "none of above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To make clean breast of", "opta": "To gain prominence", "optb": "To praise oneself", "optc": "To confess without of reserve", "optd": "To destroy before it blooms", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To keeps one's temper", "opta": "To become hungry", "optb": "To be in good mood", "optc": "To preserve ones energy", "optd": "To be aloof from", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To catch a tartar", "opta": "To trap wanted criminal with great difficulty", "optb": "To catch a dangerous person", "optc": "To meet with disaster", "optd": "To deal with a person who is more than one's match", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To drive home", "opta": "To find one's roots", "optb": "To return to place of rest", "optc": "Back to original position", "optd": "To emphasise", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To have an axe to grind", "opta": "A private end to serve", "optb": "To fail to arouse interest", "optc": "To have no result", "optd": "To work for both sides", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To cry wolf", "opta": "To listen eagerly", "optb": "To give false alarm", "optc": "To turn pale", "optd": "To keep off starvation", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To end in smoke", "opta": "To make completely understand", "optb": "To ruin oneself", "optc": "To excite great applause", "optd": "To overcome someone", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To be above board", "opta": "To have a good height", "optb": "To be honest in any business deal", "optc": "They have no debts", "optd": "To try to be beautiful", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To put one's hand to plough", "opta": "To take up agricultural farming", "optb": "To take a difficult task", "optc": "To get entangled into unnecessary things", "optd": "Take interest in technical work", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To pick holes", "opta": "To find some reason to quarrel", "optb": "To destroy something", "optc": "To criticise someone", "optd": "To cut some part of an item", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To leave someone in the lurch", "opta": "To come to compromise with someone", "optb": "Constant source of annoyance to someone", "optc": "To put someone at ease", "optd": "To desert someone in his difficulties", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To play second fiddle", "opta": "To be happy, cheerful and healthy", "optb": "To reduce importance of one's senior", "optc": "To support the role and view of another person", "optd": "To do back seat driving", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To beg the question", "opta": "To refer to", "optb": "To take for granted", "optc": "To raise objections", "optd": "To be discussed", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A black sheep", "opta": "An unlucky person", "optb": "A lucky person", "optc": "An ugly person", "optd": "A partner who takes no share of the profits", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "In the English language, 'Black sheep' is an idiom used to describe an odd or disreputable member of a group, especially within a family."}, {"question": "A man of straw", "opta": "A man of no substance", "optb": "A very active person", "optc": "A worthy fellow", "optd": "An unreasonable person", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To smell a rat", "opta": "To see signs of plague epidemic", "optb": "To get bad small of a bad dead rat", "optc": "To suspect foul dealings", "optd": "To be in a bad mood", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To hit the nail right on the head", "opta": "To do the right thing", "optb": "To destroy one's reputation", "optc": "To announce one's fixed views", "optd": "To teach someone a lesson", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "To do exactly the right thing; to do something in the most effective and efficient way."}, {"question": "To set one's face against", "opta": "To oppose with determination", "optb": "To judge by appearence", "optc": "To get out of difficulty", "optd": "To look at one steadily", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Extreme old age when a man behaves like a fool", "opta": "Imbecility", "optb": "Senility", "optc": "Dotage", "optd": "Superannuation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "That which cannot be corrected", "opta": "Unintelligible", "optb": "Indelible", "optc": "Illegible", "optd": "Incorrigible", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Incorrigible (Adjective): (of a person or their tendencies) Not able to be corrected, improved, or reformed."}, {"question": "The study of ancient societies", "opta": "Anthropology", "optb": "Archaeology", "optc": "History", "optd": "Ethnology", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person of good understanding knowledge and reasoning power", "opta": "Expert", "optb": "Intellectual", "optc": "Snob", "optd": "Literate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person who insists on something", "opta": "Disciplinarian", "optb": "Stickler", "optc": "Instantaneous", "optd": "Boaster", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "State in which the few govern the many", "opta": "Monarchy", "optb": "Oligarchy", "optc": "Plutocracy", "optd": "Autocracy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A style in which a writer makes a display of his knowledge", "opta": "Pedantic", "optb": "Verbose", "optc": "Pompous", "optd": "Ornate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "List of the business or subjects to be considered at a meeting", "opta": "Schedule", "optb": "Timetable", "optc": "Agenda", "optd": "Plan", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Leave or remove from a place considered dangerous", "opta": "Evade", "optb": "Evacuate", "optc": "Avoid", "optd": "Exterminate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A prima facie case is such", "opta": "As it seems at first sight", "optb": "As it is made to seem at first sight", "optc": "As it turns out to be at the end", "optd": "As it seems to the court after a number of hearings", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person pretending to be somebody he is not", "opta": "Magician", "optb": "Rogue", "optc": "Liar", "optd": "Imposter", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person who knows many foreign languages", "opta": "Linguist", "optb": "Grammarian", "optc": "Polyglot", "optd": "Bilingual", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who has little faith in human sincerity and goodness", "opta": "Egoist", "optb": "Fatalist", "optc": "Stoic", "optd": "Cynic", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who possesses many talents", "opta": "Versatile", "optb": "Nubile", "optc": "Exceptional", "optd": "Gifted", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Words inscribed on tomb", "opta": "Epitome", "optb": "Epistle", "optc": "Epilogue", "optd": "Epitaph", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who eats everything", "opta": "Omnivorous", "optb": "Omniscient", "optc": "Irrestible", "optd": "Insolvent", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Malafide case is one", "opta": "Which is undertaken in a good faith", "optb": "Which is undertaken in a bad faith", "optc": "Which is undertaken after a long delay", "optd": "Which is not undertaken at all", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The custom or practice of having more than one husband at same time", "opta": "Polygyny", "optb": "Polyphony", "optc": "Polyandry", "optd": "Polychromy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tending to move away from the centre or axis", "opta": "Centrifugal", "optb": "Centripetal", "optc": "Axiomatic", "optd": "Awry", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Teetotaller means", "opta": "One who abstains from theft", "optb": "One who abstains from meat", "optc": "One who abstains from taking wine", "optd": "One who abstains from malice", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person interested in collecting, studying and selling of old things", "opta": "Antiquarian", "optb": "Junk-dealer", "optc": "Crank", "optd": "Archealogist", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A drawing on transparent paper", "opta": "Red print", "optb": "Blue print", "optc": "Negative", "optd": "Transparency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who is not easily pleased by anything", "opta": "Maiden", "optb": "Mediaeval", "optc": "Precarious", "optd": "Fastidious", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A remedy for all diseases", "opta": "Stoic", "optb": "Marvel", "optc": "Panacea", "optd": "Recompense", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who is fond of fighting", "opta": "Bellicose", "optb": "Aggressive", "optc": "Belligerent", "optd": "Militant", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A small shop that sells fashionable clothes, cosmetics, etc.", "opta": "Store", "optb": "Stall", "optc": "Boutique", "optd": "Booth", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "That which cannot be read", "opta": "Negligible", "optb": "Illegible", "optc": "Ineligible", "optd": "Incorrigible", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a state of tension or anxiety or suspense", "opta": "Off balance", "optb": "Depressed", "optc": "Diffused", "optd": "On tenterhooks", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "That which cannot be seen", "opta": "Insensible", "optb": "Intangible", "optc": "Invisible", "optd": "Unseen", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To slap with a flat object", "opta": "Chop", "optb": "Hew", "optc": "Gnaw", "optd": "Swat", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Habitually silent or talking little", "opta": "Servile", "optb": "Unequivocal", "optc": "Taciturn", "optd": "Synoptic", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Taciturn means tending to be silent and uncommunicative, reticent."}, {"question": "One who cannot be corrected", "opta": "Incurable", "optb": "Incorrigible", "optc": "Hardened", "optd": "Invulnerable", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Be the embodiment or perfect example of", "opta": "Characterise", "optb": "Idol", "optc": "Personify", "optd": "Signify", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person not sure of the existence of god", "opta": "Cynic", "optb": "Agnostic", "optc": "Atheist", "optd": "Theist", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A paper written by hand", "opta": "Handicraft", "optb": "Manuscript", "optc": "Handiwork", "optd": "Thesis", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The act of violating the sanctity of the church is", "opta": "Blashphemy", "optb": "Heresy", "optc": "Sacrilege", "optd": "Desecration", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Something that can be heard", "opta": "Auditory", "optb": "Audio-visual", "optc": "Audible", "optd": "Audition", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A name adopted by an author in his writings", "opta": "Nickname", "optb": "Pseudonym", "optc": "Nomenclature", "optd": "Title", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Study of birds", "opta": "Orology", "optb": "Optology", "optc": "Ophthalmology", "optd": "Ornithology", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A place that provides refuge", "opta": "Asylum", "optb": "Sanatorium", "optc": "Shelter", "optd": "Orphanage", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A child born after death of his father", "opta": "Posthumous", "optb": "Orphan", "optc": "Bastard", "optd": "Progenitor", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The absence of law and order", "opta": "Rebellion", "optb": "Anarchy", "optc": "Mutiny", "optd": "Revolt", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The raison d'etre of a controversy is", "opta": "The enthusiasm with which it is kept alive", "optb": "The fitness with which participants handle it", "optc": "The reason or justification of its existence", "optd": "The unending hostility the parties concerned have towards each other", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A place where bees are kept in called", "opta": "An apiary", "optb": "A mole", "optc": "A hive", "optd": "A sanctury", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A religious discourse", "opta": "Preach", "optb": "Stanza", "optc": "Sanctorum", "optd": "Sermon", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A talk on a religious or moral subject, especially one given during a church service and based on a passage from the Bible."}, {"question": "Parts of a country behind the coast or a river's banks", "opta": "Isthmus", "optb": "Archipelago", "optc": "Hinterland", "optd": "Swamps", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Study of the evolution of man as an animal", "opta": "Archaeology", "optb": "Anthropology", "optc": "Chronology", "optd": "Ethnology", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person who speaks many languages", "opta": "Linguist", "optb": "Monolingual", "optc": "Polyglot", "optd": "Bilingual", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who does not believe in existence of god", "opta": "Egoist", "optb": "Atheist", "optc": "Stoic", "optd": "Naive", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A disease of mind causing an uncontrollable desire to steal", "opta": "Schizophrenia", "optb": "Claustrophobia", "optc": "Kleptomania", "optd": "Magolomania", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who sacrifices his life for a cause", "opta": "Patriot", "optb": "Martyr", "optc": "Revolutionary", "optd": "Soldier", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person who brings goods illegally into the country", "opta": "Importer", "optb": "Exporter", "optc": "Fraud", "optd": "Smuggler", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To take secretly in small quantities", "opta": "Robbery", "optb": "Pilferage", "optc": "Theft", "optd": "Defalcation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To accustom oneself to a foreign climate", "opta": "Adapt", "optb": "Adopt", "optc": "Accustom", "optd": "Acclimatise", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who knows everything", "opta": "Literate", "optb": "Scholar", "optc": "Omnipotent", "optd": "Omniscient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Detailed plan of journey", "opta": "Travelogue", "optb": "Travelkit", "optc": "Schedule", "optd": "Itinerary", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Giving undue favours to one's own kith and kin", "opta": "Nepotism", "optb": "Favouritism", "optc": "Wordliness", "optd": "Corruption", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hater of learning and knowledge", "opta": "Misologist", "optb": "Bibliophile", "optc": "Misogynist", "optd": "Misanthropist", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person interested in reading books and nothing else", "opta": "Book-keepr", "optb": "Scholar", "optc": "Book-worm", "optd": "Student", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A place where monks live as a secluded community", "opta": "Cathedral", "optb": "Diocese", "optc": "Convent", "optd": "Monastery", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Incapable of being seen through", "opta": "Ductile", "optb": "Opaque", "optc": "Obsolete", "optd": "Potable", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who does not care for literature or art", "opta": "Primitive", "optb": "Illiterate", "optc": "Philistine", "optd": "Barbarian", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A large sleeping-room with many beds", "opta": "Bedroom", "optb": "Dormitory", "optc": "Hostel", "optd": "Basement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Continuing fight between parties, families, clans, etc.", "opta": "Enmity", "optb": "Feud", "optc": "Quarrel", "optd": "Skirmish", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A building for storing threshed grain", "opta": "Hangar", "optb": "Dockyard", "optc": "Store", "optd": "Granary", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Policeman riding on motorcycles as guards to a VIP", "opta": "Outriders", "optb": "Servants", "optc": "Commandos", "optd": "Attendants", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who is determined to exact full vengeance for wrongs done to him", "opta": "Virulent", "optb": "Vindictive", "optc": "Usurer", "optd": "Vindicator", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Murder of a king", "opta": "Infanticide", "optb": "Matricide", "optc": "Genocide", "optd": "Regicide", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An expression of mild disapproval", "opta": "Warning", "optb": "Denigration", "optc": "Impertinence", "optd": "Reproof", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One absorbed in his own thoughts and feelings rather than in things outside", "opta": "Scholar", "optb": "Recluse", "optc": "Introvert", "optd": "Intellectual", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who dabbles in fine arts for the love of it and not for monetary gains", "opta": "Connoisseur", "optb": "Amateur", "optc": "Professional", "optd": "Dilettante", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A school boy who cuts classes frequently is a", "opta": "Defeatist", "optb": "Sycophant", "optc": "Truant", "optd": "Martinet", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ready to believe", "opta": "Credulous", "optb": "Credible", "optc": "Creditable", "optd": "Incredible", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Medical study of skin and its diseases", "opta": "Dermatology", "optb": "Endocrinology", "optc": "Gynealogy", "optd": "Orthopaedics", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A person who tries to deceive people by claiming to be able to do wonderful things", "opta": "Trickster", "optb": "Imposter", "optc": "Magician", "optd": "Mountebank", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A dramatic performance", "opta": "Mask", "optb": "Mosque", "optc": "Masque", "optd": "Mascot", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who does not marry, especially as a religious obligation", "opta": "Bachelor", "optb": "Celibate", "optc": "Vigin", "optd": "Recluse", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "That which is perceptible by touch is", "opta": "Contagious", "optb": "Contingent", "optc": "Tenacious", "optd": "Tangible", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Very pleasing to eat", "opta": "Appetising", "optb": "Palatable", "optc": "Tantalising", "optd": "Sumptuous", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The part of government which is concerned with making of rules", "opta": "Court", "optb": "Tribunal", "optc": "Bar", "optd": "Legislature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who believes that all things and events in life are predetermined is a", "opta": "Fatalist", "optb": "Puritan", "optc": "Egoist", "optd": "Tyrant", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Something that relates to everyone in the world", "opta": "General", "optb": "Common", "optc": "Usual", "optd": "Universal", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To walk with slow or regular Steps is to", "opta": "Limp", "optb": "Stride", "optc": "Pace", "optd": "Advance", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A style full of words", "opta": "Verbose", "optb": "Pedantic", "optc": "Rhetorical", "optd": "Abundant", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Murder of a brother", "opta": "Patricide", "optb": "Regicide", "optc": "Homicide", "optd": "Fratricide", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Having superior or intellectual interests and tastes", "opta": "Elite", "optb": "Highbrow", "optc": "Sophisticated", "optd": "Fastidious", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To cause troops, etc. to spread out in readiness for battle", "opta": "Disperse", "optb": "Deploy", "optc": "Collocate", "optd": "Align", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A voice loud enough to be heard", "opta": "Audible", "optb": "Applaudable", "optc": "Laudable", "optd": "Oral", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A light sailing boat built specially for racing", "opta": "Canoe", "optb": "Yacht", "optc": "Frigate", "optd": "Dinghy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who is in charge of museum", "opta": "Curator", "optb": "Supervisor", "optc": "Caretaker", "optd": "Warden", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A government by the nobles", "opta": "Aristocracy", "optb": "Democracy", "optc": "Autocracy", "optd": "Bureaucracy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One who is honourably discharged from service", "opta": "Retired", "optb": "Emeritus", "optc": "Relieved", "optd": "Emancipated", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Present opposing arguments or evidence", "opta": "Criticise", "optb": "Rebuff", "optc": "Reprimand", "optd": "Rebut", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The policy of extending a country's empire and influence", "opta": "Communism", "optb": "Internationalism", "optc": "Capitalism", "optd": "Imperialism", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Of outstanding significance", "opta": "Monumental", "optb": "Rational", "optc": "Ominous", "optd": "Evident", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Code of diplomatic etiquette and precedence", "opta": "Statesmanship", "optb": "Formalism", "optc": "Hierarchy", "optd": "Protocol", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A fixed orbit in space in relation to earth", "opta": "Geological", "optb": "Geo-synchronous", "optc": "Geo-centric", "optd": "Geo-stationary", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "That which cannot be believed", "opta": "Incredible", "optb": "Incredulous", "optc": "Implausible", "optd": "Unreliable", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To issue a thunderous verbal attack", "opta": "Languish", "optb": "Animate", "optc": "Fulminate", "optd": "Invigorate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIn the middle of one side of the square sits the Chairman of the committee, the most important person in the room.\n\n\nP :\nFor a committee is not just a mere collection of individuals.\n\n\nQ :\nOn him rests much of the responsibility for the success or failure of the committee.\n\n\nR :\nWhile this is happening we have an opportunity to get the 'feel' of this committe.\n\n\nS :\nAs the meeting opens, he runs briskly through a number of formalities.\n\n\nS6:\nFrom the moment its members meet, it begins to have a sort nebulous life of its own.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "PQRS", "optc": "SQPR", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA force of exists between everybody in the universe.\n\n\nP :\nNormally it is very small but when the one of the bodies is a planet, like earth, the force is considerable.\n\n\nQ :\nIt has been investigated by many scientists including Galileo and Newton.\n\n\nR :\nEverything on or near the surface of the earth is attracted by the mass of earth.\n\n\nS :\nThis gravitational force depends on the mass of the bodies involved.\n\n\nS6:\nThe greater the mass, the greater is the earth's force of attraction on it. We can call this force of attraction gravity.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRQS", "optb": "PRSQ", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "QSPR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nCalcutta unlike other cities kepts its trams.\n\n\nP :\nAs a result there horrendous congestion.\n\n\nQ :\nIt was going to be the first in South Asia.\n\n\nR :\nThey run down the centre of the road\n\n\nS :\nTo ease in the city decided to build an underground railway line.\n\n\nS6:\nThe foundation stone was laid in 1972.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nFor some time in his youth Abraham Lincoln was manager for a shop.\n\n\nP :\nThen a chance Customer would come.\n\n\nQ :\nYoung Lincoln way of keeping shop was entirely unlike anyone else's\n\n\nR :\nLincoln would jump up and attend to his needs and then revert to his reading.\n\n\nS :\nHe used to lie full length on the counter of the shop eagerly reading a book.\n\n\nS6:\nNever before had Lincoln had so much time for reading as had then.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAll the land was covered by the ocean.\n\n\nP :\nThe leading god fought the monster, killed it and chopped its body in to two halves.\n\n\nQ :\nA terrible monster prevented the gods from separating the land from the water.\n\n\nR :\nThe god made the sky out of the upper part of the body and ornamented it with stars.\n\n\nS :\nThe god created the earth from the lower part, grew plants on it and populated it with animals.\n\n\nS6:\nThe god moulded the first people out of clay according to his own image and mind.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSmoke oozed up between the planks.\n\n\nP :\nPassengers were told to be ready to quit the ship.\n\n\nQ :\nThe rising gale fanned the smouldering fire.\n\n\nR :\nEveryone now knew there was fire on board.\n\n\nS :\nFlames broke out here and there.\n\n\nS6:\nMost people bore the shock bravely.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nYou know my wife, Madhavi, always urged me to give up smoking.\n\n\nP :\nI really gave it up.\n\n\nQ :\nAnd so When I went to jail I said to myself I really must give it up, if for no other reason than of being self-reliant.\n\n\nR :\nWhen I emerged from jail, I wanted to tell her of my great triumph.\n\n\nS :\nBut when I met her, there she was with a packet of cigarettes.\n\n\nS6:\npoor girl!.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWhen a satellite is launched, the rocket begins by going slowly upwards through the air.\n\n\nP :\nHowever, the higher it goes, the less air it meets.\n\n\nQ :\nAs the rocket goes higher, it travels faster.\n\n\nR :\nFor the atmosphere becomes thinner.\n\n\nS :\nAs a result there is less friction.\n\n\nS6:\nConsequently, the rocket still does not become too hot.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "PQRS", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA father having offered to take the baby out in a perambulator, was tempted by the sunny morning to slip into a pub for a glass of beer.\n\n\nP :\nIndignant at her husband's behaviour, she decided to teach him a lesson.\n\n\nQ :\nShe wheeled away the pram.\n\n\nR :\nA little later, his wife came by, where to her horror, she discovered her sleeping baby.\n\n\nS :\nLeaving the pram outside, he disappeared inside the bar.\n\n\nS6:\nShe waited for him, anticipating the white face and quivering lips which would soon appear with the news that the baby had been stolen.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "RQPS", "optc": "SPQR", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe city is almost a slum and stinks most of time.\n\n\nP :\nThe slush on the road did not deter them.\n\n\nQ :\nThe occasional slips and falls were considered a small price to pay for the trip.\n\n\nR :\nThey were excited, fascinated by the sight of fresh snow on the roads.\n\n\nS :\nEven so, it looked beautiful to tourists of various categories.\n\n\nS6:\nBut some visitors came away with the unforgettable sight of young labours scantily clad.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQPS", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nVenice is a strange and beautiful city in the north of Italy.\n\n\nP :\nThere are about four hundred old stone bridges joining the island of Venice.\n\n\nQ :\nIn this city there are no motor cars, no horses, no buses.\n\n\nR :\nThese small islands are near one another.\n\n\nS :\nIt is not an island but a hundred and seventeen islands.\n\n\nS6:\nThis is because Venice has no streets.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PRQS", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe Hound of Baskervilles was feared by the people of the area.\n\n\nP :\nSome people spoke of seeing a huge, shadowy form a Hound at midnight on the moor.\n\n\nQ :\nBut they spoke of it in tones of horror.\n\n\nR :\nNobody had actually seen the hound.\n\n\nS :\nThis shadowy form did not reveal any details about the animal.\n\n\nS6:\nThe Hound of Baskervilles remains an unsolved mystery.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPQR", "optb": "SPRQ", "optc": "PSRQ", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA gentleman who lived alone always had two plates placed on the table at dinner time.\n\n\nP :\nOne day just as he sat down to dine, the cat rushed in to the room.\n\n\nQ :\nOne plate was for himself and other was for his cat.\n\n\nR :\nshe drooped a mouse into her own plate and another into her master plate.\n\n\nS :\nHe used to give the cat a piece of meat from his own plate.\n\n\nS6:\nIn this way the cat showed her gratitude to her master.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSPR", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "RPQS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAnts eat worms, centipedes and spiders.\n\n\nP :\nThey are usually much quicker than the ant itself.\n\n\nQ :\nNevertheless, these animals do not make easy game for ants.\n\n\nR :\nBesides, they have an extraordinary number of ways of escaping.\n\n\nS :\nThey also eat larvae and insect adults such as flies, moths and spring tails.\n\n\nS6:\nSome jump, and some give out a pungent repellent substance.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "SPRQ", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "SRQP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSatyajit Ray made several films for children.\n\n\nP :\nLater film makers have followed his lead.\n\n\nQ :\nToday other nations are making the children's film in a big way.\n\n\nR :\nThis was at a time when no director considered children as potential audience.\n\n\nS :\nRay was, thus, a pioneer in the field.\n\n\nS6:\nBut today few think of Ray as a maker of children's films.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nHungary, with a population of about 10 million, lies between Czechoslovakia to the north and Yugoslavia to the south.\n\n\nP :\nHere a great deal of grain is grown.\n\n\nQ :\nIn recent years, however, progress has been made also in the field of industrialisation.\n\n\nR :\nMost of this country consists of an extremely fertile plain, through which the river Danube flows.\n\n\nS :\nIn addition to grain, the plain produces potatoes, sugar, wine and livestock.\n\n\nS6:\nThe new industries derive mainly from agricultural production.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "RQSP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nPalaeobotany is the study of fossil plants preserved in rocks dating back in millions of years.\n\n\nP :\nRecords of the history of the world are contained in fossils.\n\n\nQ :\nThrough the ages, plants have evolved from simple to more complex forms.\n\n\nR :\nFirst there were water plants then land plants appeared during the Paleozoic era.\n\n\nS :\nBut since the fossil remains appear locked in rock layers, they are closely related to the geologist area of investigation.\n\n\nS6:\nThe fossil plants indicate the age of the rock, and also point to facts regarding climate, temperature and topography.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQSP", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "PSQR", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOn vacation in Tangier, Morocco, my friend and I sat down at a street cafe.\n\n\nP :\nAt one point, he bent over with a big smile, showing me, a single gold tooth and a dingy fez.\n\n\nQ :\nsoon I felt the presence of someone standing alongside me.\n\n\nR :\nBut this one wouldn't budge.\n\n\nS :\nWe had been cautioned about beggars and were told to ignore them.\n\n\nS6:\nFinally a man walked over to me and whispered, \"Hey buddy this guy is your waiter and he wants your order\"\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQRP", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "QSPR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAnd then Gandhi came.\n\n\nP :\nGet off the backs of these peasants and workers, he told us, all you who live by their exploitation.\n\n\nQ :\nHe was like a powerful current of fresh air, like a beam of light, like a whirlwind that upset many things.\n\n\nR :\nHe spoke their language and constantly dre their attention to their appalling conditions.\n\n\nS :\nHe didn't descent from the top, he seemed to emerge from the masses of India.\n\n\nS6:\nPolitical freedom took new shape and then acquired a new content.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "PRSQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nBiological evolution has not fitted man to any specific environment.\n\n\nP :\nIt is by no means a biological evolution, but it is a cultural one.\n\n\nQ :\nHis imagination, his reason, his emotional subtlety and toughness, makes it possible for him not to accept the environment but to change.\n\n\nR :\nAnd that series of inventions by which man from age by age has reshaped his environment is a different kind of evolution.\n\n\nS :\nAmong the multitude of animals which scamper, burrow swim around us he is in the only one who is not locked in to his environment.\n\n\nS6:\nThat brilliant sequence of cultural peaks can most appropriately be termed the ascent of man.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe dictionary is the best friend of you task.\n\n\nP :\nThat may not be possible always.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is wise to look it up immediately.\n\n\nR :\nThen it must be firmly written on the memory and traced at the first opportunity.\n\n\nS :\nNever allow a strange word to pass unchallenged.\n\n\nS6:\nsoon you will realize that this is an exciting task.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "SQPR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe Bhagavadgita recognises the nature of man and the needs of man.\n\n\nP :\nAll these three aspects constitute the nature of man.\n\n\nQ :\nIt shows how the human being is rational one, an ethical one and a spiritual one.\n\n\nR :\nMore than all, it must be a spiritual experience.\n\n\nS :\nNothing can give him fulfilment unless it satisfies his reason, his ethical conscience.\n\n\nS6:\nA man whom does not harmonise them, is not truly human.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "RSPQ", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "PSQR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI usually sleep quite well in the train, but this time I slept only a little.\n\n\nP :\nMost people wanted it shut and I wanted it open.\n\n\nQ :\nAs usual, I got angry about the window.\n\n\nR :\nThe quarrel left me completely upset.\n\n\nS :\nThere were too many people too much huge luggage all around.\n\n\nS6:\nIt was shut all night, as usual\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIn 1934, William Golding published a small volume of poems.\n\n\nP :\nDuring the World War II(1939-45) he joined the Royal Navy and was present at the sinking of the Bismarck.\n\n\nQ :\nHe returned to teaching in 1945 and gave it up in 1962, and is now a full time writer.\n\n\nR :\nIn 1939, he married and started teaching at Vishop Wordsworth school in Salisbury.\n\n\nS :\nAt first his novels were not accepted.\n\n\nS6:\nBut the Lord of the files which came out in 1954 was welcomed as \"a most absorbing and instructive tale\".\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "SQPR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe future beckons to us.\n\n\nP :\nIn fact we have hard work ahead.\n\n\nQ :\nWhere do we go and what shall be our endeavour?\n\n\nR :\nWe shall also have to fight and end poverty, ignorance and disease.\n\n\nS :\nIt will be to bring freedom and oppurtunity to the common man.\n\n\nS6:\nThere is no resting for any one of us till we redeem our pledge in full.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMost of the universities in the country are now facing financial crisis.\n\n\nP :\nCost benefit yardstick thus should not be applied in the case of universities.\n\n\nQ :\nThe current state of affairs cannot be allowed to continue for long.\n\n\nR :\nUniversities cannot be equated with commercial enterprises.\n\n\nS :\nProper development of universities and colleges must be ensured.\n\n\nS6:\nThe Government should realise this before it is too late.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWhile talking to a group, one should feel self-confident and courageous.\n\n\nP :\nNor is it a gift bestowed by providence on only a few.\n\n\nQ :\nOne should also learn how to think calmly and clearly.\n\n\nR :\nIt is like the ability to play golf.\n\n\nS :\nIt is not as difficult as most men imagine.\n\n\nS6:\nAny man can develop his capacity if he has  the desire to do so.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "RSQP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA ceiling on urban property.\n\n\nP :\nNo mill-owner could own factories or mills or plants.\n\n\nQ :\nAnd mass circulation papers\n\n\nR :\nWould mean that\n\n\nS :\nNo press magnate could own printing presses.\n\n\nS6:\nsince their value would exceed the ceiling fixed by the government.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe art of growing old is one which the passage of time has forced upon my attention.\n\n\nP :\nOne of these is undue absorption in the past.\n\n\nQ :\nOne's thought must be directed to the future and to things about which there is something to be done.\n\n\nR :\nPsychologically, there are two dangers to be guarded against in old age.\n\n\nS :\nIt does not do to live in memories, in regrets for the good old days, or in sadness about friend who are dead.\n\n\nS6:\nThis is not always easy one's own past is gradually increasing weight.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "RPSQ", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI keep on flapping my big ears all day.\n\n\nP :\nThey also fear that I will flip them all away.\n\n\nQ :\nBut children wonder why I flap them so.\n\n\nR :\nI flap them so to make sure they are safely there on either side of my head.\n\n\nS :\nBut I know what I am doing.\n\n\nS6:\nAm I not a smart, intelligent elephant?\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOnce King Shantnu met a young and beautiful fisher girl.\n\n\nP :\nHe went to the fisherman and asked him for her asked him for her hand in marriage.\n\n\nQ :\nThe King was extremely sad and returned to his palace.\n\n\nR :\nHe fell in love with the fisher girl.\n\n\nS :\nThe fisherman agreed to it condition that the son of his daughter should be heir to the throne of Hastinapur.\n\n\nS6:\nDevavrata, the King's son, asked him the reason of his sadness.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PSQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nReliogion is not a matter of mere dogmatic conformity.\n\n\nP :\nIt is not merely going through the ritual prescribed to us.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is not a question of ceremonial piety.\n\n\nR :\nUnless that kind of transformation occurs, you are not an authentically religious man.\n\n\nS :\nIt is the remarking of your own self, the transformation of your nature.\n\n\nS6:\nA man of that character is free from fear, free from hatred.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPRQ", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "PSRQ", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWe speak today of self-determination in politics.\n\n\nP :\nSo long as one is conscious of a restraint, it is possible to resist it or to near it as a necessary evil and to keep free in spirit.\n\n\nQ :\nSlavery begins when one ceases to feel that restraint and it depends on if the evil is accepted as good.\n\n\nR :\nThere is, however, a subtler domination exercised in the sphere of ideas by one culture to another.\n\n\nS :\nPolitical subjection primarily means restraint on the outer life of people.\n\n\nS6:\nCultural subjection is ordinarily of an unconscious character and it implies slavery from the very start.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPRQ", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "SPQR", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOnce upon a time an ant lived on the bank of river.\n\n\nP :\nThe dove saw the ant struggling in water in a helpless condition.\n\n\nQ :\nAll its efforts to come up is failed.\n\n\nR :\nOne day it suddenly slipped in to water.\n\n\nS :\nA dove lived in the tree on the bank not far from the spot.\n\n\nS6:\nShe was touched.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQSP", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe December dance and music season in Madras is like the annual tropical cyclone.\n\n\nP :\nA few among the new aspirants dazzle witht he colour of youth, like fresh saplings.\n\n\nQ :\nIt rains an abundance of music for over a fortnight.\n\n\nR :\nThick clouds expectation charge the atmosphere with voluminous advertisements.\n\n\nS :\nAt the end of it one is left with the feeling that the music of only those artists seasoned by careful nurturing, stands tall like well-routed trees.\n\n\nS6:\nMany a hastily planed shrub gets washed away in the storm.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQPS", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "RQSP", "optd": "QRSP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThere is a touching story of Professor Hardy visiting Ramanujan as he lay desperately ill in hospital at Putney.\n\n\nP :\n'No Hardy, that is not a dull number in the very least.\n\n\nQ :\nHardy, who was a very shy man, could not find the words for his distress.\n\n\nR :\nIt was 1729.\n\n\nS :\nThe best he could do, as he got to the beside was \"I say Ramanujan, I thought the number of taxi I came down in was a very dull number\"\n\n\nS6:\nIt is the lowest number that can be expressed in two different ways as the sum of two cubes.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "QSRP", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nPoliteness is not a quality possessed by only one nation or race.\n\n\nP :\nOne may observe that a man of one nation will remove his hat or fold his hands by way of greetings when he meets someone he knows.\n\n\nQ :\nA man of another country will not to do so.\n\n\nR :\nIt is a quality to be found among all peoples and nations in every corner of the earth.\n\n\nS :\nObviously, each person follows the custom of his particular country.\n\n\nS6:\nIn any case, we should not mock at others habits.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "PRQS", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThroughout history man has used energy from the sun.\n\n\nP :\nToday, when we burn wood or use electric current we are drawing an energy.\n\n\nQ :\nHowever we now have a new supply of energy.\n\n\nR :\nAll our ordinary life depends on sun.\n\n\nS :\nThis has come from the sun.\n\n\nS6:\nThis energy comes from inside atoms.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "RQPS", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThis weather-vane often tops a church spire, tower or high building.\n\n\nP :\nThey are only wind-vanes.\n\n\nQ :\nNeither alone can tell us what the weather will be.\n\n\nR :\nThey are designed to point to direction from which the wind is coming.\n\n\nS :\nJust as the barometer only tells us the pressure of air, the weather-vane tells us the direction of wind.\n\n\nS6:\nThe weather-vane can, however give us some indication of other.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nBut how does a new word get into the dictionary?\n\n\nP :\nWhen a new dictionary is being edited, a lexicographer collects all the alphabetically arranged citation slips for a particular word.\n\n\nQ :\nThe dictionary makers notice it and make a note of it on a citation slip.\n\n\nR :\nThe moment new word is coined, it usually enter the spoken language.\n\n\nS :\nThe word then passes from the realm of hearing to the realm of writing.\n\n\nS6:\nHe sorts them according to their grammatical function, and carefully writes a definition.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PRSQ", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "RSQP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nGrowing up means not only getting larger, but also using our sense and our brain is to become more aware of things around us.\n\n\nP :\nNot only does he have a memory but he is able to think and reason.\n\n\nQ :\nIn this, man differs from all other animals.\n\n\nR :\nBefore we spray our roadside plants or turn sewage in to our rivers, we should pause to think what the results of our action are likely to do.\n\n\nS :\nThis is to say, he is able to plan what he is is going to do in the light of his experience before he does it.\n\n\nS6:\nIn other words, we must develop and use our ability to reason, because the destruction or the preservation of the places in which we live depend on us.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "SPRQ", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nJawaharlal Nehru was the greatest plan-enthusiast.\n\n\nP :\nUnder Nehru's advice, the pre-Independent congress set up National Planning Commission in 1938.\n\n\nQ :\nBut he forgot that what could be achieved by force under the communist dictatorship of Russia was not possible under the democratic set up of India.\n\n\nR :\nHe took the idea from Russia where Five year plans transformed a very backward country into a top power of the world.\n\n\nS :\nNo free government can call for compulsory sacrifice and suffering from the whole people.\n\n\nS6:\nNehru himself became the chairman of the commission.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "RQSP", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nDuryodhana was a wicked prince.\n\n\nP :\none day Bhima made Duryodhana fall from a tree from which Duryodhana was stealing fruits.\n\n\nQ :\nHe did not like that Pandavas should be loved and respected by the people of Hastinapur\n\n\nR :\nDuryodhana specially hated Bhima.\n\n\nS :\nAmong the Pandavas, Bhima was extraordinary strong and powerful\n\n\nS6:\nThis enraged Duryodhana so much that he began to think of removing Bhima from his way.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nJawaharlal Nehru was born in Allahabad on 14 Nov 1889.\n\n\nP :\nNehru meet Mahatma Gandhi in February 1920.\n\n\nQ :\nIn 1905 he was sent to London to study at a school called Haroow.\n\n\nR :\nHe became the first Prime Minister of Independent India on 15 August 1947.\n\n\nS :\nHe married Kamla Kaul in 1915.\n\n\nS6:\nHe died on 27 May 1964.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "RPQS", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIt was a dark moonless night.\n\n\nP :\nHe turned over the pages, reading passages here and there.\n\n\nQ :\nHe heard them on the floor.\n\n\nR :\nThe poet took down his books of poems from his shelves.\n\n\nS :\nSome of them contained his earliest writings which he had almost forgotten.\n\n\nS6:\nThey all seemed to him to be poor and ordinary mere childish words.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "RQSP", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI had halted on the road.\n\n\nP :\nAs soon as I saw the elephant I knew I should not shoot him.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is a serious matter to shoot a working elephant.\n\n\nR :\nI knew that his 'must' was already passing off.\n\n\nS :\nThe elephant was standing 8 yards from the road.\n\n\nS6:\nI decided to watch him for a while and then go home.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPQR", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThere is only one monkey we can thoroughly recommend as an indoor pet.\n\n\nP :\nThey quickly die from colds and coughs after the first winter fogs.\n\n\nQ :\nIt is beautiful and intelligent Capuchin monkey.\n\n\nR :\nThe lively little Capuchins, however, may be left for years in an English house without the least danger to their health.\n\n\nS :\nThe Marmosets, it is true, are more beautiful than a Capuchins and just as pleasing, but they are too delicate for the English climate\n\n\nS6:\nFinally let me say that no other monkey has a better temper or winning ways.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA man can be physically confined within stone walls.\n\n\nP :\nBut his mind and spirit will still be free.\n\n\nQ :\nThus his freedom of action may be restricted.\n\n\nR :\nHis hopes and aspiration still remain with him.\n\n\nS :\nHence, he will be free spiritually if not physically.\n\n\nS6:\nNo tyranny can intimidate a lover of liberty.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "SRQP", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOnce upon atime there lived three young men in a certain town of Hindustan.\n\n\nP :\nAll the people of the neighbourhood were mortally afraid of them.\n\n\nQ :\nThey were so powerful that they could catch growing lions and tear them to pieces.\n\n\nR :\nSomeone told them that they would become immortal if they killed Death.\n\n\nS :\nThe young men believed themselves to be very good friends.\n\n\nS6:\nAll of them set out in search of their foe called Death.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMetals are today being replaced by polymers in many applications.\n\n\nP :\nAbove all, they are cheaper and easier to process making them a viable alternative to metals.\n\n\nQ :\nPolymers are essentially a long chains of hydrocarbon molecules.\n\n\nR :\nToday polymers as strong as metals have been developed.\n\n\nS :\nThese have replaced the traditional chromium-plated metallic bumpers in cars.\n\n\nS6:\nMany Indian Institutes of science and Technology run special programmes on polymer science.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "RQSP", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSince the sixties there has been an increasing interest in neurophysiology, which deals with the neural bases of mental activity and behaviour.\n\n\nP :\nIt has format which is very similar to that of Brain and Language, a sister journal.\n\n\nQ :\nSince then, a number of journals devoted entirely to this area of research have appeared.\n\n\nR :\nBefore the 1960's when this field was the concern of a small number of investigators, research articles were scattered in various neurological journals.\n\n\nS :\nBrain and cognition is one such journal.\n\n\nS6:\nSo far the journal has published the mixture of articles including reports and investigations.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQSP", "optb": "QRSP", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAn elderly lady suddenly became blind.\n\n\nP :\nThe doctor called daily and every time he took away some of her furniture he liked.\n\n\nQ :\nAt last she was cured and the doctor demanded his fee.\n\n\nR :\nShe agreed to pay a large fee to the doctor who would cure her\n\n\nS :\nOn being refused, the doctor wanted to know the reason.\n\n\nS6:\nThe lady said that she had not been properly cured because she could not see all his furniture.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWhat are the causes of our chronic food shortage ?\n\n\nP :\nTo find for these growing new millions is desperate task.\n\n\nQ :\nevery year, we add more than a crore of persons to our population.\n\n\nR :\nDespite stupendous efforts by our government, the population is growing unabated.\n\n\nS :\nThe chief cause is the population explosion.\n\n\nS6:\nThis unprecedented growth can drag us to the doors of starvation very soon.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PSQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nOur ancestors thought that anything which moved itself was alive.\n\n\nP :\nThe philosopher Descartes thought that both men and animals were machines.\n\n\nQ :\nBut a machine such as a motorcar or a steamship moves itself, as soon as machines which moved themselves had been made, people asked \"Is man a machine?\"\n\n\nR :\nAnd before the days of machinery that was a good definition.\n\n\nS :\nHe also thought that the human machine was partly controlled by the soul action on a certain part of the brain, while animals had no souls.\n\n\nS6:\nTherefore some scientists think that life is just a very complicated mechanism.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "PSQR", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nPayment for imports and exports is made through a system called foreign exchange.\n\n\nP :\nThe value of the money of one country in relation to the money of other countries is agreed upon.\n\n\nQ :\nThese rates of exchange vary from time to time.\n\n\nR :\nFor instance, an American dollar or a British pound sterling is worth certain amounts in the money of other countries.\n\n\nS :\nSometimes a United States dollar is worth 12 pesos in Mexico.\n\n\nS6:\nAnother time it may be worth eight pesos.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "PRQS", "optd": "RPQS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMoncure Conway devoted his life to two great objects freedom of thought, and freedom of the individual.\n\n\nP :\nThey threaten both kinds of freedom.\n\n\nQ :\nBut something also has been lost.\n\n\nR :\nThere are now dangers, somewhat different in form from those of the past ages.\n\n\nS :\nIn regard to both these objects, something has been gained since his time.\n\n\nS6:\nUnless a vigorous and vigilant public opinion can be aroused in defence of them, there will be much less of both a hundred years hence then there is now.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe study of speech disorders due to brain injury suggests that patients can think without having adequate control over their language.\n\n\nP :\nBut they succeed in playing games of chess.\n\n\nQ :\nSome patients, for example fail to find the names of objects presented to them.\n\n\nR :\nThey can even use the concepts needed for chess playing, though they are unable to express many of the concepts in ordinary language.\n\n\nS :\nThey even find it difficult to interpret long written notices.\n\n\nS6:\nHow they manage to do this we do not know.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA black haired, young woman came tripping along.\n\n\nP :\nShe was leading a young woman wearing a hat.\n\n\nQ :\nThe woman swept it off and tossed it in the air.\n\n\nR :\nThe child jumped up to catch the hat.\n\n\nS :\nThe young man tossed his head to shake the hat back.\n\n\nS6:\nBoth disappeared from view.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nWe now know that the oceans are very deep.\n\n\nP :\nFor example, the Indian ocean has a range called the Indian Ridge.\n\n\nQ :\nMuch of it is fairly flat.\n\n\nR :\nHowever, there are great mountain ranges as well.\n\n\nS :\nOn average the bottom is 2.5 miles to 3.5 miles down\n\n\nS6:\nThis reaches from the India to the Antarctic.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMinnie went shopping one morning.\n\n\nP :\nDisappointed She turned around and returned to the parking lot.\n\n\nQ :\nShe got out and walked to the nearest shop.\n\n\nR :\nShe drove her car into the parking lot and stopped.\n\n\nS :\nIt was there that she realised that she'd forgotten her purse at home.\n\n\nS6:\nShe drove home with an empty basket.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "RQSP", "optc": "PQRS", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nFar away in a little street there is a poor house.\n\n\nP :\nHer face is thin and worn and her hands are coarse, pricked by a needle, for she is a seam stress.\n\n\nQ :\nOne of the windows is open and through it I can see a poor woman.\n\n\nR :\nHe has a fever and asking for oranges.\n\n\nS :\nIn a bed in a corner of the room her little boy is lying ill.\n\n\nS6:\nHis mother has nothing to give but water, so he is crying.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "PQSR", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nA noise started above their heads.\n\n\nP :\nBut people did not take it seriously.\n\n\nQ :\nThat was to show everyone that there was something wrong\n\n\nR :\nIt was a dangerous thing to do.\n\n\nS :\nFor, within minutes the ship began to sink.\n\n\nS6:\nNearly 200 lives were lost on the fateful day.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQSR", "optb": "PRQS", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAmerican private lies may seem shallow.\n\n\nP :\nStudents would walk away with books they had not paid for.\n\n\nQ :\nA Chinese journalist commented on a curious institution: the library\n\n\nR :\nTheir public morality, however, impressed visitors.\n\n\nS :\nBut in general they returned them.\n\n\nS6:\nThis would not happen in china, he said.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe path of Venus lies inside the path of the Earth.\n\n\nP :\nWhen at its farthest from the Earth, Venus is 160 million away\n\n\nQ :\nWith such a wide range between its greatest and leat distances it is natural that at sometimes Venus appears much brighter than at others.\n\n\nR :\nNo other body ever comes so near the Earth, with the exception of the Moon and occasional comet or asteroid.\n\n\nS :\nWhen Venus is at its nearest to the earth it is only 26 million miles away.\n\n\nS6:\nWhen at its brightest, it is easily seen with the naked eye in broad daylight.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "PSQR", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIn India marriages are usually arranged by parents\n\n\nP :\nSometimes boys and girls do not like th idea of arranged marriages.\n\n\nQ :\nMost young people accepts the state of affairs.\n\n\nR :\nShanta was like that.\n\n\nS :\nThey assume their parents can make good choices.\n\n\nS6:\nShe felt she was a modern girl and not subject for bargaining.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPRQ", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nShe said on the phone that she would report for duty next day.\n\n\nP :\nWe waited for few days then we decided to go to her place.\n\n\nQ :\nBut she did not.\n\n\nR :\nwe found it locked.\n\n\nS :\nEven after that we waited for her quite a few days.\n\n\nS6:\nEventually we reported to the police.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "SQPR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSeveral sub-cities have been planned around capital.\n\n\nP :\nDwarga is the first among them.\n\n\nQ :\nThey are expected to alleviate the problem of housing.\n\n\nR :\nIt is coming up in the south west of capital.\n\n\nS :\nIt will cater to over one million people when completed.\n\n\nS6:\nHopefully the housing problem will not be as acute at present after these sub-cities are built.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "PRSQ", "optc": "PQRS", "optd": "QRSP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nForecasting the weather has always been a difficult business.\n\n\nP :\nDuring a period of drought, streams and rivers dried up, the cattle died from thirst and were ruined.\n\n\nQ :\nMany different things affect the weather and we have to study them carefully to make accurate forecast.\n\n\nR :\nAncient Egyptians had no need of weather in the  Nile Valley hardly ever changes.\n\n\nS :\nIn early times, when there were no instruments, such as thermometer or the barometer, man looked for tell-tale signs in the sky.\n\n\nS6:\nHe made his forecasts by watching flights of the birds or the way smoke rose from fire.\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRQS", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nAs he passed beneath her he heard the swish of her wings.\n\n\nP :\nHe was not falling head long now.\n\n\nQ :\nThe monstrous terror seized him.\n\n\nR :\nBut it only lasted a minute.\n\n\nS :\nHe could hear nothing.\n\n\nS6:\nThe next moment he felt his wings spread outwards.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "PRQS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nMs. Parasuram started a Petrol Pump in Madras.\n\n\nP :\nA total to 12 girls now work at the pump.\n\n\nQ :\nShe advertised in newspapers for women staff.\n\n\nR :\nThey operate in 2 shifts.\n\n\nS :\nThe response was good.\n\n\nS6:\nThus she has shown the way for many others.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQSR", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nSun birds are among the smallest of Indian birds.\n\n\nP :\nThough they are functionally similar to the humming birds of the New World, they are totally unrelated.\n\n\nQ :\nThey do eat insects too.\n\n\nR :\nThey are also some of the most brilliantly coloured birds.\n\n\nS :\nsun birds feed on nectar mostly and helped in pollination.\n\n\nS6:\nOur common sun birds are the purple sun bird, the glossy black species and purple rumped sun bird, the yellow and maroon species.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nFor decades, American society has been calling a melting pot\n\n\nP :\nDifferences remained - in appearence, mannerisms, customs, speech, religion and more.\n\n\nQ :\nThe term has long been a cliche and half-truth.\n\n\nR :\nBut homogenisation was never acheived.\n\n\nS :\nYes, immigrants from diverse cultures and traditions did cast off vestiges of their native lands and become almost imperceptibly woven in to the American fabric.\n\n\nS6:\nIn recent years, such differences accentuated by the arrival of immigrants from Asia and other parts of the world in the United States - have become something to celebrate and to nurture.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "SQPR", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nI took cigarettes from my case.\n\n\nP :\nBut when the fit of coughing was over, he replaced it between his lips.\n\n\nQ :\nI lit one of them and placed it between the lips.\n\n\nR :\nThen with a feeble hand he removed the cigarette.\n\n\nS :\nSlowly he took a pull at it and coughed violently.\n\n\nS6:\nThen he continues to draw on it.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThere is difference between Gandhiji's concept of secularism and that of Nehru's.\n\n\nP :\nNehru's idea of secularism was equal indifference to all religions and bothering about none of them.\n\n\nQ :\nAccording to Gandhiji, all religions are equally true and each scripture is worthy of respect.\n\n\nR :\nSuch secularism which means the rejection of all religions is contrary to our culture and tradition.\n\n\nS :\nIn Gandhiji's view, secularism stands for equal respect for all religions.\n\n\nS6:\nInstead of doing any good, such secularism can do harm instead of good.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PRSQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\n As a dramatist Rabindranath was not what might be called a success.\n\n\nP :\nHis dramas were moulded on the lines of the traditional Indian village dramas than the dramas of modern world.\n\n\nQ :\nHis plays were more a catalogue of ideas than a vehicle of the expression of action.\n\n\nR :\nActually the drama has always been the life of Indian people, as it deals with legends of gods and goddesses.\n\n\nS :\nAlthough in his short stories and novels he was able to create living and well defined characters, he did not seem to be able to do so in dramas\n\n\nS6:\nTherefor, drama forms the essential part of the traditional Indian Culture.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "RSQP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nIt is regrettable that there is widespread corruption in the country at all levels.\n\n\nP :\nSo there is hardly anything that the government can do about it now.\n\n\nQ :\nAnd there are graft and other malpractices too.\n\n\nR :\nThe impression that corruption is universal phenomenon persists and the people not cooperate in checking this evil.\n\n\nS :\nRecently several offenders were brought to book, but they were not given deterrent punishment.\n\n\nS6:\nThis is indeed a tragedy of great magnitude.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QSRP", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nThe heart is pump of life.\n\n\nP :\nThey have even succeeded in heart transplants.\n\n\nQ :\nNowadays surgeons are able to stop a patients heart and carry out complicated operations.\n\n\nR :\nA few years ago it was impossible to operate on a patient whose heart was not working properly.\n\n\nS :\nIf heart stops we die in about five minutes.\n\n\nS6:\nAll this was made possible by the invention of heart-lung machine.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "SPRQ", "optc": "SQPR", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "S1:\nYour letter was big relief.\n\n\nP :\nHow did you exams go?\n\n\nQ :\nAfter your result, you must come here for a week.\n\n\nR :\nYou hadn't written for over a month.\n\n\nS :\nI am sure you will come out with flying colours.\n\n\nS6:\nBut don't forget to bring chocolate for Geetha.\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "RPSQ", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When he\n\n\n\nP :\n did not know\n\n\n\nQ :\n he was nervous and\n\n\n\nR :\n heard the hue and cry at midnight\n\n\n\nS :\n what to do\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQPS", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "SQPR", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It has been established that\n\n\n\nP :\n Einstein was\n\n\n\nQ :\n although a great scientist\n\n\n\nR :\n weak in arithmetic\n\n\n\nS :\n right from his school days\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Then\n\n\n\nP :\n it struck me\n\n\n\nQ :\n of course\n\n\n\nR :\n suitable it was\n\n\n\nS :\n how eminently\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPQR", "optb": "QSRP", "optc": "PSRQ", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I read an advertisement that said\n\n\n\nP :\n posh, air-conditioned\n\n\n\nQ :\n gentleman of taste\n\n\n\nR :\n are available for \n\n\n\nS :\n fully furnished rooms\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "PSQR", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Since the beginning of history \n\n\nP :\n have managed to catch  \n\n\nQ :\n the Eskimos and Red Indians \n\n\nR :\n by a very difficulty method \n\n\nS :\n a few specimens of this aquatic animal \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A French woman\n\n\n\nP :\n committed suicide\n\n\n\nQ :\n where she had put up\n\n\n\nR :\n who had come to Calcutta\n\n\n\nS :\n by jumping from the first floor balcony of the hotel\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRQS", "optb": "QSRP", "optc": "RPSQ", "optd": "SRQP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The national unity of a free people\n\n\n\nP :\n to make it impracticable\n\n\n\nQ :\n for there to be an arbitrary administration\n\n\n\nR :\n depends upon a sufficiently even balance of political power\n\n\n\nS :\n against a revolutionary opposition that is irreconcilably opposed to it\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "QRSP", "optc": "RPQS", "optd": "RSPQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The grocer\n\n\n\nP :\n did not listen to the protests of customer\n\n\n\nQ :\n who was in the habit of weighing less\n\n\n\nR :\n whom he had cheated\n\n\n\nS :\n with great audacity\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PRSQ", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They felt safer \n\n\nP :\n to watch the mountain \n\n\nQ :\n of more than five miles \n\n\nR :\n as they settled down \n\n\nS :\n from a distance \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPSQ", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "PQSR", "optd": "PRSQ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "People \n\n\nP :\n at his dispensary \n\n\nQ :\n went to him \n\n\nR :\n of all professions \n\n\nS :\n for medicine and treatment \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "RQSP", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you need help \n\n\nP :\n promptly and politely \n\n\nQ :\n ask for attendants \n\n\nR :\n to help our customers \n\n\nS :\n who have instructions \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "SQRP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is easier \n\n\n\nP :\n to venture into space\n\n\n\nQ :\n for men\n\n\n\nR :\n beneath their feet\n\n\n\nS :\n than to explore\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "PSRQ", "optd": "PQSR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was to be \n\n\nP :\n before their school examination \n\n\nQ :\n which was due to start \n\n\nR :\n the last expedition \n\n\nS :\n in a month's \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "RQSP", "optc": "RPQS", "optd": "SPRQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This time\n\n\n\nP :\n exactly what he had been told\n\n\n\nQ :\n the young man did\n\n\n\nR :\n beyond his dreams\n\n\n\nS :\n and the plan succeeded\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "QPSR", "optc": "PQSR", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the darkness\n\n\n\nP :\n the long, narrow beard\n\n\n\nQ :\n was clearly visible with\n\n\n\nR :\n the tall stooping figure of the doctor\n\n\n\nS :\n and the aquiline nose\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQPS", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We have to\n\n\n\nP :\n as we see it \n\n\n\nQ :\n speak the truth\n\n\n\nR :\n there is falsehood and weakness\n\n\n\nS :\n even if all around us\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQSP", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When it began to rain suddenly on the first of January \n\n\nP :\n to celebrate the new year \n\n\nQ :\n we ran for shelter \n\n\nR :\n to the neighbouring house \n\n\nS :\n where many people had gathered \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRPS", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "QRSP", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He told us that\n\n\n\nP :\n and enjoyed it immensely\n\n\n\nQ :\n in a prose translation\n\n\n\nR :\n he had read Milton\n\n\n\nS :\n which he had borrowed from his teacher\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "RQSP", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He knew that\n\n\n\nP :\n and then to save himself\n\n\n\nQ :\n was to save all the lives\n\n\n\nR :\n entrusted to his care\n\n\n\nS :\n the duty of a captain\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "SPRQ", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is not, therefore\n\n\n\nP :\n that I pay a tribute\n\n\n\nQ :\n to conductors as a class\n\n\n\nR :\n with any feeling of unfriendliness\n\n\n\nS :\n to a particular member of that class\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "RQPS", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Of many artists\n\n\n\nP :\n those who impressed me the most\n\n\n\nQ :\n I was a child\n\n\n\nR :\n but those with unique personalities off stage\n\n\n\nS :\n were not always the successful ones\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRQP", "optb": "QRSP", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As a disease\n\n\n\nP :\n and breaks up marriages\n\n\n\nQ :\n accidents and suicides\n\n\n\nR :\n alcoholism leads to\n\n\n\nS :\n affecting all ages\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "RPSQ", "optc": "SRQP", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is easy to excuse \n\nP :\nbut it is hard \n\n\nQ :\nin a boy of fourteen  \n\n\nR :\nthe mischief of early childhood \n\n\nS :\nto tolerate even unavoidable faults  \n\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "QRSP", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "RPSQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The majestic mahogany table\n\n\n\nP :\n belongs to an old prince\n\n\n\nQ :\n which has one leg missing\n\n\n\nR :\n who is no impoverished\n\n\n\nS :\n but not without some pride\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQSR", "optb": "QRSP", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Education is\n\n\n\nP :\n of the proper sense of responsibilities \n\n\n\nQ :\n the first need\n\n\n\nR :\n in a citizen\n\n\n\nS :\n for the development\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQPR", "optb": "QSRP", "optc": "QSPR", "optd": "PQRS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It would\n\n\n\nP :\n appear from his statement\n\n\n\nQ :\n about the policy of management\n\n\n\nR :\n in dealing with the strike\n\n\n\nS :\n that he was quite in the dark\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPSQ", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "PRQS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He was so kind and generous that \n\n\nP :\n he not only \n\n\nQ :\n made others do so \n\n\nR :\n but also \n\n\nS :\n helped them himself \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSRQ", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "QPRS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We went\n\n\n\nP :\n along the railway line\n\n\n\nQ :\n and had a right to\n\n\n\nR :\n where other people not allowed to go\n\n\n\nS :\n but daddy belonged to the railway\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "PRSQ", "optc": "RSQP", "optd": "PRQS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There was\n\n\n\nP :\n needed for it everyday life\n\n\n\nQ :\n a time when each family\n\n\n\nR :\n for itself most of the things it\n\n\n\nS :\n actually produced\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QRSP", "optb": "RQPS", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "QSRP", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Little\n\n\n\nP :\n that he had been let down\n\n\n\nQ :\n stood by all these years\n\n\n\nR :\n did he realise\n\n\n\nS :\n by a colleague whom he had\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPSQ", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "QSPR", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I saw that \n\n\nP :\n but seeing my host in this mood \n\n\nQ :\n I deemed it proper to take leave \n\n\nR :\n as I had frequently done before \n\n\nS :\n it had been my intention to pass the night there \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPSR", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "SPQR", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is very easy\n\n\n\nP :\n a great deal more than one realises\n\n\n\nQ :\n may mean\n\n\n\nR :\n that a phrase that one does not quite understand\n\n\n\nS :\n to persuade oneself\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSQP", "optb": "SPQR", "optc": "SRQP", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I was\n\n\n\nP :\n and stay fro few days in Delhi\n\n\n\nQ :\n when my father told me\n\n\n\nR :\n very excited\n\n\n\nS :\n that I could go with him\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "RQSP", "optc": "QRSP", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "work is the one thing\n\n\n\nP :\n and without it\n\n\n\nQ :\n that is necessary\n\n\n\nR :\n to keep the world going\n\n\n\nS :\n we should all die\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPSR", "optb": "RPQS", "optc": "SRPQ", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The appearance \n\n\n\nP :\n this dinosaurs were at their peak \n\n\n\nQ :\n of the first mammals on the earth \n\n\n\nR :\n at the time when\n\n\n\nS :\n went almost unnoticed\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "QSRP", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "RPQS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "By this time\n\n\n\nP :\n at the railway station\n\n\n\nQ :\n reported mass looting\n\n\n\nR :\n reports of violence were flooding in\n\n\n\nS :\n which police dispatches\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RSPQ", "optb": "SPRQ", "optc": "SQRP", "optd": "RSQP", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Then the women\n\nP :\nlamenting their evil desire \n\n\nQ :\nthat had brought \n\n\nR :\nwept loudly\n\n\nS :\nthis sorrow upon them \n\n\n\r\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPQS", "optb": "RQPS", "optc": "PQSR", "optd": "PRQS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Women\n\n\n\nP :\n till the other day\n\n\n\nQ :\n who were content being housewives\n\n\n\nR :\n about spending their time cooking\n\n\n\nS :\n now sound apologetic\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "RSPQ", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "RQPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Though he dialled frequently\n\n\n\nP :\n on telephone\n\n\n\nQ :\n my brother could not contact me\n\n\n\nR :\n and had left no information\n\n\n\nS :\n as I had gone out of office\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPRS", "optb": "SQRP", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "SPQR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He said\n\n\n\nP :\n here is the cat\n\n\n\nQ :\n throughout the night\n\n\n\nR :\n which had been paying havoc with things\n\n\n\nS :\n that ate the rat\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PSQR", "optb": "PSRQ", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He sat\n\n\n\nP :\n through the Town Hall Park\n\n\n\nQ :\n which flanked a path running\n\n\n\nR :\n under the boughs\n\n\n\nS :\n of a spreading tamarind tree\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQSR", "optb": "RSQP", "optc": "RSPQ", "optd": "PRSQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I don't remember \n\n\nP :\n I saw a man dying in front of a hospital  \n\n\nQ :\n but when I left lucknow in 1984 \n\n\nR :\n hit apparently by a fast moving car \n\n\nS :\n the exact date \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SQRP", "optb": "SQPR", "optc": "QRPS", "optd": "SPRQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was\n\n\n\nP :\n in keeping with my mood\n\n\n\nQ :\n a soft summer evening\n\n\n\nR :\n as I walked sedately\n\n\n\nS :\n in the direction of new house\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SRPQ", "optb": "QRPS", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "SQPR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All such students\n\n\n\nP :\n get success\n\n\n\nQ :\n who are honest and hard-working\n\n\n\nR :\n and recognition\n\n\n\nS :\n in very walk of life\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "SPRQ", "optb": "PRQS", "optc": "QPRS", "optd": "PSRQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The master \n\n\nP :\n who was very loyal to him \n\n\nQ :\n punished the servant \n\n\nR :\n without giving any valid reason \n\n\nS :\n when he left the work unfinished \n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RQPS", "optb": "RQSP", "optc": "QPSR", "optd": "QRPS", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With her body\n\n\n\nP :\n dragging her unwilling feet\n\n\n\nQ :\n weak and infirm\n\n\n\nR :\n doubled with age\n\n\n\nS :\n she persisted in her mission\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "PQRS", "optb": "QPRS", "optc": "RQPS", "optd": "SRPQ", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "P: We must read\n\n\n\nP :\n if we want to absorb the fruits of great literature\n\n\n\nQ :\n but with concentration\n\n\n\nR :\n them not as we do cricket stories\n\n\n\nS :\nundefined\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "QPSR", "optb": "PSQR", "optc": "PRSQ", "optd": "PRQS", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I enclose\n\n\n\nP :\n and the postage\n\n\n\nQ :\n a postal order\n\n\n\nR :\n the price of books\n\n\n\nS :\n which will cover\n\n\n\nThe Proper sequence should be:", "opta": "RPSQ", "optb": "QSPR", "optc": "QSRP", "optd": "QPSR", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which sentence should come third in the paragraph?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "opte": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which sentence should come last in the paragraph?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "opte": "5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which sentence should come fourth in the paragraph?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "opte": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which sentence should come second in the paragraph?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "opte": "5", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which sentence should come first in the paragraph?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "opte": "5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fate smiles ...... those who untiringly grapple with stark realities of life.", "opta": "with", "optb": "over", "optc": "on", "optd": "round", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The miser gazed ...... at the pile of gold coins in front of him.", "opta": "avidly", "optb": "admiringly", "optc": "thoughtfully", "optd": "earnestly", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catching the earlier train will give us the ...... to do some shopping.", "opta": "chance", "optb": "luck", "optc": "possibility", "optd": "occasion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I saw a ...... of cows in the field.", "opta": "group", "optb": "herd", "optc": "swarm", "optd": "flock", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The grapes are now ...... enough to be picked.", "opta": "ready", "optb": "mature", "optc": "ripe", "optd": "advanced", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Success in this examination depends ...... hard work alone.", "opta": "at", "optb": "over", "optc": "for", "optd": "on", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My uncle decided to take ...... and my sister to the market.", "opta": "I", "optb": "mine", "optc": "me", "optd": "myself", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you smuggle goods into the country, they may be ...... by the customs authority.", "opta": "possessed", "optb": "punished", "optc": "confiscated", "optd": "fined", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Man does not live by ...... alone.", "opta": "food", "optb": "bread", "optc": "meals", "optd": "diet", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Piyush behaves strangely at times and, therefore, nobody gets ...... with him.", "opta": "about", "optb": "through", "optc": "along", "optd": "up", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rohan and Rohit are twin brothers, but they do not look ......", "opta": "unique", "optb": "different", "optc": "likely", "optd": "alike", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To err is ...... to forgive divine.", "opta": "beastly", "optb": "human", "optc": "inhuman", "optd": "natural", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ruling party will have to put its own house ...... order.", "opta": "in", "optb": "on", "optc": "to", "optd": "into", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "...... of old paintings is a job for experts.", "opta": "Resurrection", "optb": "Retrieval", "optc": "Restoration", "optd": "Resumption", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During Diwali the shops are ...... of people.", "opta": "busy", "optb": "full", "optc": "crowded", "optd": "bubbling", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The paths of glory lead ...... to the grave.", "opta": "straight", "optb": "but", "optc": "in", "optd": "directly", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The telephone ...... several times before I answered it.", "opta": "was ringing", "optb": "has rung", "optc": "had rung", "optd": "would ring", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He passed the examination in the first class because he ......", "opta": "was hard working for it", "optb": "worked hardly for it", "optc": "had worked hard for it", "optd": "was working hard for it", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Jawaharlal spent his childhood ...... Anand Bhawan.", "opta": "at", "optb": "in", "optc": "on", "optd": "across", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If negotiations are to prove fruitful, there must not only be sincerity on each side, but there must also be ...... in the sincerity of the other side.", "opta": "faith", "optb": "belief", "optc": "substance", "optd": "certainty", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I hate sitting ...... him as he always smells of garlic.", "opta": "besides", "optb": "along", "optc": "at", "optd": "beside", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some regions of our country still remain ...... to the average man.", "opta": "inaccessible", "optb": "impossible", "optc": "impermeable", "optd": "impenetrable", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It ...... that Prashant will not be selected for the post", "opta": "feels", "optb": "looks", "optc": "believes", "optd": "seems", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In Bush, Saddam was up ...... more than his match.", "opta": "for", "optb": "into", "optc": "against", "optd": "to", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I haven't seen you ...... a week.", "opta": "within", "optb": "since", "optc": "for", "optd": "from", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I listened, but I had no idea what he was ...... about.", "opta": "saying", "optb": "talking", "optc": "telling", "optd": "discussing", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The car in which the minister was traveling ...... with an accident.", "opta": "hit", "optb": "drove", "optc": "crashed", "optd": "met", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The non cooperative attitude of the members can only ...... the image of the society.", "opta": "spoil", "optb": "improve", "optc": "degrade", "optd": "defame", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sonika is quite intelligent but rather ......", "opta": "idealistic", "optb": "generous", "optc": "lazy", "optd": "optimistic", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a little-publicised deal, Pepsi, Cola has ...... the entire soft drink market in Afghanistan.", "opta": "occupied", "optb": "conquered", "optc": "swallowed", "optd": "captured", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He ...... in wearing the old fashioned coat in spite of his wife's disapproval.", "opta": "insists", "optb": "persists", "optc": "desists", "optd": "resists", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She ...... a brief appearance at the end of party.", "opta": "put on", "optb": "put in", "optc": "put across", "optd": "put up", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Life is to death as pleasure is to ......", "opta": "poverty", "optb": "suffering", "optc": "anguish", "optd": "pain", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This, partly, explains how the Mehta family has been able to ...... its lavish lifestyle in recent times, despite the fact that all its assets have been ......", "opta": "keep, removed", "optb": "afford, attached", "optc": "develop, liquidated", "optd": "keep up, destroyed", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The machine is difficult to build ...... easy to maintain.", "opta": "but", "optb": "and", "optc": "for", "optd": "if", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you work beyond your capacity, you will naturally feel ......", "opta": "drowsy", "optb": "tired", "optc": "confident", "optd": "giddy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you persists in telling lies to me I shall sue you ...... slander.", "opta": "to", "optb": "on", "optc": "for", "optd": "with", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "His father-in-law ...... him up in business.", "opta": "put", "optb": "made", "optc": "set", "optd": "built", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "...... works of reference are valuable as Encyclopedia, Brittanica.", "opta": "A few", "optb": "Few", "optc": "The few", "optd": "Fewer", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This book is quite similar ......", "opta": "with the \"Treasure Island\"", "optb": "of that film we saw at school", "optc": "to the one I read last week", "optd": "than a story told by our teacher", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If our friends are not able to take us in their car, we must make ...... arrangements to go to the airport.", "opta": "alternative", "optb": "another", "optc": "alternate", "optd": "possible", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A crescendo of metallic thuds arose from the market, where the iron-smiths were ...... the pieces of metals.", "opta": "flattening", "optb": "striking", "optc": "hammering", "optd": "thrashing", "ans": "C", "explanation": "We use the word 'hammering' when we would like to say about the events related to \nmetals."}, {"question": "I haven't eaten an apple ...... a long while.", "opta": "from", "optb": "since", "optc": "for", "optd": "until", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The parliament invested the new organisation ...... judicial authority.", "opta": "by", "optb": "with", "optc": "from", "optd": "through", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Owing to the power cut in the area, factories are being forced to ...... men", "opta": "throw away", "optb": "send off", "optc": "put off", "optd": "lay off", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Man must ...... to stop pollution.", "opta": "act", "optb": "perform", "optc": "operate", "optd": "behave", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He was sent to the prison for his ......", "opta": "sin", "optb": "vice", "optc": "crime", "optd": "guilt", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The answer was written ...... blue ink.", "opta": "with", "optb": "by", "optc": "in", "optd": "on", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Many ...... decisions were taken at the meeting.", "opta": "hectic", "optb": "historic", "optc": "historical", "optd": "histrionic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Those who persist in the endeavor at long last triumph ...... the odds of life.", "opta": "over", "optb": "on", "optc": "upon", "optd": "about", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the modern materialistic society, the only aim of people appears to be ...... money by fair means or foul.", "opta": "print", "optb": "produce", "optc": "acquire", "optd": "extort", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the ...... for an air letter?", "opta": "fare", "optb": "value", "optc": "postage", "optd": "stamp", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He became enamored ...... her grace when he first saw her dance.", "opta": "with", "optb": "of", "optc": "by", "optd": "in", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rama was so badly injured that he needed ...... care in the hospital.", "opta": "extensive", "optb": "little", "optc": "deep", "optd": "intensive", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You cannot devise a method which ...... all possibility of errors.", "opta": "excludes", "optb": "includes", "optc": "avoids", "optd": "ignores", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Many areas of the city were ...... into darkness for several hours.", "opta": "spread", "optb": "plunged", "optc": "merged", "optd": "deep", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Find the ...... that accompany these cartoons.", "opta": "topics", "optb": "titles", "optc": "captions", "optd": "headings", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I don't really know how to ...... the problem.", "opta": "tackle", "optb": "cope", "optc": "draw", "optd": "erase", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The English schemed to continue their rule in India by playing off one community ...... the other.", "opta": "before", "optb": "upon", "optc": "against", "optd": "with", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The passengers were afraid, but the captain ...... them that there was no danger.", "opta": "promised", "optb": "assured", "optc": "advised", "optd": "counselled", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The family gave father a gold watch on the ...... of his fiftieth birthday.", "opta": "time", "optb": "event", "optc": "occasion", "optd": "celebration", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The park ...... as far as the river.", "opta": "extends", "optb": "advances", "optc": "enlarges", "optd": "emerges", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Many of the advances of civilisation have been conceived by young people just on the ...... of adulthood", "opta": "boundary", "optb": "threshold", "optc": "peak", "optd": "horizon", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Arti pulled a long ...... when she was told that she could not go to Agra.", "opta": "mouth", "optb": "skirt", "optc": "face", "optd": "hand", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Brothers must live in harmony. They must never fall ......", "opta": "off", "optb": "out", "optc": "apart", "optd": "away", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I was astounded at his ...... lack of knowledge about the Continent of Africa.", "opta": "abundant", "optb": "colossal", "optc": "huge", "optd": "great", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ayesha always ...... the permission of her father before going for movies.", "opta": "seeking", "optb": "seeks", "optc": "sought", "optd": "seeker", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He felt no ...... as he plunged the knife into her back.", "opta": "qualms", "optb": "scruple", "optc": "conscience", "optd": "morals", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You haven't had your lunch yet, ...... you?", "opta": "are", "optb": "aren't", "optc": "have", "optd": "haven't", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The manner in which bombs exploded in five trains with in a short span of time suggests that it is a part of a ......", "opta": "game", "optb": "conspiracy", "optc": "villainy", "optd": "sabotage", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Wheat ...... carbohydrates, vitamins, proteins, and dietary fibre in our daily diet.", "opta": "has", "optb": "gives", "optc": "yields", "optd": "provides", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The waiter hasn't brought the coffee ...... I've been here an hour already.", "opta": "till", "optb": "up", "optc": "yet", "optd": "still", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In our zeal for progress we should not ...... executive with more power.", "opta": "avoid", "optb": "give", "optc": "enhance", "optd": "arm", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You've only three months to complete the course, Don't give ...... now.", "opta": "out", "optb": "away", "optc": "up", "optd": "off", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The traveler slept under the ...... shade of banyan tree.", "opta": "cold", "optb": "cool", "optc": "cooling", "optd": "dark", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She has an aversion ...... taking even onion and garlic.", "opta": "with", "optb": "at", "optc": "against", "optd": "to", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The river overflowed its ...... and flooded the area.", "opta": "edges", "optb": "fronts", "optc": "limits", "optd": "banks", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "...... The arrival of the police, nobody went near the victim.", "opta": "Unless", "optb": "Although", "optc": "Even", "optd": "Till", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When I was a child, I ......to school everyday instead going by cycle.", "opta": "had walked", "optb": "walked", "optc": "have walked", "optd": "have been walking", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Farida sings very well and ...... does salim.", "opta": "even", "optb": "too", "optc": "also", "optd": "so", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The old Nature versus ...... debate regarding crime continues even today.", "opta": "Man", "optb": "Universe", "optc": "Culture", "optd": "Nurture", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Sun ...... at six this morning.", "opta": "raised", "optb": "rose", "optc": "arose", "optd": "aroused", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "That rule is applicable ...... every one.", "opta": "to", "optb": "for", "optc": "about", "optd": "with", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Her parents will never give their ...... to so much an unsuitable match.", "opta": "acquiescence", "optb": "consent", "optc": "agreement", "optd": "willingness", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He tried to ...... himself against a horde of ruffians.", "opta": "collect", "optb": "save", "optc": "support", "optd": "defend", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to corporate circles data is pushing through the merger to create financially ...... company in the processed foods business, the group's thrust area for the 1990's", "opta": "acceptable", "optb": "powerful", "optc": "leading", "optd": "straight", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Indeed, all over the world, more and more people are ...... coffee.", "opta": "wanting", "optb": "drinking", "optc": "liking", "optd": "partaking", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Like any other country India has its ...... share of superstitions.", "opta": "proper", "optb": "abundant", "optc": "fair", "optd": "peculiar", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The new education policy provides a useful ...... for the planners to remove illiteracy.", "opta": "breakup", "optb": "breakthrough", "optc": "breakaway", "optd": "break-in", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "People who ...... on horses usually lose in the end.", "opta": "gamble", "optb": "play", "optc": "risk", "optd": "place", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "About twenty clerks were made ...... when the banks introduced computers.", "opta": "dispensable", "optb": "redundant", "optc": "expandable", "optd": "obsolete", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "After the rain the weather ...... and the sun came out.", "opta": "cleared out", "optb": "cleared up", "optc": "cleared away", "optd": "cleared off", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The building comprises ...... sixty rooms.", "opta": "of", "optb": "onto", "optc": "by", "optd": "no preposition needed", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Namrata was found to ...... the required qualifications for the job.", "opta": "contain", "optb": "disclose", "optc": "posses", "optd": "acquire", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Government buildings are ...... on the Republic day.", "opta": "enlightened", "optb": "lightened", "optc": "illuminated", "optd": "glowed", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "we had ...... wonderful time at the party last night.", "opta": "such a", "optb": "so", "optc": "such", "optd": "very", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An employment advertisement should ...... the number of vacancies.", "opta": "provide", "optb": "specify", "optc": "contain", "optd": "declare", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When varun left the cocktail party he was as ...... as a judge.", "opta": "sober", "optb": "drunk", "optc": "brave", "optd": "wise", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The criminal seems to have acted in ...... the three others.", "opta": "collusion", "optb": "coalition", "optc": "collision", "optd": "cohesion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Soft minded individuals are ...... to embrace all kinds superstitions.", "opta": "disposed", "optb": "eager", "optc": "reluctant", "optd": "prone", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The stenographer is very efficient. He is ...... to his firm.", "opta": "a boon", "optb": "a credit", "optc": "a blessing", "optd": "an asset", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "However, the group's long-term strategy is to ...... on core sector business connected with infrastructure and energy.", "opta": "breed", "optb": "develop", "optc": "concentrate", "optd": "depend", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The man came in a van to ...... the television set.", "opta": "mend", "optb": "reform", "optc": "correct", "optd": "alter", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nobody can ...... me to do anything which I do not want to do.", "opta": "encourage", "optb": "request", "optc": "oppose", "optd": "compel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A sanguine outlook is associated with the ......", "opta": "rationalist", "optb": "socialist", "optc": "philanthropist", "optd": "optimist", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "His conduct is bad, and his honesty is not ...... suspicion.", "opta": "above", "optb": "beyond", "optc": "under", "optd": "in", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is 14 years since i ...... him.", "opta": "have seen", "optb": "had seen", "optc": "saw", "optd": "see", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It being an ...... issue, it is not correct to introduce questions of morality in to the debate.", "opta": "moral", "optb": "immoral", "optc": "amoral", "optd": "irrelevant", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Natwarlal ...... them all for a ride by producing false documents.", "opta": "took", "optb": "cheated", "optc": "kept", "optd": "let", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "True brevity ...... in saying only what needs to be said.", "opta": "consists", "optb": "depicts", "optc": "portrays", "optd": "resides", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Health is too important to be ......", "opta": "discarded", "optb": "despised", "optc": "detested", "optd": "neglected", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In hot weather I like lying in the ...... of a tree.", "opta": "shade", "optb": "shelter", "optc": "protection", "optd": "shadow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was indeed unreasonable ...... him to leave this job and start business.", "opta": "in", "optb": "with", "optc": "upon", "optd": "of", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One major ...... between the Election Commission and the Union Government related to the powers of the former in respect of the deployment of central police forces at places where are elections is held.", "opta": "irritant", "optb": "conflict", "optc": "pain", "optd": "culprit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We shall not to be able to use your ability in court unless we can find someone to ...... to statements.", "opta": "corroborate", "optb": "avouch", "optc": "verify", "optd": "approve", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is too dull ...... this problem.", "opta": "solving", "optb": "to solving", "optc": "to solve", "optd": "solves", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is the person who is ...... to blame.", "opta": "mostly", "optb": "sure", "optc": "most", "optd": "bound", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We had to pay more taxi fare because the driver brought us by a ...... route.", "opta": "circular", "optb": "circumscribed", "optc": "longest", "optd": "circuitous", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He was accused ...... stealing his aunt's necklace.", "opta": "for", "optb": "with", "optc": "of", "optd": "on", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He knew everything better than anybody else, and it was an affront to his ...... vanity that you should disagree with him.", "opta": "overstrung", "optb": "overweening", "optc": "overwhelming", "optd": "overwrought", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It's very kind of you to ...... to speak at the meeting.", "opta": "accept", "optb": "agree", "optc": "comply", "optd": "concur", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pakistan lost a ...... wicket just when they seemed to be doing so well, and that led to their eventual defeat.", "opta": "critical", "optb": "crucial", "optc": "sensitive", "optd": "providential", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sita's heart ...... at the sight of the beautiful diamond necklace.", "opta": "leapt", "optb": "stopped", "optc": "slowed", "optd": "ran", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He lives near a lovely ...... of countryside.", "opta": "length", "optb": "piece", "optc": "section", "optd": "stretch", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ambition is one of those ......which are never satisfied.", "opta": "ideas", "optb": "fancies", "optc": "passions", "optd": "feeds", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is a person of sound character and ...... disposition.", "opta": "beneficent", "optb": "morous", "optc": "amiable", "optd": "amicable", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If I take a state roadways bus, I'll get late, ...... ?", "opta": "isn't it", "optb": "won't I", "optc": "will I", "optd": "is it", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In high school many of us never realised  the importance that grammar would ...... in later life.", "opta": "figure", "optb": "portray", "optc": "play", "optd": "exercise", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a changing and ...... unstructured business environment, creativity and innovation are being ...... demanded of executives.", "opta": "highly, extremely", "optb": "progressively, increasingly", "optc": "increasingly, moderately", "optd": "excessively, rapidly", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "On account of the dearth of grass on the arid plains the cattle became ......", "opta": "flippant", "optb": "jubilant", "optc": "agitated", "optd": "emaciated", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A woman came in with a baby who, she said, ...... a safety pin.", "opta": "was just swallowing", "optb": "swallowed", "optc": "had just swallowed", "optd": "just swallowed", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Hubble Space Telescope will search for planets around the stars, a key to the ...... extraterrestrial life, and examine interstellar dust and gases out of which stars are born.", "opta": "perception", "optb": "discovery", "optc": "enquiry", "optd": "quest", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She ...... Rs 80 out of the bank every Friday.", "opta": "obtains", "optb": "draws", "optc": "pulls", "optd": "extracts", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The American ...... presented his credentials to the President of India.", "opta": "adviser", "optb": "ambassador", "optc": "delegate", "optd": "representative", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Once he has signed the agreement, he won't be able to ......", "opta": "back up", "optb": "back in", "optc": "back at", "optd": "back out", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was difficult to remove my feet as it had got stuck ...... in the mud.", "opta": "fairly", "optb": "greatly", "optc": "widely", "optd": "firmly", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is a very careful person, he never takes side but remains ......", "opta": "impartial", "optb": "unbiased", "optc": "neutral", "optd": "prejudiced", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "West Bengal ...... plentiful rainfall and is consequently a very green part of the country.", "opta": "misses", "optb": "receives", "optc": "expects", "optd": "regrets", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "this brand of TV is quite inferior ...... that one.", "opta": "than", "optb": "to", "optc": "with", "optd": "over", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is not what you say that ...... but what you do", "opta": "matches", "optb": "implies", "optc": "matters", "optd": "moves", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "'Please' and 'Thank you' are the little courtesies by which we keep the ...... of life oiled and running smoothly.", "opta": "path", "optb": "machine", "optc": "garden", "optd": "river", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I put ...... the light and slept.", "opta": "up", "optb": "down", "optc": "in", "optd": "out", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "...... all intents and purposes, the manager is the master of the firm.", "opta": "in", "optb": "upon", "optc": "with", "optd": "to", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pilot had been warned about the storm, before he ......", "opta": "took away", "optb": "took up", "optc": "took over", "optd": "took off", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hardly had he arrived ...... it started raining.", "opta": "before", "optb": "when", "optc": "than", "optd": "after", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I ...... a car to be absolutely necessary these days.", "opta": "consider", "optb": "regard", "optc": "think", "optd": "agree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Besides other provisions, that shopkeeper deals ...... cosmetics.", "opta": "with", "optb": "in", "optc": "at", "optd": "for", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Leave a two inch ...... on each page for the teacher's remarks.", "opta": "border", "optb": "margin", "optc": "blank", "optd": "gap", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The team was well trained and strong, but somehow their ...... was low.", "opta": "feeling", "optb": "moral", "optc": "consciousness", "optd": "morale", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lovers were meeting each other secretly, but their ...... affair was soon known to everyone.", "opta": "clandestine", "optb": "covert", "optc": "unknown", "optd": "candid", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The king ...... the rebel.", "opta": "excused", "optb": "forgave", "optc": "pardoned", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I shall call ...... you tomorrow.", "opta": "at", "optb": "on", "optc": "with", "optd": "by", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She ...... from the crowd because of her height and flaming red hair.", "opta": "stood out", "optb": "stood off", "optc": "stood up", "optd": "stood by", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a large cities people are cut ...... from nature.", "opta": "away", "optb": "off", "optc": "out", "optd": "down", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The more your action and thought are allied and ...... the happier you grow.", "opta": "diverget", "optb": "unravelled", "optc": "integrated", "optd": "invincible", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We had a ...... of warm weather in February.", "opta": "time", "optb": "spell", "optc": "length", "optd": "phase", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Physically we are now all neighbors, but psychologically. we are ...... to each other.", "opta": "primitives", "optb": "complimentary", "optc": "strangers", "optd": "cowards", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When their examinations are over, the children gleefully ...... the books they had been reading.", "opta": "shelve", "optb": "sidetrack", "optc": "overthrew", "optd": "abandon", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chintu is ...... small to start playing cricket now.", "opta": "very", "optb": "much", "optc": "too", "optd": "more", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The thief ...... all the money.", "opta": "made up", "optb": "made off with", "optc": "mode do with", "optd": "made good", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The luggage was ...... heavy for him to lift", "opta": "much", "optb": "as", "optc": "so", "optd": "too", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Walking at 3'o clock, I heard the ...... of thunder.", "opta": "crackle", "optb": "rumble", "optc": "ripple", "optd": "clank", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A stone that goes on rolling ...... no moss.", "opta": "collects", "optb": "gets", "optc": "gathers", "optd": "accumulates", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The earth is at present in great danger of becoming uninhabitable because of ...... environmental pollution which is going on at an incredible rapid pace.", "opta": "gigantic", "optb": "inhuman", "optc": "stupendous", "optd": "colossal", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Moreover, a fact finding mission ...... by BSN to India in January this year strongly recommended that the French group should go it alone, and not hand over ...... to an Indian Partner.", "opta": "organised, papers", "optb": "constituted, authority", "optc": "sponsored, power", "optd": "dispatched, control", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There is a keen ...... in each trade.", "opta": "contest", "optb": "comparison", "optc": "competition", "optd": "cooperation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Now, the management graduate can expect to have a prosperous life on a ...... income without having to depend on finding a place in family busiess having to tend the paternal estates.", "opta": "professional", "optb": "regular", "optc": "meaningful", "optd": "dependable", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The boy fell ...... bicycle.", "opta": "of", "optb": "off", "optc": "from", "optd": "under", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The French ...... reputed to have a very good sense of humour.", "opta": "is", "optb": "was", "optc": "are", "optd": "will be", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Johny, where are you? ...... up this tree.", "opta": "There I am", "optb": "There am I", "optc": "Here am I", "optd": "Here I am", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "That the poor in our country, are happy is", "opta": "a dream", "optb": "a vision", "optc": "an ideal", "optd": "an illusion", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The robbers were arrested and ...... prison yesterday.", "opta": "brought into", "optb": "brought to", "optc": "taken into", "optd": "taken to", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cinema ...... a welcome escape from cramped and dull city life and the Indians are avid movie-goers.", "opta": "depicts", "optb": "highlights", "optc": "follows", "optd": "offers", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I shall take revenge ...... you.", "opta": "from", "optb": "with", "optc": "on", "optd": "at", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This book is a useful ...... to our library.", "opta": "discovery", "optb": "asset", "optc": "addition", "optd": "arrival", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The boy was cured ...... typhoid.", "opta": "from", "optb": "of", "optc": "for", "optd": "through", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The communalist represents the ...... of everything noble that we have inherited from our culture and history.", "opta": "antithesis", "optb": "antidote", "optc": "immorality", "optd": "antagonism", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is so ...... to light that he never leaves the house without sunglasses.", "opta": "insensitive", "optb": "sensitive", "optc": "afraid", "optd": "immune", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ...... of the Minister's statement cannot be verified by people who have no access to official records.", "opta": "veracity", "optb": "verbosity", "optc": "ambiguity", "optd": "validity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "But the introductory fee does not stop after the initial handshake, brokers have to ...... it up after each transaction.", "opta": "bring", "optb": "cough", "optc": "boost", "optd": "give", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Colgate has also set an ambitious aim of ......on 8% value shared of tooth paste market by then end of first years.", "opta": "cornering", "optb": "soliciting", "optc": "disturbing", "optd": "keeping", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "...... a failure of some traffic lights, traffic is moving very slowly.", "opta": "Owing", "optb": "Due to", "optc": "Because", "optd": "Since", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The battalion operating from the mountain was able to ...... three enemy divisons.", "opta": "tie up", "optb": "tie down", "optc": "tie on", "optd": "tie with", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I purposely ...... meet you during my last visit to Kashmir.", "opta": "didn't", "optb": "won't", "optc": "hadn't", "optd": "wouldn't", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I have read one novel by Premchand. I want to read ...... novel by him.", "opta": "other", "optb": "another", "optc": "all", "optd": "few", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A man remains narrow minded, self compliance and ignorant unless he visits other people and ...... from them.", "opta": "earns", "optb": "borrows", "optc": "learns", "optd": "hears", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My father ...... down for a nap.", "opta": "lays", "optb": "laid", "optc": "lain", "optd": "lie", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I think they allow their children too much ......", "opta": "liberality", "optb": "latitude", "optc": "lassitude", "optd": "levity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Once you suspect a person of double dealing, you ought to keep him at arm's ......", "opta": "distance", "optb": "length", "optc": "aim", "optd": "width", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Affix a revenue stamp and put your signature ...... it.", "opta": "on", "optb": "upo", "optc": "above", "optd": "over", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My first lesson ...... forgiveness came from my mother.", "opta": "upon", "optb": "about", "optc": "in", "optd": "on", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At one point, it looked as if an area of agreement would ...... specially over the issue of productivity linked wages.", "opta": "develop", "optb": "come out", "optc": "emerge", "optd": "grow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Do you know ......?", "opta": "where she comes from", "optb": "where does she come from", "optc": "where from she comes", "optd": "from where does she come", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "God is ......", "opta": "graceful", "optb": "gracious", "optc": "grateful", "optd": "greatful", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is so ...... that he immediately believe my story of ghosts.", "opta": "innocent", "optb": "credulous", "optc": "vociferous", "optd": "credible", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The small child does whatever his father was done.", "opta": "has done", "optb": "did", "optc": "does", "optd": "had done", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You need not come unless you want to.", "opta": "You don't need to come unless you want to", "optb": "You come only when you want to", "optc": "You come unless you don't want to", "optd": "You needn't come until you don't want to", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There are not many men who are so famous that they are frequently referred to by their short names only", "opta": "initials", "optb": "signatures", "optc": "pictures", "optd": "middle names", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The man to who I sold my house was a cheat.", "opta": "to whom I sell", "optb": "to who I sell", "optc": "who was sold to", "optd": "to whom I sold", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They were all shocked at his failure in the competition.", "opta": "were shocked at all", "optb": "had all shocked at", "optc": "had all shocked by", "optd": "had been all shocked on", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I need not offer any explanation regarding this incident - my behaviour is speaking itself.", "opta": "will speak to itself", "optb": "speaks for itself", "optc": "has been speaking", "optd": "speaks about itself", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is too important for tolerating any delay.", "opta": "to tolerate", "optb": "to tolerating", "optc": "at tolerating", "optd": "with tolerating", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The population of Tokyo is greater than that of any other town in the world.", "opta": "greatest among any other", "optb": "greater than all other", "optc": "greater than those of any other", "optd": "greater than any other", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The performance of our players was rather worst than I had expected.", "opta": "bad as I had expected", "optb": "worse than I had expected", "optc": "worse than expectation", "optd": "worst than was expected", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Why did you not threw the bag away?", "opta": "did you not throw", "optb": "had you not threw", "optc": "did you not thrown", "optd": "you did not thrown", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shapes of gods and goddess are worshipped by people.", "opta": "Images", "optb": "Reflections", "optc": "Clay shapes", "optd": "Clay toys", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In addition to enhanced their reputations through strategic use of philanthropy, companies are sponsoring  social initiatives to open new markets.", "opta": "of enhancing their reputation", "optb": "to having enhance their reputation", "optc": "to enhancing their reputation", "optd": "to have their reputation enhancing", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The intruder stood quietly for few moments", "opta": "for few time", "optb": "for the few moments", "optc": "for moments", "optd": "for a few moments", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The police has so far succeeded in recovering only a part of the stolen property.", "opta": "thus far succeeded for recovery", "optb": "so far succeeded in recovery of", "optc": "as for as succeeded in recovery of", "optd": "so far succeeded to recover", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He confidentially asked the crowd if they thought he was right and the crowd shouted that they did.", "opta": "that he did", "optb": "that they had", "optc": "that he is", "optd": "that he didn't", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Why should the candidates be afraid of English Language is not clear.", "opta": "the candidates should be", "optb": "do the candidates be", "optc": "should be the candidates", "optd": "are the candidates", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He found the gold coin as he cleans the floor.", "opta": "as he had cleaned", "optb": "while he cleans", "optc": "which he is cleaning", "optd": "while cleaning", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He admired the speed with which he completed the work and appreciating the method adopted by him", "opta": "appreciate the method being adopted", "optb": "appreciated the method adopted", "optc": "appreciate the method of adoption", "optd": "appreciated the method adopting method", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maria unnecessarily picked up a quarrel with Rani and left the party hurried.", "opta": "has picked up", "optb": "picked on", "optc": "picked", "optd": "picking up", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She cooks, washes dishes, does her homework and then relaxing.", "opta": "relaxing then", "optb": "then is relaxing", "optc": "relaxing is then", "optd": "then relaxes", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Acquisition of certain specific skills can be facilitated from general awareness, education to novel situations", "opta": "can be facilitated by", "optb": "may facilitate through", "optc": "can be felicitated with", "optd": "may be felicitated with", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He never has and ever will take such strong measures.", "opta": "had taken nor will ever take", "optb": "had taken and will ever take", "optc": "has and never will take", "optd": "had and ever will take", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Technology must use to feed the forces of change.", "opta": "must be used to feed", "optb": "must have been using to feed", "optc": "must use having fed", "optd": "must be using to feed", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Anyone interested in the use of computers can learn much if you have access to a personal computer.", "opta": "they have access", "optb": "access can be available", "optc": "he or she has access", "optd": "one of them have access", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They are not beware of all the facts", "opta": "are not aware for", "optb": "are not aware of", "optc": "are not to be aware", "optd": "must not to be aware for", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We can not always convey ourselves in simple sentences.", "opta": "cannot always convey", "optb": "can not always express", "optc": "cannot always express", "optd": "can not always communicate", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What does agonise me most is not this criticism, but the trivial reason behind it.", "opta": "most agonising me", "optb": "agonises me most", "optc": "agonising me most", "optd": "I most agonised", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As there was no time, the remaining items were deferred into the next meeting.", "opta": "are deferred till", "optb": "were deferred till", "optc": "were deferred to", "optd": "had deferred with", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Despite of their differences on matters of principles, they all agree on the demand of hike is salary?", "opta": "Despite their", "optb": "Despite of the", "optc": "Despite for their", "optd": "Despite off their", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The man who has committed such a serious crime must get the mostly severe punishment.", "opta": "be getting the mostly severely", "optb": "get the most severe", "optc": "have got the most severely", "optd": "have been getting the severe most", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For many centuries in Indian History there was no city so famous like the city of Ujjain.", "opta": "as", "optb": "such as", "optc": "likewise", "optd": "so like", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We don't know how did the thief made an escape.", "opta": "how the thief did make", "optb": "how the thief does make", "optc": "how the thief made", "optd": "how was the thief made", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He is a singer of repute, but his yesterday's performance was quite disappointing.", "opta": "performances of yesterday were", "optb": "yesterday performance was", "optc": "yesterday performance were", "optd": "performances about yesterday were", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Their earnings are such that they find it difficult to make both ends to meet.", "opta": "to makings both ends meet", "optb": "to make both ends for meeting", "optc": "to make both ends meet", "optd": "for making both ends to meet", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He has received no other message than an urgent telegram asking him to rush his village immediately.", "opta": "asked him to rush his village", "optb": "asking him to have rush his village", "optc": "asking him to rush to his village", "optd": "asking him rushing at his village", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One of the most significant phenomenons of our time has been the development of cinema.", "opta": "phenomenon", "optb": "phenomena", "optc": "phenomenonna", "optd": "phenomenonns", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Had you been told me about your problem, I would have helped you.", "opta": "If you would have told", "optb": "Had you have told", "optc": "had you told", "optd": "If you have told", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was until many years later that Gandhi became a rebel against authority.", "opta": "It was not until many years", "optb": "It was till many years", "optc": "It was not many years", "optd": "Until It was many years", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Anand has the guts to rise from the occasion and come out successfully.", "opta": "in rising from", "optb": "to raise with", "optc": "to rise to", "optd": "to rise against", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you are thinking about investigation overseas, isn't it makes sense to find an experience guide?", "opta": "it is not making", "optb": "doesn't it make", "optc": "does it make", "optd": "is it making", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This is one of the most important inventions of this century.", "opta": "invention of this century", "optb": "invention of these century", "optc": "invention of centuries", "optd": "invention of the centuries", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The orator had been left the auditorium before the audience stood up.", "opta": "had been leaving", "optb": "was left", "optc": "had left", "optd": "would leave", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He dislikes the word dislike, isn't he", "opta": "didn't he", "optb": "doesn't he", "optc": "hasn't he", "optd": "does he", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We must take it granted that Madhu will not come for today's function.", "opta": "take it for granted", "optb": "taking it granted", "optc": "took it as granted", "optd": "have it granted", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The research study is an eye-opener and attempts to acquaint us with the problems of poor nations.", "opta": "attempted to acquaint", "optb": "attempts at acquainting", "optc": "attempt to acquaint", "optd": "attempting to acquaint", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was unanimously resolved that the parties should unitedly undertook launching of popular programmes.", "opta": "should be united undertook", "optb": "should be unitedly undertaken", "optc": "should be unitedly undertake", "optd": "should unitedly undertake", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They continued to work in the field despite of the heavy rains.", "opta": "even though there is heavy rain", "optb": "although heavily rains", "optc": "in spite the heavy rains", "optd": "even though it rained heavily", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is always better to make people realise the importance of discipline than to impose them on it.", "opta": "impose it with them", "optb": "impose them with it", "optc": "imposing them on it", "optd": "impose it on them", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My doctor knew that I would eventually recover and do kind of work I would be doing before", "opta": "would have been doing", "optb": "would have done", "optc": "had been done", "optd": "had been doing", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Later he became unpopular because he tried to lord it on his followers.", "opta": "to lord it for", "optb": "to lord over", "optc": "to lord it over", "optd": "to lord it over on", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The crops are dying; it must not had rained.", "opta": "must had not", "optb": "must not be", "optc": "must not have", "optd": "must not have been", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The courts are actively to safeguard the interests and the rights of the poor.", "opta": "are actively to safeguarding", "optb": "have been actively safeguarding", "optc": "have to active in safeguarding", "optd": "are actively in safeguarding", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The drama had many scenes which were so humorous that it was hardly possible to keep a straight face.", "opta": "hardly possible for keeping", "optb": "hardly impossible for keeping", "optc": "hardly impossible for keep", "optd": "hardly possible keeping", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hardly does the sun rise when the stars disappeared.", "opta": "have the sun rose", "optb": "had the sun risen", "optc": "did the sun rose", "optd": "the sun rose", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You will be late if you do not leave now", "opta": "did not leave", "optb": "left", "optc": "will not leave", "optd": "do not happen to leave", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The train will leave at 8.30 pm, we have been ready by 7.30pm so that, we can reach the station in time.", "opta": "were", "optb": "must be", "optc": "are", "optd": "should have", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All the allegations levelled against him were found to be baseless.", "opta": "level against", "optb": "level with", "optc": "levelling with", "optd": "levelled for", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ramesh is as tall if not,  taller than Mahesh.", "opta": "not as tall but", "optb": "not so tall but as", "optc": "as tall as, if not", "optd": "as if not", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He hesitated to listen to what his brother was saying.", "opta": "listened to hesitate", "optb": "hesitated listen to", "optc": "hesitates to listening", "optd": "is hesitated to listen to", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The prosecution failed in establish in every case today.", "opta": "to", "optb": "on", "optc": "as", "optd": "upon", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One of my drawbacks is that I do not have to tolerance of ambiguity.", "opta": "do not have", "optb": "cannot have", "optc": "am not", "optd": "did not have to", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They should have calmly thought of the advantages that would accrue to them.", "opta": "should have been calm in thinking about", "optb": "should be calmly thought of", "optc": "shall have to calmly thought of", "optd": "should have calmly think of", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The easiest of the thing to do is to ask the address to the postman.", "opta": "of the things to do", "optb": "among the things did", "optc": "of the thing to be done", "optd": "of all the things done", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We demonstrated to them how we were prepared the artistic patterns.", "opta": "are prepared", "optb": "have prepared", "optc": "are preparing", "optd": "had prepared", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Because of his mastery in this field, his suggestions are wide accepted.", "opta": "are widely accepted", "optb": "widely acceptance", "optc": "have widely accepted", "optd": "have been wide accepted", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They felt humiliated because they realised that they had cheated.", "opta": "have been cheated", "optb": "had been cheated", "optc": "had been cheating", "optd": "were to be cheated", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tax evaders should heavily punished as they do it intentionally.", "opta": "should be heavy fined", "optb": "should have heavily fined", "optc": "shall have heavy fine", "optd": "should be heavily fined", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We met him immediately after the session in which he had been given a nice speech.", "opta": "would be giving", "optb": "has been given", "optc": "will have given", "optd": "had given", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For some days the new professor lectured above the heads of his pupils.", "opta": "over the head of", "optb": "over the heads of", "optc": "on the heads of", "optd": "through the heds of", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The accused now flatly denies have admitted his guilt in his first statement.", "opta": "having admitted", "optb": "had admitted", "optc": "have been admitting", "optd": "has admitting", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We were still standing in the queue when the film was beginning.", "opta": "film began", "optb": "film had begun", "optc": "beginning of the film was over", "optd": "film begins", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If I would have realised the nature of job earlier, I would not have accepted it.", "opta": "If I have had", "optb": "In case I would have", "optc": "Had I been", "optd": "Had I", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The crime has growth rapidly in Russia since the disintegration of the communist system.", "opta": "rapid crime has grown", "optb": "crime has grown rapidly", "optc": "crimes grow rapidly", "optd": "crimes have been rapidly grown", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The crime has grown rapidly in Russia since the disintegration of the communist system."}, {"question": "They failed in their attempt to repair the demolished portion of that building.", "opta": "for their attempt to repair", "optb": "in their attempting to repair", "optc": "with their attempt to repair", "optd": "in their attempt for repairs", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I earnestly believe that you will visit our relatives during your forthcoming trip to Mumbai.", "opta": "had hardly believe that", "optb": "sincerely would believe", "optc": "certainly believing that", "optd": "could not believe", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "By such time you finish that chapter, I will write a letter.", "opta": "The time when", "optb": "By the time", "optc": "By that time", "optd": "The time", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Though we have kept in mind to try and maintain most facilities, we would like to request you to kindly bear with us any inconvenience that may be caused.", "opta": "must keep in mind to try and maintain", "optb": "have kept in mind trying and maintain", "optc": "would keep in mind to try and to maintain", "optd": "should have kept in mind to try and to maintain", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The tea-estate administration is in such mess there is no leader to set the things right.", "opta": "in such a mess here", "optb": "in a such mess that here", "optc": "in such a mess that there", "optd": "with such a mess that there", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They examined both the samples very carefully but failed to detect any difference in them.", "opta": "some difference in", "optb": "some difference between", "optc": "any difference between", "optd": "any difference among", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"Friends and comrades, the light has gone away from our lives and there is darkness everywhere\"", "opta": "off", "optb": "out of", "optc": "out from", "optd": "out off", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Because of his ill health, the doctor has advised him not to refrain from  smoking.", "opta": "to not refrain from", "optb": "to resort to", "optc": "to refrain from", "optd": "to be refrained from", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They have a scheme of rewarding the best of the performers every year.", "opta": "a best performer", "optb": "the best among the performer", "optc": "a best among performer", "optd": "the best of the performer", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What happens to all those travellers on the ship was not known?", "opta": "What happened of", "optb": "What happened in", "optc": "What is that happens to", "optd": "What happened to", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Making friends is more rewarding than to make enemies.", "opta": "to be unsociable", "optb": "to be sociable", "optc": "being unsociable", "optd": "making enemies", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The moment they saw me, they were delight", "opta": "had delighted", "optb": "were delighted", "optc": "are delighted", "optd": "have been delighted", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He should not had done it.", "opta": "had not", "optb": "should had not", "optc": "should not have", "optd": "should have", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "No sooner do the bells ring than the curtain rose.", "opta": "did the bell ring", "optb": "did the bells ring", "optc": "had the bell rang", "optd": "had the bell rung", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The moment the manager came to know fraudulent action of his assistant, he order immediately dismissed him.", "opta": "immediately ordered his dismissed", "optb": "ordered his immediate dismissal", "optc": "immediately order dismissal of his", "optd": "ordered for immediately dismissal of him", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The meeting was attended to by all invitees.", "opta": "all attended to by", "optb": "attended by all", "optc": "fully attended to by", "optd": "like attending to all", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If he has to spend five hours in the queue, it was really a wastage.", "opta": "is a really wastage", "optb": "is real a wastage", "optc": "has really a wastage", "optd": "is really a wastage", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The world has seen small real attempt at population and resource planning.", "opta": "few", "optb": "little", "optc": "less", "optd": "a few", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My hair stood off ends when I saw the horrible sight.", "opta": "stood at ends", "optb": "stood on ends", "optc": "stood to ends", "optd": "stands on ends", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The long or short of it is that I do not want to deal with that new firm.", "opta": "The long and short of it", "optb": "The long and short for it", "optc": "The long or short for it", "optd": "The shot and long for it", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Can you tell me why did you not speak the truth?", "opta": "why did not you speak", "optb": "that why did you not speak", "optc": "why you did not speak", "optd": "why did you not spoke", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The people generally try to curry favour with the corrupt but influential person.", "opta": "cook favour", "optb": "seek favour", "optc": "extract favour", "optd": "display favour", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I have got some tea, but I do not have a sugar.", "opta": "some", "optb": "got", "optc": "more", "optd": "any", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Had I realised how close I was to the edge of the valley, I would not have carried the bags there.", "opta": "Had I been realised", "optb": "If I would have realised", "optc": "When I realised", "optd": "Had I had realised", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most of the Indian workers are as healthy as, if not healthier than, British workers.", "opta": "as if healthy as not healthier", "optb": "healthier but not as healthy", "optc": "as healthy, if not healthier", "optd": "so healthy, if not healthier", "opte": "No correction required", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "1. I\n2. immediately\n3. salary\n\n4. my\n5. want", "opta": "43152", "optb": "15432", "optc": "25143", "optd": "42351", "opte": "45132", "ans": "B", "explanation": "\"I want my salary immediately.\""}, {"question": "1. do\n2. today\n3. you\n\n4. must\n5. it", "opta": "34152", "optb": "25413", "optc": "12543", "optd": "51324", "opte": "45213", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\"You must do it today.\""}, {"question": "1. left\n2. the\n3. house\n\n4. he\n5. suddenly", "opta": "12435", "optb": "21354", "optc": "45123", "optd": "52341", "opte": "24135", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\"He suddenly left the house.\""}, {"question": "1. medicine\n2. a\n3. Neeta\n\n4. given\n5. was", "opta": "51423", "optb": "25431", "optc": "15423", "optd": "42531", "opte": "35421", "ans": "E", "explanation": "\"Neeta was given a medicine.\""}, {"question": "1. of\n2. we\n3. heard\n\n4. him\n5. had", "opta": "42351", "optb": "52341", "optc": "25341", "optd": "25431", "opte": "25314", "ans": "E", "explanation": "\"We had heard of him.\""}, {"question": "1. at\n2. it\n3. take\n\n4. once\n5. away", "opta": "23514", "optb": "14352", "optc": "32514", "optd": "53214", "opte": "42315", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\"Take it away at once.\""}, {"question": "1. him\n2. the\n3. to\n\n4. charge\n5. handover", "opta": "42531", "optb": "51342", "optc": "41352", "optd": "45231", "opte": "52431", "ans": "E", "explanation": "\"Handover the charge to him.\""}, {"question": "1. seen\n2. going\n3. you\n\n4. him\n5. have", "opta": "35214", "optb": "35142", "optc": "32514", "optd": "35124", "opte": "53124", "ans": "B", "explanation": "\"You have seen him going.\""}, {"question": "1. bag?\n2. you\n3. seen\n\n4. have\n5. my", "opta": "51432", "optb": "43512", "optc": "42351", "optd": "42153", "opte": "21435", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\"Have you seen my bag?\""}, {"question": "1. killed\n2. a\n3. Jaswant\n\n4. bear\n5. wild", "opta": "31254", "optb": "53124", "optc": "23145", "optd": "43125", "opte": "15234", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\"Jaswant killed a wild bear.\""}, {"question": "1. was\n2. and\n3. Suresh\n\n4. kind\n5. loving", "opta": "31425", "optb": "54213", "optc": "34251", "optd": "15243", "opte": "12345", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\"Suresh was kind and loving.\""}, {"question": "1. tea\n2. have\n3. that\n\n4. some\n5. before", "opta": "43251", "optb": "24315", "optc": "24153", "optd": "52431", "opte": "41325", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\"Have some tea before that.\""}, {"question": "1. not\n2. hotel\n3. comfortable\n\n4. was\n5. the", "opta": "34521", "optb": "53412", "optc": "34152", "optd": "41352", "opte": "52413", "ans": "E", "explanation": "\"The hotel was not comfortable.\""}, {"question": "1. I\n2. help\n3. not\n\n4. you\n5. did", "opta": "24351", "optb": "15324", "optc": "45231", "optd": "43152", "opte": "52431", "ans": "B", "explanation": "\"I did not help you.\""}, {"question": "1. not\n2. Hari\n3. away\n\n4. run\n5. did", "opta": "13542", "optb": "35412", "optc": "52431", "optd": "25143", "opte": "21345", "ans": "D", "explanation": "\"Hari did not run away.\""}, {"question": "The workers are hell bent at getting what is due to them.", "opta": "hell bent on getting", "optb": "hell bent for getting", "optc": "hell bent upon getting", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When it was feared that the serfs might go too far and gain their freedom from serfdom, the protestant leaders joined the princes at crushing them.", "opta": "into crushing", "optb": "in crushing", "optc": "without crushing", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the room had been brighter, I would have been able to read for a while before bed time.", "opta": "If the room was brighter", "optb": "If the room are brighter", "optc": "Had the room been brighter", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The record for the biggest tiger hunt has not been met since 1911 when Lord Hardinge. then Viceroy of India, shot a tiger than measured 11 feet and 6 inches.", "opta": "improved", "optb": "broken", "optc": "bettered", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "his powerful desire brought about his downfall.", "opta": "His intense desire", "optb": "His desire for power", "optc": "His fatal desire", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Will you kindly open the knot?", "opta": "untie", "optb": "break", "optc": "loose", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He sent a word to me that he would be coming late.", "opta": "sent word", "optb": "had sent a word", "optc": "sent words", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "John had told me that he hasn't done it yet.", "opta": "told", "optb": "tells", "optc": "was telling", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If he had time he will call you.", "opta": "would have", "optb": "would have had", "optc": "has", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Will you lend me few rupees in this hour of need?", "opta": "lend me any rupees", "optb": "borrow me a few rupees", "optc": "lend me a few rupees", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During his long discourse, he did not touch that point.", "opta": "touch upon", "optb": "touch on", "optc": "touch of", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He found a wooden broken chair in the room.", "opta": "wooden and broken chair", "optb": "broken wooden chair", "optc": "broken and wooden chair", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He could not look anything in the dark room.", "opta": "look at", "optb": "see", "optc": "see through", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The greatest thing in style is to have a use of metaphor.", "opta": "knowledge", "optb": "command", "optc": "need", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While crossing the highway a five year old child was knocked out by a passing car.", "opta": "away", "optb": "up", "optc": "down", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "hoping not to be disturbed, I sat down in my easy chair to read the book. I won as a prize.", "opta": "I had won as a prize", "optb": "I have won as prize", "optc": "I had to win as a prize", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "More than one person was killed in accident.", "opta": "were killed", "optb": "are killed", "optc": "have been killed", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The expression more than one + noun, though plural in sense, is followed by a singular verb.\nExample: More than one person has died in the accident.\nExplanation provided by: Samy Kumar. Updated on 4th Aug 2018."}, {"question": "No one could explain how a calm and balanced person like him could penetrate such a mindless act on his friends.", "opta": "perpetuate", "optb": "perpetrate", "optc": "precipitate", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Five years ago today, I am sitting in a small Japanese car, driving across Poland towards Berlin.", "opta": "was sitting", "optb": "sat", "optc": "have been sitting", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I took the cycle which he bought yesterday.", "opta": "that he bought yesterday", "optb": "that which he had bought yesterday", "optc": "that he had bought yesterday", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Please make it a point to send you letter at my address.", "opta": "on my address", "optb": "to my address", "optc": "in my address", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you are living near a market place you should be ready to bear the disturbances caused by traffic.", "opta": "to bear upon", "optb": "to bear with", "optc": "to bear away", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I hope you won't object to me watching while you work.", "opta": "against me watching", "optb": "me to watch", "optc": "to my watching", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You cannot forbid him leaving.", "opta": "he leaving", "optb": "his leaving", "optc": "him to leave", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You have come here with a view to insult me.", "opta": "to insulting me", "optb": "of insulting me", "optc": "for insulting me", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "20 kms are not a great distance in these days of fast moving vehicles.", "opta": "is not a great distance", "optb": "is no distance", "optc": "aren't a great distance", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The more they earn, more they spend.", "opta": "More they earn, more they spend", "optb": "More they earn, the more they spend", "optc": "The more they earn, the more they spend", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It became clear that the strangers were heading into a serious disaster.", "opta": "along", "optb": "towards", "optc": "for", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dissidents hold a great problem in every political party.", "opta": "cause", "optb": "give", "optc": "pose", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I would have waited for you at the station if I knew that you would come.", "opta": "had known", "optb": "was knowing", "optc": "have known", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "They are social insects, living in communities, regulated by definite laws, each member of society bearing well-defined and separate part in the work of a colony.", "opta": "who are living in communities", "optb": "living among a community", "optc": "who lives with a community", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Practically every part of the banana tree is used by man.", "opta": "each part", "optb": "any part", "optc": "most part", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My opinion for  the film is that it will bag the national ward.", "opta": "opinion to", "optb": "opinion about", "optc": "opinion on", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The end of the examinations is (an) oppurtunity for celebrating.", "opta": "chance", "optb": "moment", "optc": "occasion", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We were not the wiser for all this effort to explain the case to us.", "opta": "none", "optb": "neither", "optc": "nevertheless", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Whenever my students come across new words, I ask them to look for them in the dictionary.", "opta": "to look it up", "optb": "to look them up", "optc": "to look at them", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We look forward to hear from you.", "opta": "hearing", "optb": "have heard", "optc": "listen", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It was indeed a shock for her, but she has later recovered from it.", "opta": "since", "optb": "then", "optc": "afterwards", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Realising is the significance of technical education for developing country, the government laid aside a large sum on it during the last plan-period.", "opta": "laid up", "optb": "set aside", "optc": "laid out", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you are not clear about the meaning of a word, it is wise to look to a dictionary.", "opta": "look for", "optb": "look at", "optc": "look up", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "You are warned against committing the same mistake again.", "opta": "to commit", "optb": "for committing", "optc": "against to commit", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "No sooner he had returned home then his mother felt happy.", "opta": "had he returned home when", "optb": "he had returned home than", "optc": "did he return home than", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He should move on to the next point, and not harp one sting only.", "opta": "harp on string only", "optb": "harp only one string", "optc": "harp upon one string only", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Either he or I am going.", "opta": "he or I are going", "optb": "he is going or I am", "optc": "I or he is going", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I hope you vividly remember the premier of the film when I, my wife and you were present in the hall.", "opta": "my wife, I and you", "optb": "you, I and my wife", "optc": "my wife, you and I", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To get one's name in the Rowland Ward's book of hunting records was the hot ambition of every serious hunter.", "opta": "extreme", "optb": "burning", "optc": "high", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Taxpayers are to be conscious of their privileges.", "opta": "have to", "optb": "need", "optc": "ought to", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As she was suffering from high fever, she could not face the examination.", "opta": "bear", "optb": "suffer", "optc": "take", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The demonstration passed off peacefully.", "opta": "passed out", "optb": "passed away", "optc": "passed on", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Every time I go in a lift to my sixth floor apartment, I remember the calm and serenity of my ancestral home in the village.", "opta": "move in a lift", "optb": "ascend in a lift", "optc": "take a lift", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In fact, if it hadn't been for his invaluable advice on so many occasions I wouldn't have achieved anything in life.", "opta": "remarkable advice", "optb": "valuable advices", "optc": "priceless suggestion", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Mr. Smith arrived at India in June last year.", "opta": "to", "optb": "by", "optc": "in", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "But in all these cases conversion from scale have well-formulated.", "opta": "can be well-formulated", "optb": "are well-formulated", "optc": "well-formulated", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With a thundering roar the huge rocket soared up from the launching pad.", "opta": "flew up", "optb": "went upwards", "optc": "took off", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There is dearth of woman doctor in our state. We shall have to recruit some from the other states.", "opta": "women doctor", "optb": "woman doctors", "optc": "women doctors", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you cross the line you will be disqualified.", "opta": "cross upon the line", "optb": "cross on the line", "optc": "cross out the line", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Why the dinosaurs died out is not known.", "opta": "it is not known", "optb": "the reason is not known", "optc": "that is not known", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "His father won't be able to leave for Varnasi until they have arrived.", "opta": "until they arrive", "optb": "until they will have arrived", "optc": "until they will arrive", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I will not go to school, if it shall rain tomorrow.", "opta": "it would rain tomorrow", "optb": "it will rain tomorrow", "optc": "it rains tomorrow", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If I stood alone in defence of truth, and the whole world is banded against me and against truth. I would fight them all.", "opta": "will be banded", "optb": "were banded", "optc": "banded", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He has not and can never be in the good books of his employer because he lacks honesty.", "opta": "has not and cannot be", "optb": "has not and can never been", "optc": "has not been and can never be", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the examinations were over Anil and me went to our native town.", "opta": "me and Anil", "optb": "Anil and I", "optc": "I and Anil", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Our office clock is not so correct as it should be it is usually five minutes fast.", "opta": "right", "optb": "regular", "optc": "accurate", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cloud of misfortunes appears to have blown out.", "opta": "over", "optb": "up", "optc": "away", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While we would like that all Indian Children to go to school, we need to ponder why they do not.", "opta": "that all the Indian children", "optb": "if all the children of India", "optc": "all Indian children", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India today many of our intellectuals still talk in terms of the French Revolution and the Rights of Man, not appreciating that much has happened since then.", "opta": "much has been happening", "optb": "much had happened", "optc": "much might happen", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I shall be grateful to you if you are of help to me now.", "opta": "help", "optb": "would help", "optc": "helped", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The logic of Berlin wall already had been undermined but when the news came through that the wall itself had been opened I jumped into a car.", "opta": "had been undetermined already", "optb": "had already been undetermined", "optc": "had been already undetermined", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Other countries have eradicated this disease ten years ago.", "opta": "eradicated", "optb": "had eradicated", "optc": "did eradicated", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Young men and women should get habituated to reading and writing about current affairs.", "opta": "used", "optb": "prepared", "optc": "trained", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The poor villagers have waited in the bitter cold for more than 4 hours now.", "opta": "have been waiting", "optb": "had waited", "optc": "has been waiting", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The old man felled some trees in the garden with hardly no effort at all.", "opta": "hard effort", "optb": "hardly any effort", "optc": "a hardly any effort", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The company goes to great length to ensure that employees can be comfortable in their work environment.", "opta": "are comfortable", "optb": "will be comfortable", "optc": "should be comfortable", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I want you to clearly understand that excuses won't do", "opta": "you clearly to understand", "optb": "you to understand clearly", "optc": "to clearly understand you", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He was fined for careless driving.", "opta": "got fined", "optb": "fined", "optc": "was to be fined", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Although India is still by far a poor country, it can become rich if its natural and human resources are fully utilised.", "opta": "few and far between", "optb": "by and large", "optc": "by and by", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reason why he wrote the letter was because he could not contact him over the phone.", "opta": "why he wrote the letter was since", "optb": "for which he wrote the letter because", "optc": "why he wrote the letter was that", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As he is past his teens now, he can look for himself.", "opta": "after", "optb": "to", "optc": "around", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There is no more room for you in this compartment.", "opta": "there is no more seat", "optb": "there is no more space", "optc": "there is no more accommodation", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most donors would seriously protest any effort to extrapolate from such limited data.", "opta": "protest against", "optb": "protest at", "optc": "protest to", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "She says she's already paid me back, but I can't remember, so I 'll have to take her word.", "opta": "to take her word true", "optb": "to take her at her word", "optc": "to take her word for it", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If you had attended the meeting, you would have benefited a great deal.", "opta": "could benefit", "optb": "would benefit", "optc": "benefited", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This matter admits of no excuse.", "opta": "admits to", "optb": "admits from", "optc": "admits", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If he would have tried he would have succeeded.", "opta": "is tried", "optb": "was tried", "optc": "had tried", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It will be no good trying to find an excuse next time.", "opta": "to try to find", "optb": "to try finding", "optc": "trying finding", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Please remind me of posting these letters to my relatives.", "opta": "by posting", "optb": "to post", "optc": "for posting", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Not a word they spoke to the unfortunate wife about it", "opta": "did they speak", "optb": "they will speak", "optc": "they had spoken", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Not long back, in Japan, a mysterious nerve gas affected a large number of people.", "opta": "effected", "optb": "infected", "optc": "infested", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We had nothing to eat since 8'o clock, this morning.", "opta": "have had nothing", "optb": "has had nothing", "optc": "did have nothing", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "We did not see this movie yet.", "opta": "have seen", "optb": "have not seen", "optc": "have seen", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "My friend was in hospital for a week after an accident.", "opta": "through", "optb": "following", "optc": "for", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All, but her,  had made an attempt.", "opta": "All, but she,", "optb": "All, but herself,", "optc": "All, but her,", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Whatever to our other problems. we have no shortcoming to cheap labour in India.", "opta": "default", "optb": "deficit", "optc": "scarcity", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I have lived in Delhi since I was four.", "opta": "am living", "optb": "lived", "optc": "had lived", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "This telephone number is not existing.", "opta": "has not existed", "optb": "does not exist", "optc": "has not been existing", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "I shall not go untill I am invited.", "opta": "till I am invited", "optb": "Unless I am invited", "optc": "if not I am invited", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "He died in the year 1960 at 11pm on 14 July.", "opta": "on 14 July in the year 1960 at 11pm", "optb": "in the year 1960 on 14 July at 11pm", "optc": "at 11pm on 14 July in the year 1960", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to these reason we are all in favour of universal compulsory education.", "opta": "Out of these reasons", "optb": "For these reasons", "optc": "By these reasons", "optd": "No improvement", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Efficient", "optb": "Treatmeant", "optc": "Beterment", "optd": "Employd", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Foreign", "optb": "Foreine", "optc": "Fariegn", "optd": "Forein", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Ommineous", "optb": "Omineous", "optc": "Ominous", "optd": "Omenous", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Pessenger", "optb": "Passenger", "optc": "Pasanger", "optd": "Pesanger", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Benefitted", "optb": "Benifited", "optc": "Benefited", "optd": "Benefeted", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Treachrous", "optb": "Trecherous", "optc": "Trechearous", "optd": "Treacherous", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Treacherous means guilty of or involving betrayal or deception."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Forcast", "optb": "Forecaste", "optc": "Forcaust", "optd": "Forecast", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Rigerous", "optb": "Rigourous", "optc": "Regerous", "optd": "Rigorous", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Palete", "optb": "Palet", "optc": "Palate", "optd": "Pelate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Bouquete", "optb": "Bouquette", "optc": "Bouquet", "optd": "Boqquet", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Bouquet - bunch of flowers, nosegay, fragrance of a wine, compliment."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Vetarinary", "optb": "Veteninary", "optc": "Vetinary", "optd": "Veterinary", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Veterinary  - pertaining to the medical treatment of animals"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Chancelary", "optb": "Chancellery", "optc": "Chancelery", "optd": "Chancellary", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Excessive", "optb": "Exccessive", "optc": "Exxcesive", "optd": "Excesive", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Indipensable", "optb": "Indipenseble", "optc": "Indispansible", "optd": "Indispensable", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Humorous", "optb": "Ganerous", "optc": "Pupolous", "optd": "Maretorious", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Itinarery", "optb": "Itinerary", "optc": "Itenary", "optd": "Itinarary", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Itinerary - of a trip, of a journey, of travelling, of the route taken on a journey."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Survaillance", "optb": "Surveillance", "optc": "Survellance", "optd": "Surveilance", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Surveillance - careful observation of a person or group, supervision."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Sepulchral", "optb": "Sepilchrle", "optc": "Sepalchrul", "optd": "Sepalchrl", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Sepulchral - pertaining to a grave or tomb. (or) serving as a grave or tomb."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Acommodation", "optb": "Accomodaton", "optc": "Accommodation", "optd": "Acomodation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Accommodation is used to refer to buildings or rooms where people live or stay."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Faithfuly", "optb": "Sincerely", "optc": "Truely", "optd": "Affectionatly", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Klaptomania", "optb": "Klepptomania", "optc": "Kleptemania", "optd": "Kleptomania", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Kleptomania: A recurrent urge to steal, typically without regard for need or profit."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Schedulle", "optb": "Schedeule", "optc": "Schdule", "optd": "Schedule", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Skillful", "optb": "Skillfull", "optc": "Skilfull", "optd": "Skilpull", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Judicious", "optb": "Cancious", "optc": "Dilicous", "optd": "Gracous", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Gaurantee", "optb": "Guarantee", "optc": "Garuntee", "optd": "Guaruntee", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Guarantee - vouch for, give a guarantee, give a warranty, promise, assure"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Friming", "optb": "Burnning", "optc": "Running", "optd": "Fryng", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Dammage", "optb": "Damaige", "optc": "Dammege", "optd": "Damage", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Accomplish", "optb": "Acomplush", "optc": "Ackmplesh", "optd": "Accompalish", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Puerrile", "optb": "Puerrille", "optc": "Purrile", "optd": "Puerile", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Satelite", "optb": "Sattelite", "optc": "Satellite", "optd": "Sattellite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Inoculation", "optb": "Innoculation", "optc": "Inocculation", "optd": "Inocullation", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Velnerable", "optb": "Vulnarable", "optc": "Vulnerable", "optd": "Valnerable", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Simpal", "optb": "Bannar", "optc": "Pattren", "optd": "Modern", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Scripher", "optb": "Scripture", "optc": "Skripture", "optd": "Scriptur", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Comitte", "optb": "Commitee", "optc": "Committee", "optd": "Comiittee", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Exaggerate", "optb": "Exeggrate", "optc": "Exagerate", "optd": "Exadgerate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Asspersion", "optb": "Voluptuous", "optc": "Voguei", "optd": "Equestrain", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Hindrance", "optb": "Hinderrance", "optc": "Hindrence", "optd": "Hinderence", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Parallelled", "optb": "Parralleled", "optc": "Paralleled", "optd": "Paraleled", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Lckadaisicle", "optb": "Lackdaisical", "optc": "Lackadisical", "optd": "Lackadaisical", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Lackadaisical - listless, lacking energy, lacking enthusiasm, disinterested, apathetic, lazy"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Equanimity", "optb": "Equannimity", "optc": "Equanimmity", "optd": "Equinimity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Equanimity is a calm state of mind and attitude to life, so that you never lose your temper or become upset."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Occured", "optb": "Occurad", "optc": "Ocurred", "optd": "Occurred", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Swelte", "optb": "Filpant", "optc": "Licentious", "optd": "Puessile", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Grief", "optb": "Breif", "optc": "Recieve", "optd": "Diceive", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Furnituer", "optb": "Exampel", "optc": "Medicine", "optd": "Sampal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Eflorescence", "optb": "Efllorescence", "optc": "Efflorescence", "optd": "Efflorascence", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Efflorescence - flowering, blossoming"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Exterminatte", "optb": "Inexpliccable", "optc": "Offspring", "optd": "Reffere", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Occasion", "optb": "Occassion", "optc": "Ocasion", "optd": "Ocassion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Entrepreneur", "optb": "Entrapreneur", "optc": "Entrepraneur", "optd": "Enterprenuer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Entrepreneur - one who undertakes and assumes the risk of a business enterprise."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "We discussed about the problem so thoroughly", "optb": "on the eve of the examination", "optc": "that I found it very easy to work it out.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "We discussed the problem so thoroughly"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "An Indian ship", "optb": "laden with merchandise", "optc": "got drowned in the Pacific Ocean.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "sank in the Pacific Ocean"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I could not put up in a hotel", "optb": "because the boarding and lodging charges", "optc": "were exorbitant.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'I could not put up at a hotel'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The Indian radio", "optb": "which was previously controlled by the British rulers", "optc": "is free now from the narrow vested interests.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "is now free from the narrow vested interests."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I had known", "optb": "this yesterday", "optc": "I will have helped him.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "I would have helped him"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A lot of travel delay is caused", "optb": "due to the inefficiency and lack of good management", "optc": "on behalf of the railways.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "on the part of the railways"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "One of the members", "optb": "expressed doubt if", "optc": "the Minister was an atheist.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "expressed doubt that"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I have got", "optb": "my  M.Sc. degree", "optc": "in 1988.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I got"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Having received your letter", "optb": "this morning, we are writing", "optc": "to thank you for the same.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If  you lend him a book", "optb": "he will lend it to some one else", "optc": "and never you will get it back.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "and you will never get it back"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "According to the Bible", "optb": "it is meek and humble", "optc": "who shall inherit the earth.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "it is the meek and the humble"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Do the roses in your garden smell", "optb": "more sweetly", "optc": "than those in ours?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "sweeter"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Block of Residential flats", "optb": "are coming up", "optc": "near our house.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Blocks of Residential flats"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You can get", "optb": "all the information that you want", "optc": "in this book.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "all the information you want"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The students were", "optb": "awaiting for", "optc": "the arrival of the chief guest.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "awaiting"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Sixty miles", "optb": "are", "optc": "a good distance.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Sixty miles is a good distance."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "They have been", "optb": "very close friends", "optc": "until they quarrelled.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'They had been'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When the dentist came in", "optb": "my tooth was stopped aching", "optc": "out of fear that I might lose my tooth.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "my tooth stopped aching"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is the duty of every citizen to do his utmost", "optb": "to defend the hardly-won", "optc": "freedom of the country.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "to defend the hard-won"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "No sooner did I open the door", "optb": "when the rain, heavy and stormy, rushed in", "optc": "making us shiver from head to foot", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "than the rain, heavy and stormy, rushed in"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If a man diligently seeks to come into the contact", "optb": "with the best that has been thought and said in this world", "optc": "he will become simple and unselfish.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If a man diligently seeks to come into contact"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You must", "optb": "remember me", "optc": "to post this letter.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "remind me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I shall certainly", "optb": "write you", "optc": "when I shall reach NewDelhi.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "when I reach New Delhi"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "On the busy Ring Road", "optb": "we witnessed  a collusion", "optc": "between a truck and an auto.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "we witnessed a collision"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Mr.Praful Patel", "optb": "is not attending his office", "optc": "for the last one month.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "has not been attending his office"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He couldn't  but help", "optb": "shedding tears at the plight of the villagers", "optc": "rendered homeless by a devastating cyclone.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He couldn't help"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He will certainly help you", "optb": "if you will ask him", "optc": "in a pleasant manner.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "if you ask him"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The brand propositon now therefore had to be that Keokarpin Antiseptic Cream is more effective", "optb": "because it penetrates deepdown (beinglight and non-sticky) and works from within", "optc": "(because of its ayurvedic ingredients) to keep skin blemish, free and helps cope with cuts nicks, burns and nappy rash.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The brand proposition now therefore is"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Will you please buy", "optb": "some jaggery for me", "optc": "if  you go to the market?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Most of the members at the meeting felt", "optb": "that the group appointed for investigating  the case", "optc": "were not competent to do the job efficiently.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "was not competent to do the job efficiently"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In these  days of inflation", "optb": "a ten rupee's note will not buy you", "optc": "even an ordinary meal.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "a ten rupee note will not buy you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He persisted", "optb": "to do it", "optc": "in spite of my advice", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "in doing it"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The long-awaited moment at last came,", "optb": "and we set out  for the station", "optc": "as merry a band of children as I have ever seen before or since.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "as merry a band of children as I have ever seen since or before"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Our conception of", "optb": "what should a science of mental life be", "optc": "has changed considerably since James' time.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "what a science of mental life should be"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is not coming tomorrow", "optb": "as he is having  a pain in the chest", "optc": "and has to see a doctor.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'and he has to see a doctor'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Many times the news has been published", "optb": "in the papers that the end of the world will be certain", "optc": "if a nuclear war breaks out.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The reason Ram", "optb": "is absent from his duty", "optc": "is because he is unwell.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The reason why Ram"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Azharuddin is one of the finest batsmen", "optb": "that India have produced", "optc": "over the decades.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "that India has produced"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The thief broke in the", "optb": "house at the", "optc": "dead of night", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The thief broke into the"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "May I", "optb": "know who you want", "optc": "to see please", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "know whom you want"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He said that he", "optb": "will mind if", "optc": "I refused his offer.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "would mind if"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Arun's parents died when he was young and", "optb": "he looked after his aunt", "optc": "who had no children.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he was looked after by his aunt"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Though child marriage", "optb": "has been banned.", "optc": "the custom still prevailed among some groups in India.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The custom still prevails among some groups in India"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My papa is", "optb": "in bad mood", "optc": "today", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "in a bad mood"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The warden", "optb": "forbade the student", "optc": "from leaving the hostel.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In spite of several reminders,", "optb": "he did not so far send", "optc": "any reply to me, letters.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he has not so far sent"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "As much as I admire him for his sterling qualities.", "optb": "I cannot excuse him for", "optc": "being unfair to his friends.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Much as I admire him for his sterling qualities."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Please try to understand", "optb": "that the dispute on this issue is between my brother and myself,", "optc": "and concerns nobody else.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "that the dispute on this issue is between my brother and me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "All  the furnitures have been", "optb": "sent to the new house", "optc": "located in a village.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All the furniture have been"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It does not matter how you do it;", "optb": "what I want is that", "optc": "you should finish the work within a month.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "I want that"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Though senior in age,", "optb": "his father is junior  than", "optc": "my father in service.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "his father is junior to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "While walking slowly in the park", "optb": "on a quiet summer afternoon", "optc": "a mad dog suddenly attacked him from behind", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "While he was walking slowly in the park"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Everyone visiting the house asked the young girl", "optb": "how could she kill the wolf", "optc": "single handed and without a weapon.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'how she could kill the wolf'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Many health-conscious people", "optb": "prefer  margarine", "optc": "than butter.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to butter"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The retiring principal asked his old pupils", "optb": "to take the interest in the school", "optc": "after he has retired.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "to take interest in his school"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At present juncture", "optb": "however, the supercomputer", "optc": "would be a costly toy.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "At the present juncture"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The crew were on board,", "optb": "and they soon busied themselves", "optc": "in preparing to meet the storm.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "in preparing to face the storm"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Troy was taken by Greeks", "optb": "this formed the basis of a story", "optc": "which has become famous.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Troy was taken by the Greeks"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am much pleased", "optb": "to know that", "optc": "you have topped the list.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I am very pleased"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He has not been attending", "optb": "English classes", "optc": "since one month", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "since the last one month"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is time", "optb": "we should accept all our people as equals", "optc": "and as partners in the task of building a strong and united nation.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "we should accept all our people as equal"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Twice twelve", "optb": "makes", "optc": "twenty-four", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "make"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Regretfully, profits earned by your company", "optb": "fell by 20 per cent last year", "optc": "despite higher sales.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Regrettably, profits earned by your company"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In a report issued by Indian Statistical Institute,", "optb": "the Iron and Steel Industry is investing more than any other", "optc": "Indian industry in fighting pollution.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Indian industry on fighting pollution"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is going everyday", "optb": "for a morning walk", "optc": "with his friends and neighbours", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He goes everyday"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My father goes", "optb": "to the office", "optc": "five day week.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "five days a week"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If she will be promoted", "optb": "she will get", "optc": "a higher salary.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If she is promoted"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I were him,", "optb": "I would have taught", "optc": "those cheats a lesson.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If I were he, I would have taught those cheats a lesson."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Looking back, I find that among the many impressions ofthe people of India,", "optb": "absorbed while I lived among them,", "optc": "are their reverence for great men and women.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I find that among the many impressions I got of the people of India"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If  you work hard,", "optb": "you will get good grades", "optc": "in examinations.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "C", "explanation": "in the examination"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He managed to make sense of the book", "optb": "even though it was the first time", "optc": "he read anything on the subject.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "when he read anything on the subject"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She reluctantly said that", "optb": "if nobody else was doing it", "optc": "she will do it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "she would do it"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I fail to understand", "optb": "why he replied in negative", "optc": "when the proposal was in his favour.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I failed to understand"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I have", "optb": "an appointment", "optc": "on the 9th September on five o'clock", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "on the 9th September at five o'clock"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "They", "optb": "enjoyed  thoroughly", "optc": "at the party.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "thoroughly enjoyed themselves"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The method suggested in the lecture", "optb": "enables a student to learn more quickly", "optc": "and to have remembered for a longer period of time.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "and to remember for a longer period of time"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My friend asked me", "optb": "if I can lend him my Parker pen", "optc": "for a few days.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "If I could lend him my Parker pen"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The test will not need", "optb": "more than one and half hour", "optc": "to finish.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "B", "explanation": "more than one and a half hour"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The school is", "optb": "within hundred yards", "optc": "from the church.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "within a hundred yards"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "His father died of cholera", "optb": "but his mother also,", "optc": "though very weak, is out of danger.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "but his mother"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The police  broke upon the robbers", "optb": "when they were in the lonely place", "optc": "to divide their booty.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The police came upon the robbers"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since it was his first election campaign, the  candidate was confused;", "optb": "none  could clearly understand", "optc": "either the principles he stood for or the benefits he promised.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Jayesh is getting", "optb": "fatter because he", "optc": "does not take exercise at all", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "fat because he"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He loved", "optb": "none but", "optc": "his neighbour's daughter.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The criminal was", "optb": "caught, convicted the hung", "optc": "in a short period of time.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "within a short period of time"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am thinking of", "optb": "to go to Agra", "optc": "for my cousin's marriage.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "going to Agra"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In management, as you rise higher,", "optb": "the problems you face becomemore and more unstructured and you can't just fall back on", "optc": "the tools you had been", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "the problem you face become more and more unstructured and you can't afford to fall back upon"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Neeraj said", "optb": "that he would rather fail than copying", "optc": "in the examination", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he would rather fail than copy"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I had hoped to have met him yesterday", "optb": "to discuss the matter with him", "optc": "but he was not in his house, and so I could not meet him.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I had hoped to meet him yesterday"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You will come", "optb": "to my party tomorrow,", "optc": "isn't it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "won't you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I wonder", "optb": "how am I", "optc": "to do it", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "how I am going"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is not to blame", "optb": "for what has happened", "optc": "for he is in no way connected with it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He is not to be blamed"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Had you not", "optb": "reached in time", "optc": "he would have lost allour belongings.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "we would have lost all our belongings"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The man told to her", "optb": "that he had not brought his dog", "optc": "out for a walk as he was afraid that it would rain.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The man told her"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I am you", "optb": "I would have seen to it", "optc": "that I won the prize.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If I were you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is unfortunate that", "optb": "many youngsters get", "optc": "addicted to gamble.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "addicted to gambling"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Kamala's fountain-pen", "optb": "is as expensive", "optc": "as Shyama.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "as Shyama's"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When we consider all the factors, which are many,", "optb": "the number of school dropouts", "optc": "are quite disturbing.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "is quite disturbing"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She has never", "optb": "approve of him", "optc": "working as a clerk.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "approved of his"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At the station,", "optb": "I'll hire a coolie", "optc": "to carry my baggages", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to carry my baggage"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The number of marks carried by each question", "optb": "are indicated", "optc": "at the end of the question", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "is indicated"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "There is no question", "optb": "of my failing", "optc": "in the examination.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "of me failing"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She is", "optb": "no longer  popular as she has", "optc": "a friends", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "few friends"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is necessary", "optb": "that everybody", "optc": "must have a house.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "should have a house"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Students should  not take part", "optb": "in party politics and political demonstrations", "optc": "as they interfere in serious study", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'as they interfere with serious study'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "To facilitate exports and improve sales in the domestic market", "optb": "some of the improvised  fabrics and garments fabricated out  from them", "optc": "are displayed in the main pavilion.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "some of the improvised fabrics and garments made from them"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Both of you two", "optb": "can come with me", "optc": "to the play tonight", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Both of you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "No sooner did the sun rise", "optb": "when we took a hasty breakfast", "optc": "and resumed the journey.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "than we took a hasty breakfast"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The charges in this hospital", "optb": "are less than", "optc": "the hospital near my house.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "C", "explanation": "those in the hospital near my house"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The brakes and steering failed", "optb": "and  the bus ran down the hill", "optc": "without anyone being able control it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "without being controlled by anyone"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The tall three girls", "optb": "had left", "optc": "the day before.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The three tall girls"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When he was asked what is wrong with him.", "optb": "he said that he was not well.", "optc": "and asked for leave of absence for one day.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "When he was asked what was wrong with him."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Wherever they go", "optb": "Indians easily adapt to", "optc": "local circumstances.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Indians easily adapt themselves to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Remember that you are part of", "optb": "the team and your success depends on the support", "optc": "you are able to give and get from your other team members.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Remember that you are a part of"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is an established fact that the transcendental American poets and philosophers.", "optb": "who lived in the latter half of the nineteenth century.", "optc": "were more influenced by Indian philosophy, in particular by Upanishadic Philosophy.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Were much influenced by Indian Philosophy in particular by Upanishadic Philosophy."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "That house", "optb": "is costing me", "optc": "ten thousand rupees", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'will cost me' or 'costs me'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Firstly you should", "optb": "think over the meaning of the words", "optc": "and then use them.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'First you should'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is true", "optb": "that God helps those", "optc": "who helps themselves.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "who help themselves"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Happily, zoos were", "optb": "unwilling to cooperate", "optc": "in a scheme that was potentially harmful to animal welfare", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "on a scheme that was potentially harmful to animal welfare"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Neither he", "optb": "nor his father is interested", "optc": "in joining the party.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "With little patience", "optb": "you will be able to", "optc": "cross this hurdle", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "with a little patience"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She was told", "optb": "to give the award to whosoever", "optc": "she thought has done the most  for the downtrodden.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "she thought had done the most for the downtrodden"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At the end of the year", "optb": "every student who had done adequate work", "optc": "was automatically promoted.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The reason why", "optb": "he was rejected", "optc": "was because he was too young.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'was that he was too young'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since we are friends", "optb": "there should be no secret", "optc": "between you and I.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "between you and me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since the attachment of airconditioned sleeping cars to all important trains,", "optb": "travelling became very pleasant,", "optc": "especially during  the summer season.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "travelling has become very pleasant"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If I will have the time", "optb": "I shall try and make it", "optc": "to the zoo this afternoon.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If I have the time"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "We are four brothers and sisters living in this house", "optb": "but neither of us is", "optc": "satisfied with it.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "but none of us are"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A leading textile manufacturer, one  of the fastest growing in the industry.", "optb": "is looking for a marketing manager", "optc": "to look up the marketing network of the company", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to look after the marketing network of the company"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Not one of the hundreds", "optb": "of striking workers.", "optc": "were allowed to go near the factory.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "was allowed to go near the factory"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The single biggest gainer in this process", "optb": "was ITC's Gold Flake Kings sales are estimated", "optc": "to have moved up from 50 million to 200 million sticks per month during 1987 and last year.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "was ITC's Gold Flake Kings sales of which are estimated' or 'whose sales are estimated"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "They left", "optb": "their luggages", "optc": "at the railway station.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "their luggage"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Salim and Antony are such good friends", "optb": "that one  won't go to the pictures.", "optc": "without his coming too.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "without the other's coming too"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She is", "optb": "five years", "optc": "senior than me.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "senior to me"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The President had hardly spoken", "optb": "a few words", "optc": "when the microphone stopped functioning.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Locke's treatises on government toleration and education", "optb": "show a mind fully awake in", "optc": "the possibilities of social  reconstruction.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "show a mind fully alert to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "You will  get", "optb": "all the information", "optc": "if you read this booklet carefully.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "you can get"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "None of the students attending your class", "optb": "answered your questions", "optc": "did  they?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'did one' or 'did any'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "An animal", "optb": "can be just as unhappy in a vast area", "optc": "or in a small one", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "as in a small one"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is working in", "optb": "a bank in New  Delhi", "optc": "for the past several months.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He has been working in"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The  scientist must follow", "optb": "his hunches and his data", "optc": "wherever it may lead.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'whenever they may lead'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Each one of the boys", "optb": "have paid", "optc": "the tuition-fee.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "has paid"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A large scale exchange of nuclear weapons", "optb": "will produce unprecedented amounts of radiation", "optc": "that can penetrate into the biological tissue.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "that can penetrate the biological tissue"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Had I", "optb": "known it earlier", "optc": "I would contact you.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "I would have contacted you"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He asked me", "optb": "why did I call", "optc": "him a rogue.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "why I called"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Were you", "optb": "given a choice", "optc": "or you had to do it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Had you been"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The person which was", "optb": "recommended for the position", "optc": "did not fulfil the prescribed qualifications.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The person who was"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "What does Professor Dhavan", "optb": "spend so many hours", "optc": "in the laboratory?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "why does Professor Dhavan"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The presumption that the average investor does not understand", "optb": "or take interest in the affairs of the company", "optc": "is not correct.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Shanghai is", "optb": "bigger than any city", "optc": "of the world", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "bigger than any other city"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Sheela has scored a first class", "optb": "in her final exams,", "optc": "isn't it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "hasn't she"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "At the moment  the house", "optb": "was burgled the family", "optc": "attended a night  party in the neighbourhood.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The moment the house"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Scarcely had", "optb": "I arrived than", "optc": "the train left.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'I arrived when'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Though he stoutly persisted in denying his involvement in the case,", "optb": "the facts made it  very clear", "optc": "that he had hand in the cruel murder of his wife.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "that he had involved in the cruel murder of his wife."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "One of my  favourite actor", "optb": "is acting", "optc": "in this play also.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "one of my favourite actors"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Emphasis on equality of life ensures", "optb": "for the health and happiness", "optc": "of every individual.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "the health and happiness"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "There was very heavy rain last night,", "optb": "and the rivers have overflown their banks", "optc": "causing severe hardship to the people living by them.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "and the rivers have overflowed their banks"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Every motorist knows", "optb": "road signs---whether symbols or colour codes--- have an immediacy", "optc": "that neither the spoken nor the written word can match.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Supposing if", "optb": "there is no bus.", "optc": "how will you get there?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "if"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Because of the emergency help", "optb": "that the patient received", "optc": "he would have died", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "But for emergency help"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He was in such hurry", "optb": "that he didn't", "optc": "wait for me", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He was in such a hurry"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Will you be", "optb": "at Board meeting", "optc": "on next Wednesday?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "next Wednesday"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Do you know", "optb": "to play", "optc": "the guitar?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "how to play"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Few scientists changed", "optb": "people's ideas as much as", "optc": "Darwin with his Theory of Evolution.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Few scientists have changed"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The course provide", "optb": "not only theoretical inputs", "optc": "but also practical training", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The course provides"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "After the humiliating exposure", "optb": "he hanged his head", "optc": "in shame.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "he hung his head down"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The eminent speaker's speech", "optb": "was broadcasted over", "optc": "all the major radio-stations.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "was broadcast over"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The meeting adjourned abruptly", "optb": "by the Chairman after", "optc": "about three hours of deliberation.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The meeting was abruptly adjourned"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The company has put up an advertisement", "optb": "in newspapers", "optc": "all over the country.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The company has inserted an advertisement"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Will you lend me", "optb": "little money", "optc": "to tide over this crisis.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "a little money"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He gave them no money", "optb": "nor did help them", "optc": "in any way.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "and also he did not help them"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The Sharmas", "optb": "are living in this colony", "optc": "for  the last eight  years.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "have been living in this colony"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "My wife has got", "optb": "a new job", "optc": "a month ago.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "My wife got"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The ability to plan,", "optb": "organise and coordinate work is all fundamental", "optc": "to working within deadline.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to working within the deadline"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A group of friends", "optb": "want to visit", "optc": "the new plant as early as possible.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "wants to visit"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "After leaving his office", "optb": "he went directly", "optc": "to a restaurant.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He was in a hurry", "optb": "because he had an appointment", "optc": "with the company's director.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A body of volunteers", "optb": "have been organised", "optc": "to spread the message of the saint.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "has been organised"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "When I get a cold", "optb": "it  takes me weeks", "optc": "to shake it off.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "When I catch cold"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Another reason for pharmaceutical companies beefing up their", "optb": "OTC (Over the Country) divisions is that prescription drugs with proven safety records which have been reached", "optc": "the end of the their patent protection periodare", "optd": "allowed to be sold without a prescription. No error", "ans": "B", "explanation": "OTC divisions is that prescription drugs with proven safety records which have reached"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "There is still", "optb": "little tea", "optc": "left in the cup.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'a little tea' or 'some tea'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He says that", "optb": "his car does", "optc": "eight kilometers in a litre", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'eight kilometres per litre'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "After opening the door", "optb": "we entered into the room", "optc": "next to the kitchen", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "we entered the room"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Can I lend", "optb": "your pencil", "optc": "for a minute, please?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Can I borrow"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Last month we celebrated", "optb": "the wedding of our sister for whom", "optc": "we have been looking for a suitable alliance for three years.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "we had been looking for a suitable alliance for three years."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "In an English paper", "optb": "examiners should give as much weightage to language", "optc": "as they give to contents.", "optd": "No error", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am hearing", "optb": "a lot about", "optc": "the problem of AIDS these days.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I hear"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Unless you stop to make noise at once", "optb": "I will have no option but to", "optc": "bring the matter to the attention of the police.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Unless you stop making noise at once'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is generally", "optb": "more hungry", "optc": "than she is .", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Since India has gained Independence", "optb": "49 years ago.", "optc": "much progress has been made in almost every field.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Since India gained independence'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He ensured his bank manager", "optb": "that he would soon", "optc": "repay the loan.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He assured his bank manager"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A free press is not a privilege", "optb": "but  the organic necessity", "optc": "in a free society.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "But an organic necessity."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He explained the matter", "optb": "at great length", "optc": "but  I was not the wiser", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "at length"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He will end up his work", "optb": "in the city", "optc": "by the end of the year.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He will end his work"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Even though the shirt is rather expensive", "optb": "but I wish to", "optc": "purchase it with my own money.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "I wish to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He enquired me", "optb": "why I had not seen him the previous day", "optc": "as I had promised to do.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "why I could not seen him the previous day"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I was there", "optb": "many  a time", "optc": "in the past.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'I have been there'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "All the four sons", "optb": "of the old man", "optc": "quarrelled between themselves.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "quarrelled among themselves"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He wanted to work all night", "optb": "but we saw that he was completely worn out", "optc": "and so we persuaded him to stop.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "but we saw that he had completely been worn out"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Mr.Smith was accused for murder", "optb": "but the court found him not guilty", "optc": "and acquitted him.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Mr.Smith was accused of murder'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She sang", "optb": "very well", "optc": "isn't it?", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "didn't she"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I am sure that all my monthly expenses", "optb": "would exceed the income", "optc": "If I do not economic", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If I do not economise"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Whenever you go to a temple", "optb": "you must put off", "optc": "your shoes at the entrance.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "you must take off"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Having read a number of stories", "optb": "about space travel", "optc": "his dream now is about to visit the moon", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "he now dreams of visiting the moon"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The party chief made it a point to state that", "optb": "the Prime Minister and the Union Home Minister should also come.", "optc": "and they see what his party men had seen.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "and see what his party men had seen"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is easy  to see that", "optb": "a lawyer's demeanour in court", "optc": "may be prejudicial against the interests of his client.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is wiring", "optb": "for the", "optc": "last  four hours", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "He has been wiring"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "She walked in", "optb": "the room where the murder", "optc": "had taken place.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "She walked into"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Were he", "optb": "to see you,", "optc": "he would have been surprised.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "if he were"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I could not convince them", "optb": "because they persisted to suggest", "optc": "that I was lying.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "because they persisted in suggesting"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "If  you listen with", "optb": "the question carefully", "optc": "you will be able to answer them easily", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If you listen to"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is difficult", "optb": "for anyone", "optc": "to past time thus.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "to pass time thus"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "The customer handed over", "optb": "a hundred-rupees note", "optc": "to  the shopkeeper.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "a hundred-rupee note"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "Myself and Gopal", "optb": "will take care of", "optc": "the function on sunday.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "'Gopal and I'"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "It is the newspaper", "optb": "that exposes us to the widest  range", "optc": "of human experiences and behaviour.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "A  small baby breathes about", "optb": "45 times per minute while", "optc": "a child of about six years breathes about 25 times per minute.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "I have read", "optb": "too many books", "optc": "by R . K . Narayan.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "so many books"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He was sure", "optb": "that he should", "optc": "win the Prize.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "that he would"}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He is", "optb": "too intelligent", "optc": "to make a mistake.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(solve as per the direction given above)", "opta": "He fell from a running train", "optb": "and would have died", "optc": "if  the villagers did not get him admitted in the nearby hospital immediately.", "optd": "No error.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "if the villagers had not got him immediately admitted to a nearby hospital"}, {"question": "CORPULENT", "opta": "Lean", "optb": "Gaunt", "optc": "Emaciated", "optd": "Obese", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BRIEF", "opta": "Limited", "optb": "Small", "optc": "Little", "optd": "Short", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EMBEZZLE", "opta": "Misappropriate", "optb": "Balance", "optc": "Remunerate", "optd": "Clear", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Main Entry: embezzle\n\nPart of Speech: verb\n\nDefinition: steal money, often from employer\n\nSynonyms: abstract, defalcate, filch, forge, loot, misapply, misappropriate, misuse, peculate, pilfer, purloin, put hand in cookie jar, put hand in till, skim, thieve\n\nAntonyms:\t compensate, give, pay, reimburse, return"}, {"question": "VENT", "opta": "Opening", "optb": "Stodge", "optc": "End", "optd": "Past tense of go", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "AUGUST", "opta": "Common", "optb": "Ridiculous", "optc": "Dignified", "optd": "Petty", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CANNY", "opta": "Obstinate", "optb": "Handsome", "optc": "Clever", "optd": "Stout", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ALERT", "opta": "Energetic", "optb": "Observant", "optc": "Intelligent", "optd": "Watchful", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "WARRIOR", "opta": "Soldier", "optb": "Sailor", "optc": "Pirate", "optd": "Spy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DISTANT", "opta": "Far", "optb": "Removed", "optc": "Reserved", "optd": "Separate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ADVERSITY", "opta": "Failure", "optb": "Helplessness", "optc": "Misfortune", "optd": "Crisis", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Adversity is a very difficult or unfavourable situation."}, {"question": "FAKE", "opta": "Original", "optb": "Imitation", "optc": "Trustworthy", "optd": "Loyal", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INDICT", "opta": "Condemn", "optb": "Reprimand", "optc": "Accuse", "optd": "Allege", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Meanings: formally accuse of a crime (Law); accuse, charge, criticize"}, {"question": "STRINGENT", "opta": "Dry", "optb": "Strained", "optc": "Rigorous", "optd": "Shrill", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LAMENT", "opta": "Complain", "optb": "Comment", "optc": "Condone", "optd": "Console", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HESITATED", "opta": "Stopped", "optb": "Paused", "optc": "Slowed", "optd": "Postponed", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RESCUE", "opta": "Command", "optb": "Help", "optc": "Defence", "optd": "Safety", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ATTEMPT", "opta": "Serve", "optb": "Explore", "optc": "Try", "optd": "Explain", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FORAY", "opta": "Maraud", "optb": "Contest", "optc": "Ranger", "optd": "Intuition", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RECKLESS", "opta": "Courageous", "optb": "Rash", "optc": "Bold", "optd": "Daring", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CONSEQUENCES", "opta": "Results", "optb": "Conclusions", "optc": "Difficulties", "optd": "Applications", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "IMPROVEMENT", "opta": "Advancement", "optb": "Betterment", "optc": "Promotion", "optd": "Preference", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INEBRIATE", "opta": "Dreamy", "optb": "Stupefied", "optc": "Unsteady", "optd": "Drunken", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "STERILE", "opta": "Barren", "optb": "Arid", "optc": "Childless", "optd": "Dry", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ABJECT", "opta": "Challenge", "optb": "Miserable", "optc": "Deny", "optd": "Disobey", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MOVING", "opta": "Taking", "optb": "Toying", "optc": "Shifting", "optd": "Turning", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "IRONIC", "opta": "Inflexible", "optb": "Bitter", "optc": "Good-natured", "optd": "Disguisedly sarcastic", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TIMID", "opta": "Fast", "optb": "Slow", "optc": "Medium", "optd": "Shy", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EXTRICATE", "opta": "Pull", "optb": "Free", "optc": "Tie", "optd": "Complicate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "NEUTRAL", "opta": "Unbiased", "optb": "Non-aligned", "optc": "Undecided", "optd": "Indifferent", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SHALLOW", "opta": "Artificial", "optb": "Superficial", "optc": "Foolish", "optd": "Worthless", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DIVERSION", "opta": "Amusement", "optb": "Distortion", "optc": "Deviation", "optd": "Bylane", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INSOLVENT", "opta": "Poor", "optb": "Bankrupt", "optc": "Penniless", "optd": "Broke", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INEXPLICABLE", "opta": "Confusing", "optb": "Unaccountable", "optc": "Chaotic", "optd": "Unconnected", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FEEBLE", "opta": "Weak", "optb": "Vain", "optc": "Arrogant", "optd": "Sick", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TRANSIENT", "opta": "Transparent", "optb": "Fleeting", "optc": "Feeble", "optd": "Fanciful", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BARE", "opta": "Uncovered", "optb": "Tolerate", "optc": "Clear", "optd": "Neat", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "REPEAL", "opta": "Sanction", "optb": "Perpetuate", "optc": "Pass", "optd": "Cancel", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SALACITY", "opta": "Bliss", "optb": "Depression", "optc": "Indecency", "optd": "Recession", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ECSTATIC", "opta": "Animated", "optb": "Bewildered", "optc": "Enraptured", "optd": "Illful", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ADMONISH", "opta": "Punish", "optb": "Curse", "optc": "Dismiss", "optd": "Reprimand", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DILIGENT", "opta": "Progressive", "optb": "Brilliant", "optc": "Inventive", "optd": "Hard-working", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PIOUS", "opta": "Pure", "optb": "Pretentious", "optc": "Clean", "optd": "Devout", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "BROWSE", "opta": "Heal", "optb": "Deceive", "optc": "Examine", "optd": "Strike", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INFREQUENT", "opta": "Never", "optb": "Usual", "optc": "Rare", "optd": "Sometimes", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Infrequent means happening rarely, uncommon."}, {"question": "RESTRAINT", "opta": "Hindrance", "optb": "Repression", "optc": "Obstacle", "optd": "Restriction", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DEIFY", "opta": "Flatter", "optb": "Challenge", "optc": "Worship", "optd": "Face", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If someone is deified, they are considered to be a god or are regarded with very great respect."}, {"question": "HARBINGER", "opta": "Messenger", "optb": "Steward", "optc": "Forerunner", "optd": "Pilot", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VENUE", "opta": "Place", "optb": "Agenda", "optc": "Time", "optd": "Duration", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CANDID", "opta": "Apparent", "optb": "Explicit", "optc": "Frank", "optd": "Bright", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MELD", "opta": "To soothe", "optb": "Merge", "optc": "Purchase", "optd": "Glisten", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LYNCH", "opta": "Hang", "optb": "Madden", "optc": "Kill", "optd": "Shoot", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TORTURE", "opta": "Torment", "optb": "Chastisement", "optc": "Harassment", "optd": "Terror", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ABUNDANT", "opta": "Ripe", "optb": "Cheap", "optc": "Plenty", "optd": "Absent", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ENTIRE", "opta": "Part", "optb": "Quarter", "optc": "Whole", "optd": "Half", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DESTITUTION", "opta": "Humility", "optb": "Moderation", "optc": "Poverty", "optd": "Beggary", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Destitution: Poverty so extreme that one lacks the means to provide for oneself."}, {"question": "WRETCHED", "opta": "Poor", "optb": "Foolish", "optc": "Insane", "optd": "Strained", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INTIMIDATE", "opta": "To hint", "optb": "Frighten", "optc": "Bluff", "optd": "Harass", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CANTANKEROUS", "opta": "Quarrelsome", "optb": "Rash", "optc": "Disrespectful", "optd": "Noisy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RANT", "opta": "Praise inordinately", "optb": "Formalise", "optc": "To preach noisily", "optd": "Treat with screen", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ZANY", "opta": "Clown", "optb": "Pet", "optc": "Thief", "optd": "Magician", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TACITURNITY", "opta": "Dumbness", "optb": "Changeablemess", "optc": "Hesitation", "optd": "Reserve", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MASSACRE", "opta": "Murder", "optb": "Stab", "optc": "Assassinate", "optd": "Slaughter", "ans": "D", "explanation": "MASSACRE means slaughter, kill a large number of people violently."}, {"question": "KEN", "opta": "Ignorance", "optb": "Witness", "optc": "Trial", "optd": "Knowledge", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "WARY", "opta": "Sad", "optb": "vigilant", "optc": "Distorted", "optd": "Tired", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RABBLE", "opta": "Mob", "optb": "Noise", "optc": "Roar", "optd": "Rubbish", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MAYHEM", "opta": "Jubilation", "optb": "Havoc", "optc": "Excitement", "optd": "Defeat", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PONDER", "opta": "Think", "optb": "Evaluate", "optc": "Anticipate", "optd": "Increase", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CONNOISSEUR", "opta": "Ignorant", "optb": "Lover of art", "optc": "Interpreter", "optd": "Delinquent", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SHIVER", "opta": "Feel", "optb": "Rock", "optc": "Tremble", "optd": "Move", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PRESTIGE", "opta": "Influence", "optb": "Quality", "optc": "Name", "optd": "Wealth", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "STRINGENT", "opta": "Tense", "optb": "Stringly", "optc": "Strict", "optd": "Causing to Shrink", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INSOMNIA", "opta": "Lethargy", "optb": "Sleeplessness", "optc": "Drunkenness", "optd": "Unconsciousness", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LAUD", "opta": "Lord", "optb": "Eulogy", "optc": "Praise", "optd": "Extolled", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "REPERCUSSION", "opta": "Clever reply", "optb": "Recollection", "optc": "Remuneration", "optd": "Reaction", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "IMPROMPTU", "opta": "Offhand", "optb": "Unimportant", "optc": "Unreal", "optd": "Effective", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An impromptu action is one that you do without planning or organizing it in advance."}, {"question": "FRUGALITY", "opta": "Foolishness", "optb": "Extremity", "optc": "Enthusiasm", "optd": "Economy", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CORRESPONDENCE", "opta": "Agreements", "optb": "Contracts", "optc": "Documents", "optd": "Letters", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ASCEND", "opta": "Leap", "optb": "Grow", "optc": "Deviate", "optd": "Mount", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FURORE", "opta": "Excitement", "optb": "Worry", "optc": "Flux", "optd": "Anteroom", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SYNOPSIS", "opta": "Index", "optb": "Mixture", "optc": "Summary", "optd": "Puzzles", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TURN UP", "opta": "Land up", "optb": "Show up", "optc": "Crop up", "optd": "Come up", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VIGOUR", "opta": "Strength", "optb": "Boldness", "optc": "Warmth", "optd": "Enthusism", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GARNISH", "opta": "Paint", "optb": "Garner", "optc": "Adorn", "optd": "Abuse", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MENDACIOUS", "opta": "Full of Confidence", "optb": "False", "optc": "Encouraging", "optd": "Provocative", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GARRULITY", "opta": "Credulity", "optb": "Senility", "optc": "Loquaciousness", "optd": "Speciousness", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MOROSE", "opta": "Annoyed", "optb": "Gloomy", "optc": "Moody", "optd": "Displeased", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VORACIOUS", "opta": "Truthful", "optb": "Gluttonous", "optc": "Funny", "optd": "Venturous", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "AWAKENED", "opta": "Enlightened", "optb": "Realised", "optc": "Shook", "optd": "Waken", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GRATIFY", "opta": "Appreciate", "optb": "Frank", "optc": "Indulge", "optd": "Pacify", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If you are gratified by something, it gives you pleasure or satisfaction."}, {"question": "PRECARIOUS", "opta": "Cautious", "optb": "Critical", "optc": "Perilous", "optd": "Brittle", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INFAMY", "opta": "Dishonour", "optb": "Glory", "optc": "Integrity", "optd": "Reputation", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MASTERLY", "opta": "Crafty", "optb": "Skilful", "optc": "Meaningful", "optd": "Cruel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SCINTILLATING", "opta": "Smouldering", "optb": "Glittering", "optc": "Touching", "optd": "Warming", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TEPID", "opta": "Hot", "optb": "Warm", "optc": "Cold", "optd": "Boiling", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "VORACIOUS", "opta": "Wild", "optb": "Greedy", "optc": "Angry", "optd": "Quick", "ans": "B", "explanation": "If you describe a person, or their appetite for something, as voracious, you mean that they want a lot of something."}, {"question": "UNITE", "opta": "Unfold", "optb": "Unchain", "optc": "Combine", "optd": "Unhinge", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "COMBAT", "opta": "Conflict", "optb": "Quarrel", "optc": "Feud", "optd": "Fight", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "REFECTORY", "opta": "Restaurant", "optb": "Parlour", "optc": "Living Room", "optd": "Dining Room", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A refectory is a large room in a school, university, or other institution, where meals are served and eaten."}, {"question": "UNCOUTH", "opta": "Ungraceful", "optb": "Rough", "optc": "Slovenly", "optd": "Dirty", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ERROR", "opta": "Misadventure", "optb": "Misgiving", "optc": "Ambiguity", "optd": "Blunder", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "COMMENSURATE", "opta": "Measurable", "optb": "Proportionate", "optc": "Begining", "optd": "Appropriate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DEBACLE", "opta": "Collapse", "optb": "Decline", "optc": "Defeat", "optd": "Disgrace", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GERMANE", "opta": "Responsible", "optb": "Logical", "optc": "Possible", "optd": "Relevant", "ans": "D", "explanation": "GERMANE - Relevant to a subject under consideration."}, {"question": "DISTINCTION", "opta": "Diffusion", "optb": "Disagreement", "optc": "Different", "optd": "Degree", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DIVA:OPERA", "opta": "producer:theatre", "optb": "director:drama", "optc": "conductor:bus", "optd": "thespian:play", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GRAIN:SALT", "opta": "shard:pottery", "optb": "shred:wood", "optc": "blades:grass", "optd": "chip:glass", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "THRUST:SPEAR", "opta": "mangle:iron", "optb": "scabbard:sword", "optc": "bow:arrow", "optd": "fence:epee", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PAIN:SEDATIVE", "opta": "comfort:stimulant", "optb": "grief:consolation", "optc": "trance:narcotic", "optd": "ache:extraction", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "LIGHT:BLIND", "opta": "speech:dumb", "optb": "language:deaf", "optc": "tongue:sound", "optd": "voice:vibration", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "WAN:COLOUR", "opta": "corpulent:weight", "optb": "insipid:flavour", "optc": "pallid:complexion", "optd": "enigmatic:puzzle", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "PORK:PIG", "opta": "rooster:chicken", "optb": "mutton:sheep", "optc": "steer:beef", "optd": "lobster:crustacean", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "AFTER:BEFORE", "opta": "first:second", "optb": "present:past", "optc": "contemporary:historic", "optd": "successor:predecessor", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "INDIGENT:WEALTHY", "opta": "angry:rich", "optb": "native:affluent", "optc": "gauche:graceful", "optd": "scholarly:erudite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "DISTANCE:MILE", "opta": "liquid:litre", "optb": "bushel:corn", "optc": "weight:scale", "optd": "fame:television", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "TEN:DECIMAL", "opta": "seven:septet", "optb": "four:quartet", "optc": "two:binary", "optd": "five:quince", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "MUNDANE:SPIRITUAL", "opta": "common:ghostly", "optb": "worldly:unworldly", "optc": "routine:novel", "optd": "secular:clerical", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "ARMY:LOGISTICS", "opta": "business:strategy", "optb": "soldier:students", "optc": "war:logic", "optd": "team:individual", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "GRAVITY:PULL", "opta": "iron:metal", "optb": "north pole:directions", "optc": "magnetism:attraction", "optd": "dust:desert", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FILTER:WATER", "opta": "curtail:activity", "optb": "expunge:book", "optc": "edit:text", "optd": "censor:play", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "HOPE:ASPIRES", "opta": "love:elevates", "optb": "film:flam", "optc": "fib:lie", "optd": "fake:ordinary", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CORPOREAL:SPIRITUAL", "opta": "mesa:plateau", "optb": "moron:savant", "optc": "foreigner:immigrant", "optd": "pedagogue:teacher", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "SYMPHONY:COMPOSER", "opta": "Leonardo:music", "optb": "Fresco:painter", "optc": "colours:pallet", "optd": "art:appreciation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CUP : LIP :: BIRD : ?", "opta": "BUSH", "optb": "GRASS", "optc": "FOREST", "optd": "BEAK", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Cup is used to drink something with the help of lips. Similarly birds collects grass with the help of beak to make her nest."}, {"question": "Flow : River :: Stagnant : ?", "opta": "Rain", "optb": "Stream", "optc": "Pool", "optd": "Canal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As Water of a River flows similarly water of Pool is Stagnant."}, {"question": "Paw : Cat :: Hoof : ?", "opta": "Lamb", "optb": "Elephant", "optc": "Lion", "optd": "Horse", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As cat has Paw similarly Horse has Hoof."}, {"question": "Ornithologist : Bird :: Archealogist : ?", "opta": "Islands", "optb": "Mediators", "optc": "Archealogy", "optd": "Aquatic", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As Ornithologist is a specialist of Birds similarly Archealogist is a specialist of Archealogy."}, {"question": "Peacock : India :: Bear : ?", "opta": "Australia", "optb": "America", "optc": "Russia", "optd": "England", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As Peacock is the national bird of India, similarly Bear is the national animal of Russia."}, {"question": "REASON : SFBTPO :: THINK : ?", "opta": "SGHMJ", "optb": "UIJOL", "optc": "UHNKI", "optd": "UJKPM", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Carbon : Diamond :: Corundum : ?", "opta": "Garnet", "optb": "Ruby", "optc": "Pukhraj", "optd": "Pearl", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As Diamond is made of Carbon similarly Ruby is made of Corundum."}, {"question": "NATION : ANTINO :: HUNGRY : ?", "opta": "HNUGRY", "optb": "UHNGYR", "optc": "YRNGUH", "optd": "UNHGYR", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Architect : Building :: Sculptor : ?", "opta": "Museum", "optb": "Stone", "optc": "Chisel", "optd": "Statue", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As 'Architect' makes 'Building' similarly 'Sculptor' makes 'Statue'."}, {"question": "Eye : Myopia :: Teeth : ?", "opta": "Pyorrhoea", "optb": "Cataract", "optc": "Trachoma", "optd": "Eczema", "ans": "A", "explanation": "As Myopia is disease of eye similarly pyorrhoea is a disease of teeth."}, {"question": "Conference : Chairman :: Newspaper : ?", "opta": "Reporter", "optb": "Distributor", "optc": "Printer", "optd": "Editor", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As Chairman is the highest authority in a conference similarly Editor is in Newspaper."}, {"question": "Safe : Secure :: Protect : ?", "opta": "Lock", "optb": "Sure", "optc": "Guard", "optd": "Conserve", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As safe ans secure have same meaning in the same way protect and guard have same meaning."}, {"question": "Master : OCUVGT :: LABOUR : ?", "opta": "NCDQWT", "optb": "NDERWT", "optc": "NBERWT", "optd": "NEDRWT", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Microphone : Loud :: Microscope : ?", "opta": "Elongate", "optb": "Investigate", "optc": "Magnify", "optd": "Examine", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As Microphone makes sound louder similarly Microscope makes the object magnified."}, {"question": "Melt : Liquid :: Freeze : ?", "opta": "Ice", "optb": "Condense", "optc": "Solid", "optd": "Force", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As on melting, liquid is formed similarly on freezing solid is formed."}, {"question": "College : Student :: Hospital : ?", "opta": "Nurse", "optb": "Doctor", "optc": "Treatment", "optd": "Patient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As Students read in College similarly Patients are treated in Hospital."}, {"question": "Tree : Forest :: Grass : ?", "opta": "Lawn", "optb": "Garden", "optc": "Park", "optd": "Field", "ans": "A", "explanation": "As Tree is found in Forest similarly Grass is found in Lawn."}, {"question": "South : North-West :: West : ?", "opta": "North", "optb": "South-West", "optc": "North-East", "optd": "East", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As North-West is 135o clockwise from South in the same were North-East is 135o clockwise from the West."}, {"question": "Cloth : Mill :: Newspaper : ?", "opta": "Editor", "optb": "Reader", "optc": "Paper", "optd": "Press", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As Cloth is made in a Mill, similarly Newspaper is printed in press."}, {"question": "Country : President :: State : ?", "opta": "Governor", "optb": "M.P", "optc": "Legislator", "optd": "Minister", "ans": "A", "explanation": "As President is the nominal head of a country, similarly Governer is the nominal head of a State."}, {"question": "Race : Fatigue :: Fast : ?", "opta": "Food", "optb": "Laziness", "optc": "Hunger", "optd": "Race", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As the result of Race is Fatigue similarly the result of Fast is Hunger."}, {"question": "Peace : Chaos :: Creation : ?", "opta": "Build", "optb": "Construction", "optc": "Destruction", "optd": "Manufacture", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As opposite meaning of peace is chaos similarly opposite meaning of creation is destruction."}, {"question": "Tiger : Forest :: Otter : ?", "opta": "Cage", "optb": "Sky", "optc": "Nest", "optd": "Water", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As Tiger is found in Forest similarly  Otter is found in the water."}, {"question": "Poles : Magnet :: ? : Battery", "opta": "Cells", "optb": "Power", "optc": "Terminals", "optd": "Energy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As magnet has poles similarly battery has terminals."}, {"question": "Cassock : Priest :: ? : Graduate", "opta": "Cap", "optb": "Tie", "optc": "Coat", "optd": "Gown", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A Priest wears cassock while Graduate wears gown."}, {"question": "Ice : Coldness :: Earth : ?", "opta": "Weight", "optb": "Jungle", "optc": "Gravitatism", "optd": "Sea", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As effect of Ice is coldness similarly the effect of Earth is gravitation."}, {"question": "Parts : Strap :: Wolf : ?", "opta": "Fox", "optb": "Animal", "optc": "Wood", "optd": "Flow", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Physician : Treatment :: Judge : ?", "opta": "Punishment", "optb": "Judgement", "optc": "Lawyer", "optd": "Court", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As Physician does the treatment similarly Judge delivers the judgement."}, {"question": "The total of the ages of Amar, Akbar and Anthony is 80 years. What was the total of their ages three years ago ?", "opta": "71 years", "optb": "72 years", "optc": "74 years", "optd": "77 years", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Required sum = (80 - 3 x 3) years = (80 - 9) years = 71 years."}, {"question": "Two bus tickets from city A to B and three tickets from city A to C cost Rs. 77 but three tickets from city A to B and two tickets from city A to C cost Rs. 73. What are the fares for cities B and C from A ?", "opta": "Rs. 4, Rs. 23", "optb": "Rs. 13, Rs. 17", "optc": "Rs. 15, Rs. 14", "optd": "Rs. 17, Rs. 13", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Let Rs. x be the fare of city B from city A and Rs. y be the fare of city C from city A.Then, 2x + 3y = 77           ...(i)       and3x + 2y = 73           ...(ii)Multiplying (i) by 3 and (ii) by 2 and subtracting, we get: 5y = 85   or   y = 17.Putting y = 17 in (i), we get: x = 13."}, {"question": "An institute organised a fete and 1/5 of the girls and 1/8 of the boys participated in the same. What fraction of the total number of students took part in the fete ?", "opta": "2/13", "optb": "13/40", "optc": "Data inadequate", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A number of friends decided to go on a picnic and planned to spend Rs. 96 on eatables. Four of them, however, did not turn up. As a consequence, the remaining ones had to contribute Rs. 4 each extra. The number of those who attended the picnic was", "opta": "8", "optb": "12", "optc": "16", "optd": "24", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A, B, C, D and E play a game of cards. A says to B, \"If you give me three cards, you will have as many as E has and if I give you three cards, you will have as many as D has.\" A and B together have 10 cards more than what D and E together have. If B has two cards more than what C has and the total number of cards be 133, how many cards does B have ?", "opta": "22", "optb": "23", "optc": "25", "optd": "35", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Clearly, we have :B-3 = E                                    ...(i)B + 3 = D                                      ...(ii)A+B = D + E+10                    ...(iii)B = C + 2                                      ...(iv)A+B + C + D + E= 133            ...(v)From (i) and (ii), we have : 2 B = D + E  ...(vi)From (iii) and (vi), we have : A = B + 10  ...(vii)Using (iv), (vi) and (vii) in (v), we get:(B + 10) + B + (B - 2) + 2B = 133    5B = 125    B = 25."}, {"question": "A pineapple costs Rs. 7 each. A watermelon costs Rs. 5 each. X spends Rs. 38 on these fruits. The number of pineapples purchased is", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "Data inadequate", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A woman says, \"If you reverse my own age, the figures represent my husband's age. He is, of course, senior to me and the difference between our ages is one-eleventh of their sum.\" The woman's age is", "opta": "23 years", "optb": "34 years", "optc": "45 years", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Let x and y be the ten's and unit's digits respectively of the numeral denoting the woman's age.Then, woman's age = (10X + y) years; husband's age = (10y + x) years.Therefore  (10y + x)- (10X + y) = (1/11) (10y + x + 10x + y)  (9y-9x) = (1/11)(11y + 11x) = (x + y)  10x = 8y  x = (4/5)yClearly, y should be a single-digit multiple of 5, which is 5.So, x = 4, y = 5.Hence, woman's age = 10x + y = 45 years."}, {"question": "A girl counted in the following way on the fingers of her left hand : She started by calling the thumb 1, the index finger 2, middle finger 3, ring finger 4, little finger 5 and then reversed direction calling the ring finger 6, middle finger 7 and so on. She counted upto 1994. She ended counting on which finger ?", "opta": "Thumb", "optb": "Index finger", "optc": "Middle finger", "optd": "Ring finger", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, while counting, the numbers associated to the thumb will be : 1, 9,17, 25,.....i.e. numbers of the form (8n + 1).Since 1994 = 249 x 8 + 2, so 1993 shall correspond to the thumb and 1994 to the index finger."}, {"question": "A man has Rs. 480 in the denominations of one-rupee notes, five-rupee notes and ten-rupee notes. The number of notes of each denomination is equal. What is the total number of notes that he has ?", "opta": "45", "optb": "60", "optc": "75", "optd": "90", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Let number of notes of each denomination be x.Then, x + 5x + 10x = 480   16x = 480   x = 30.Hence, total number of notes = 3x = 90."}, {"question": "What is the product of all the numbers in the dial of a telephone ?", "opta": "1,58,480", "optb": "1,59,450", "optc": "1,59,480", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since one of the numbers on the dial of a telephone is zero, so the product of all the numbers on it is 0."}, {"question": "A is 3 years older to B and 3 years younger to C, while B and D are twins. How many years older is C to D?", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "6", "optd": "12", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since B and D are twins, so B = D.Now, A = B + 3 and A = C - 3.Thus, B + 3 = C - 3   D + 3 = C-3   C - D = 6."}, {"question": "The 30 members of a club decided to play a badminton singles tournament. Every time a member loses a game he is out of the tournament. There are no ties. What is the minimum number of matches that must be played to determine the winner ?", "opta": "15", "optb": "29", "optc": "61", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, every member except one (i.e. the winner) must lose one game to decide the winner. Thus, minimum number of matches to be played = 30 - 1 = 29."}, {"question": "In a garden, there are 10 rows and 12 columns of mango trees. The distance between the two trees is 2 metres and a distance of one metre is left from all sides of the boundary of the garden. The length of the garden is", "opta": "20 m", "optb": "22 m", "optc": "24 m", "optd": "26 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Each row contains 12 plants.There are 11 gapes between the two corner trees (11 x 2) metres and 1 metre on each side is left.Therefore Length = (22 + 2) m = 24 m."}, {"question": "12 year old Manick is three times as old as his brother Rahul. How old will Manick be when he is twice as old as Rahul ?", "opta": "14 years", "optb": "16 years", "optc": "18 years", "optd": "20 years", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Manick's present age = 12 years, Rahul's present age = 4 years.Let Manick be twice as old as Rahul after x years from now.Then, 12 + x = 2 (4 + x)   12 + x = 8 + 2x  x = 4.Hence, Manick's required age = 12 + x = 16 years."}, {"question": "A tailor had a number of shirt pieces to cut from a roll of fabric. He cut each roll of equal length into 10 pieces. He cut at the rate of 45 cuts a minute. How many rolls would be cut in 24 minutes ?", "opta": "32 rolls", "optb": "54 rolls", "optc": "108 rolls", "optd": "120 rolls", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Number of cuts made to cut a roll into 10 pieces = 9.Therefore Required number of rolls = (45 x 24)/9 = 120."}, {"question": "In a class of 60 students, the number of boys and girls participating in the annual sports is in the ratio 3 : 2 respectively. The number of girls not participating in the sports is 5 more than the number of boys not participating in the sports. If the number of boys participating in the sports is 15, then how many girls are there in the class ?", "opta": "20", "optb": "25", "optc": "30", "optd": "Data inadequate", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Let the number of boys and girls participating in sports be 3x and 2x respectively.Then, 3x = 15 or x = 5.So, number of girls participating in sports = 2x = 10.Number of students not participating in sports = 60 - (15 + 10) = 35.Let number of boys not participating in sports be y.Then, number of girls not participating in sports = (35 -y).Therefore (35 - y) = y + 5    2y  30   y = 15.So, number of girls not participating in sports = (35 - 15) = 20.Hence, total number of girls in the class = (10 + 20) = 30."}, {"question": "There are deer and peacocks in a zoo. By counting heads they are 80. The number of their legs is 200. How many peacocks are there ?", "opta": "20", "optb": "30", "optc": "50", "optd": "60", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Let x and y be the number of deer and peacocks in the zoo respectively. Then,x + y = 80 ...(i) and4x + 2y = 200   or   2x + y = 100 ...(ii)Solving (i) and (ii), we get) x = 20, y = 60."}, {"question": "A man wears socks of two colours - Black and brown. He has altogether 20 black socks and 20 brown socks in a drawer. Supposing he has to take out the socks in the dark, how many must he take out to be sure that he has a matching pair ?", "opta": "3", "optb": "20", "optc": "39", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since there are socks of only two colours, so two out of any three socks must always be of the same colour."}, {"question": "A motorist knows four different routes from Bristol to Birmingham. From Birmingham to Sheffield he knows three different routes and from Sheffield to Carlisle he knows two different routes. How many routes does he know from Bristol to Carlisle ?", "opta": "4", "optb": "8", "optc": "12", "optd": "24", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Total number of routes from Bristol to Carlisle = (4 x 3 x 2) = 24."}, {"question": "Mac has \u00a3 3 more than Ken, but then Ken wins on the horses and trebles his money, so that he now has \u00a3 2 more than the original amount of money that the two boys had between them. How much money did Mac and Ken have between them before Ken's win ?", "opta": "\u00a3 9", "optb": "\u00a3 11", "optc": "\u00a3 13", "optd": "\u00a3 15", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Let money with Ken = x. Then, money with Mac = x + \u00a3 3.Now, 3x = (x + x + \u00a3 3) + \u00a3 2   x = \u00a3 5.Therefore Total money with Mac and Ken = 2x + \u00a3 3 = \u00a3 13."}, {"question": "In a class, there are 18 boys who are over 160 cm tall. If these constitute three-fourths of the boys and the total number of boys is two-thirds of the total number of students in the class, what is the number of girls in the class ?", "opta": "6", "optb": "12", "optc": "18", "optd": "24", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Let the number of boys be x. Then, (3/4)x = 18   or   x = 18 x(4/3) = 24.If total number of students is y, then (2/3) y = 24   or   y = 24 x (3/2) = 36.Therefore Number of girls in the class = (36 - 24) = 12."}, {"question": "A father is now three times as old as his son. Five years back, he was four times as old as his son. The age of the son (in years) is", "opta": "12", "optb": "15", "optc": "18", "optd": "20", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Let son's age be x years. Then, father's age = (3x) years.Five years ago, father's age = (3x - 5) years and son's age = (x - 5) years.So, 3x - 5 = 4 (x - 5)  3x - 5 = 4x - 20   x = 15."}, {"question": "A waiter's salary consists of his salary and tips. During one week his tips were 5/4 of his salary. What fraction of his income came from tips ?", "opta": "4/9", "optb": "5/4", "optc": "5/8", "optd": "5/9", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "If you write down all the numbers from 1 to 100, then how many times do you write 3 ?", "opta": "11", "optb": "18", "optc": "20", "optd": "21", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Clearly, from 1 to 100, there are ten numbers with 3 as the unit's digit- 3, 13, 23, 33, 43, 53, 63, 73, 83, 93; and ten numbers with 3 as the ten's digit - 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39.So, required number = 10 + 10 = 20."}, {"question": "If 100 cats kill 100 mice in 100 days, then 4 cats would kill 4 mice in how many days ?", "opta": "1 day", "optb": "4 days", "optc": "40 days", "optd": "100 days", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Five bells begin to toll together and toll respectively at intervals of 6, 5, 7, 10 and 12 seconds. How many times will they toll together in one hour excluding the one at the start ?", "opta": "7 times", "optb": "8 times", "optc": "9 times", "optd": "11 times", "ans": "B", "explanation": "L.C.M. of 6, 5, 7, 10 and 12 is 420.So, the bells will toll together after every 420 seconds i.e. 7 minutes.Now, 7 x 8 = 56 and 7 x 9 = 63.Thus, in 1-hour (or 60 minutes), the bells will toll together 8 times, excluding the one at the start."}, {"question": "A bus starts from city X. The number of women in the bus is half of the number of men. In city Y, 10 men leave the bus and five women enter. Now, number of men and women is equal. In the beginning, how many passengers entered the bus ?", "opta": "15", "optb": "30", "optc": "36", "optd": "45", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Originally, let number of women = x. Then, number of men = 2x.So, in city Y, we have : (2x - 10) = (x + 5)   or   x - 15.Therefore Total number of passengers in the beginning = (x + 2x) = 3x = 45."}, {"question": "A, B, C, D and E play a game of cards. A says to B, \"If you give me 3 cards, you will have as many as I have at this moment while if D takes 5 cards from you, he will have as many as E has.\" A and C together have twice as many cards as E has. B and D together also have the same number of cards as A and C taken together. If together they have 150 cards, how many cards has C got ?", "opta": "28", "optb": "29", "optc": "31", "optd": "35", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, we have :A = B - 3 ...(i)D + 5 = E ...(ii)A+C = 2E ...(iii)B + D = A+C = 2E ...(iv)A+B + C + D + E=150 ...(v)From (iii), (iv) and (v), we get: 5E = 150   or   E = 30.Putting E = 30 in (ii), we get: D = 25.Putting E = 30 and D = 25 in (iv), we get: B = 35.Putting B = 35 in (i), we get: A = 32.Putting A = 32 and E = 30 in (iii), we get: C = 28."}, {"question": "A farmer built a fence around his square plot. He used 27 fence poles on each side of the square. How many poles did he need altogether ?", "opta": "100", "optb": "104", "optc": "108", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since each pole at the corner of the plot is common to its two sides, so we have :Total number of poles needed = 27 x 4 - 4 = 108 - 4 = 104."}, {"question": "In a city, 40% of the adults are illiterate while 85% of the children are literate. If the ratio of the adults to that of the children is 2 : 3, then what percent of the population is literate ?", "opta": "20%", "optb": "25%", "optc": "50%", "optd": "75%", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A is three times as old as B. C was twice-as old as A four years ago. In four years' time, A will be 31. What are the present ages of B and C ?", "opta": "9, 46", "optb": "9, 50", "optc": "10, 46", "optd": "10, 50", "ans": "B", "explanation": "We have : A = 3B ...(i) andC - 4 = 2 (A - 4) ...(ii)Also, A + 4 = 31 or  A= 31-4 = 27.Putting A = 27 in (i), we get: B = 9.Putting A = 27 in (ii), we get C = 50."}, {"question": "Today is Varun's birthday. One year, from today he will be twice as old as he was 12 years ago. How old is Varun today ?", "opta": "20 years", "optb": "22 years", "optc": "25 years", "optd": "27 years", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Let Varan's age today = x years.Then, Varan's age after 1 year = (x + 1) years.Therefore x + 1 = 2 (x - 12)  x + 1 = 2x - 24  x = 25."}, {"question": "A bird shooter was askgd how many birds he had in the bag. He replied that there were all sparrows but six, all pigeons but six, and all ducks but six. How many birds he had in the bag in all?", "opta": "9", "optb": "18", "optc": "27", "optd": "36", "ans": "A", "explanation": "There were all sparrows but six' means that six birds were not sparrows but only pigeons and ducks.Similarly, number of sparrows + number of ducks = 6 and number of sparrows + number of pigeons = 6.This is possible when there are 3 sparrows, 3 pigeons and 3 ducks i.e. 9 birds in all."}, {"question": "Mr. Johnson was to earn \u00a3 300 and a free holiday for seven weeks' work. He worked for only 4 weeks and earned \u00a3 30 and a free holiday. What was the value of the holiday?", "opta": "\u00a3 300", "optb": "\u00a3 330", "optc": "\u00a3 360", "optd": "\u00a3 420", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "What is the smallest number of ducks that could swim in this formation - two ducks in front of a duck, two ducks behind a duck and a duck between two ducks ?", "opta": "3", "optb": "5", "optc": "7", "optd": "9", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the smallest such number is 3.Three ducks can be arranged as shown above to satisfy all the three given conditions."}, {"question": "Three friends had dinner at a restaurant. When the bill was received, Amita paid 2/3 as much as Veena paid and Veena paid 1/2 as much as Tanya paid. What faction of the bill did Veena pay ?", "opta": "1/3", "optb": "3/11", "optc": "12/13", "optd": "5/8", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "In a class, 20% of the members own only two cars each, 40% of the remaining own three cars each and the remaining members own only one car each. Which of the following statements is definitely true from the given statements ?", "opta": "Only 20% of the total members own three cars each.", "optb": "48% of the total members own only one car each.", "optc": "60% of the total members own at least two cars each.", "optd": "80% of the total members own at least one car.", "opte": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Let total number of members be 100,Then, number of members owning only 2 cars = 20.Number of members owning 3 cars = 40% of 80 = 32.Number of members owning only 1 car = 100 - (20 + 32) = 48.Thus, 48% of the total members own one car each."}, {"question": "When Rahul was born, his father was 32 years older than his brother and his mother was 25 years older than his sister. If Rahul's brother is 6 years older than him and his mother is 3 years younger than his father, how old was Rahul's sister when he was born ?", "opta": "7 years", "optb": "10 years", "optc": "14 years", "optd": "19 years", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When Rahul was born, his brother's age = 6 years; his father's age = (6 + 32) years = 38 years, his mother's age = (38 - 3) years = 35 years; his sister's age = (35 - 25) years = 10 years."}, {"question": "A certain number of horses and an equal number of men are going somewhere. Half of the owners are on their horses' back while the remaining ones are walking along leading their horses. If the number of legs walking on the ground is 70, how many horses are there ?", "opta": "10", "optb": "12", "optc": "14", "optd": "16", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Let number of horses = number of men = x.Then, number of legs = 4x + 2 x (x/2) = 5x.So, 5X = 70   or   x = 14."}, {"question": "Ravi's brother is 3 years senior to him. His father was 28 years of age when his sister was born while his mother was 26 years of age when he was born. If his sister was 4 years of age when his brother was born, what were the ages of Ravi's father and mother respectively when his brother was born ?", "opta": "32 years, 23 years", "optb": "32 years, 29 years", "optc": "35 years, 29 years", "optd": "35 years, 33 years", "ans": "A", "explanation": "When Ravi's brother was born, let Ravi's father's age = x years and mother's age = y years.Then, sister's age = (x - 28) years. So, x - 28 = 4   or   x = 32.Ravi's age = (y - 26) years. Age of Ravi's brother = (y - 26 + 3) years = (y - 23) years.Now, when Ravi's brother was born, his age = 0 i.e. y - 23 = 0   or   y = 23."}, {"question": "The number of boys in a class is three times the number of girls. Which one of the following numbers cannot represent the total number of children in the class ?", "opta": "48", "optb": "44", "optc": "42", "optd": "40", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Let number of girls = x and number of boys = 3x.Then, 3x + x = 4x = total number of students.Thus, to find exact value of x, the total number of students must be divisible by 4."}, {"question": "A shepherd had 17 sheep. All but nine died. How many was he left with ?", "opta": "Nil", "optb": "8", "optc": "9", "optd": "17", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'All but nine died' means 'All except nine died' i.e. 9 sheep remained alive."}, {"question": "In a family, the father took 1/4 of the cake and he had 3 times as much as each of the other members had. The total number of family members is", "opta": "3", "optb": "7", "optc": "10", "optd": "12", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "In three coloured boxes - Red, Green and Blue, 108 balls are placed. There are twice as many balls in the green and red boxes combined as there are in the blue box and twice as many in the blue box as there are in the red box. How many balls are there in the green box ?", "opta": "18", "optb": "36", "optc": "45", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Let R, G and B represent the number of balls in red, green and blue boxes respectively.Then, .R + G + B = 108       ...(i),G + R = 2B       ...(ii)B = 2R       ...(iii)From (ii) and (iii), we have G + R = 2x 2R = 4R   or   G = 3R.Putting G = 3R and B = 2R in (i), we get:R + 3R + 2R = 108      6R = 108      R = 18.Therefore Number of balls in green box = G = 3R = (3 x 18) = 54."}, {"question": "In a cricket match, five batsmen A, B, C, D and E scored an average of 36 runs. D Scored 5 more than E; E scored 8 fewer than A; B scored as many as D and E combined; and B and C scored 107 between them. How many runs did E score ?", "opta": "62", "optb": "45", "optc": "28", "optd": "20", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Total runs scored = (36 x 5) = 180.Let the runs scored by E be x.Then, runs scored by D = x + 5; runs scored by A = x + 8;runs scored by B = x + x + 5 = 2x + 5;runs scored by C = (107 - B) = 107 - (2x + 5) = 102 - 2x.So, total runs = (x + 8) + (2x + 5) + (102 - 2x) + (x + 5) + x = 3x + 120.Therefore 3x + 120 =180  3X = 60  x = 20."}, {"question": "The total number of digits used in numbering the pages of a book having 366 pages is", "opta": "732", "optb": "990", "optc": "1098", "optd": "1305", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Total number of digits= (No. of digits in 1- digit page nos. + No. of digits in 2-digit page nos. + No. of digits in 3- digit page nos.)= (1 x 9 + 2 x 90 + 3 x 267) = (9 + 180 + 801) = 990."}, {"question": "In a family, each daughter has the same number of brothers as she has sisters and each son has twice as many sisters as he has brothers. How many sons are there in the family ?", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Let d and s represent the number of daughters and sons respectively.Then, we have :d - 1 = s       and       2 (s - 1) = d.Solving these two equations, we get: d = 4, s = 3."}, {"question": "At a dinner party every two guests used a bowl of rice between them, every three guests used a bowl of dal between them and every four used a bowl of meat between them. There were altogether 65 dishes. How many guests were present at the party ?", "opta": "60", "optb": "65", "optc": "90", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Ayush was born two years after his father's marriage. His mother is five years younger than his father but 20 years older than Ayush who is 10 years old. At what age did the father get married ?", "opta": "23 years", "optb": "25 years", "optc": "33 years", "optd": "35 years", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Ayush's present age = 10 years.His mother's present age = (10 + 20) years = 30 years.Ayush's father's present age = (30 + 5) years = 35 years.Ayush's father's age at the time of Ayush's birth = (35 - 10) years = 25 years.Therefore Ayush's father's age at the time of marriage = (25 - 2) years = 23 years."}, {"question": "Pointing to a photograph of a boy Suresh said, \"He is the son of the only son of my mother.\" How is Suresh related to that boy?", "opta": "Brother", "optb": "Uncle", "optc": "Cousin", "optd": "Father", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The boy in the photograph is the only son of the son of Suresh's mother i.e., the son of Suresh. Hence, Suresh is the father of boy."}, {"question": "If A + B means A is the mother of B; A - B means A is the brother B; A % B means A is the father of B and A x B means A is the sister of B, which of the following shows that P is the maternal uncle of Q?", "opta": "Q - N + M x P", "optb": "P + S x N - Q", "optc": "P - M + N x Q", "optd": "Q - S % P", "ans": "C", "explanation": "P - M \u2192 P is the brother of M\nM + N \u2192 M is the mother of N\nN x Q \u2192 N is the sister of Q\nTherefore, P is the maternal uncle of Q."}, {"question": "If A is the brother of B; B is the sister of C; and C is the father of D, how D is related to A?", "opta": "Brother", "optb": "Sister", "optc": "Nephew", "optd": "Cannot be determined", "ans": "D", "explanation": "If D is Male, the answer is Nephew.\nIf D is Female, the answer is Niece. \nAs the sex of D is not known, hence, the relation between D and A cannot be determined.\nNote: Niece - A daughter of one's brother or sister, or of one's brother-in-law or sister-in-law. Nephew - A son of one's brother or sister, or of one's brother-in-law or sister-in-law."}, {"question": "If A + B means A is the brother of B; A - B means A is the sister of B and A x B means A is the father of B. Which of the following means that C is the son of M?", "opta": "M - N x C + F", "optb": "F - C + N x M", "optc": "N + M - F x C", "optd": "M x N - C + F", "ans": "D", "explanation": "M x N \u2192 M is the father of N\nN - C \u2192 N is the sister of C\nand C + F \u2192 C is the brother of F.\nHence, M is the father of C or C is the son of M."}, {"question": "Introducing a boy, a girl said, \"He is the son of the daughter of the father of my uncle.\" How is the boy related to the girl?", "opta": "Brother", "optb": "Nephew", "optc": "Uncle", "optd": "Son-in-law", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The father of the boy's uncle \u2192 the grandfather of the boy and daughter of the grandfather \u2192 sister of father."}, {"question": "Pointing to a photograph Lata says, \"He is the son of the only son of my grandfather.\" How is the man in the photograph related to Lata?", "opta": "Brother", "optb": "Uncle", "optc": "Cousin", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The man in the photograph is the son of the only son of Lata's grandfather i.e., the man is the son of Lata's father. Hence, the man is the brother of Lata."}, {"question": "If A + B means A is the brother of B; A x B means A is the son of B; and A % B means B is the daughter of A then which of the following means M is the maternal uncle of N?", "opta": "M + O x N", "optb": "M % O x N + P", "optc": "M + O % N", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Because the sex of O is not known."}, {"question": "If D is the brother of B, how B is related to C? To answer this question which of the statements is/are necessary?\n\nThe son of D is the grandson of C.\nB is the sister of D.", "opta": "Only 1", "optb": "Only 2", "optc": "Either 1 or 2", "optd": "1 and 2 both are required", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Given: D is the brother of B.\nFrom statement 1, we can detect that D is son of C (son of D is the grandson of C).\nFrom statement 2, we can detect that B is 'Female' (sister of D).\nTherefore, B is daughter of C."}, {"question": "If A + B means A is the father of B; A - B means A is the brother B; A % B means A is the wife of B and A x B means A is the mother of B, which of the following shows that M is the maternal grandmother of T?", "opta": "M x N % S + T", "optb": "M x N - S % T", "optc": "M x S - N % T", "optd": "M x N x S % T", "ans": "A", "explanation": "M x N \u2192 M is the mother of N\nN % S \u2192 N is the wife of S\nand S + T \u2192 is the father of T.\nHence, M is the maternal grandmother of T."}, {"question": "Pointing to a photograph. Bajpai said, \"He is the son of the only daughter of the father of my brother.\" How Bajpai is related to the man in the photograph?", "opta": "Nephew", "optb": "Brother", "optc": "Father", "optd": "Maternal Uncle", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The man in the photo is the son of the sister of Bajpai. Hence, Bajpai is the maternal uncle of the man in the photograph."}, {"question": "Deepak said to Nitin, \"That boy playing with the football is the younger of the two brothers of the daughter of my father's wife.\" How is the boy playing football related to Deepak?", "opta": "Son", "optb": "Brother", "optc": "Cousin", "optd": "Brother-in-law", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Father's wife \u2192 mother. Hence, the daughter of the mother means sister and sister's younger brother means brother. Therefore, the boy is the brother of Deepak."}, {"question": "Pointing a photograph X said to his friend Y, \"She is the only daughter of the father of my mother.\" How X is related to the person of photograph?", "opta": "Daughter", "optb": "Son", "optc": "Nephew", "optd": "Cannot be decided", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'The only daughter of the father of X's mother' means mother of X.\nHence X is the son of the lady in the photograph.\nNote: Still have doubt like \"How X is a male?\" - Let's see the discussions."}, {"question": "Veena who is the sister-in-law of Ashok, is the daughter-in-law of Kalyani. Dheeraj is the father of Sudeep who is the only brother of Ashok. How Kalyani is related to Ashok?", "opta": "Mother-in-law", "optb": "Aunt", "optc": "Wife", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Ashok is the only brother of Sudeep and Veena is the sister-in-law of Ashok. Hence Veena is the wife of Sudeep. Kalyani is the mother-in-law of Veena. Kalyani is the mother of Ashok."}, {"question": "If A + B means A is the sister of B; A x B means A is the wife of B, A % B means A is the father of B and A - B means A is the brother of B. Which of the following means T is the daughter of P?", "opta": "P x Q % R + S - T", "optb": "P x Q % R - T + S", "optc": "P x Q % R + T - S", "optd": "P x Q % R + S + T", "ans": "B", "explanation": "P x Q \u2192 P is the wife of Q\nQ % R \u2192 Q is the father of R\nR - T \u2192 R is the brother of T\nT + S \u2192 T is the sister of S.\nTherefore, T is the daughter of P."}, {"question": "Pointing to a woman, Abhijit said, \"Her granddaughter is the only daughter of my brother.\" How is the woman related to Abhijit?", "opta": "Sister", "optb": "Grandmother", "optc": "Mother-in-law", "optd": "Mother", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Daughter of Abhijit's brother \u2192 niece of Abhijit. Thus the granddaughter of the woman is Abhijit's niece.\nHence, the woman is the mother of Abhijit."}, {"question": "Amit said - \"This girl is the wife of the grandson of my mother\". How is Amit related to the girl?", "opta": "Brother", "optb": "Grandfather", "optc": "Husband", "optd": "Father-in-law", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The girl is the wife of grandson of Amit's mother i.e., the girl is the wife of son of Amit. Hence, Amit is the father-in-law of the girl."}, {"question": "A and B are children of D. Who is the father of A? To answer this question which of the statements (1) and (2) is necessary?\n\nC is the brother of A and the son of E.\nF is the mother B.", "opta": "Only (1)", "optb": "Only (2)", "optc": "Either (1) or (2)", "optd": "(1) and (2) both", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A and B are children of D.\nFrom (1), C is the brother B and son of E.\nSince, the sex of D and E are not known. Hence (1) is not sufficient to answer the question.\nFrom (2). F is the mother of B. Hence, F is also the mother of A. Hence D is the father of A.\nThus, (2) is sufficient to answer the question."}, {"question": "Pointing towards a man, a woman said, \"His mother is the only daughter of my mother.\" How is the woman related to the man?", "opta": "Mother", "optb": "Grandmother", "optc": "Sister", "optd": "Daughter", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Only daughter of my mother \u2192 myself.\nHence, the woman is the mother of the man."}, {"question": "If P $ Q means P is the brother of Q; P # Q means P is the mother of Q; P * Q means P is the daughter of Q in A # B $ C * D, who is the father?", "opta": "D", "optb": "B", "optc": "C", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A is the mother of B, B is the brother of C and C is the daughter of D. Hence, D is the father.\n\n\nA      (Parents)        D\n|                       |\n|                       |\nB - is - Brother - of - C"}, {"question": "Introducing Sonia, Aamir says, \"She is the wife of only nephew of only brother of my mother.\" How Sonia is related to Aamir?", "opta": "Wife", "optb": "Sister", "optc": "Sister-in-law", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Brother of mother means maternal uncle. Hence only nephew of Aamir's maternal uncle means Aamir himself. Therefore Sonia is the wife of Aamir."}, {"question": "If A + B means A is the brother of B; A % B means A is the father of B and A x B means A is the sister of B. Which of the following means M is the uncle of P?", "opta": "M % N x P", "optb": "N x P % M", "optc": "M + S % R % P", "optd": "M + K % T x P", "ans": "D", "explanation": "M + K \u2192 M is the brother of K\nK % T \u2192 K is the father of T\nT x P \u2192 T is the sister of P\nTherefore, K is the father of P and M is the uncle of P."}, {"question": "Pointing to Varman, Madhav said, \"I am the only son of one of the sons of his father.\" How is Varman related to Madhav?", "opta": "Nephew", "optb": "Uncle", "optc": "Father or Uncle", "optd": "Father", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Madhav is the only son of one of the sons of Varman's father \u2192 Either Varman is the father or uncle of Madhav."}, {"question": "Introducing a woman, Shashank said, \"She is the mother of the only daughter of my son.\" How that woman is related to Shashank?", "opta": "Daughter", "optb": "Sister-in-law", "optc": "Wife", "optd": "Daughter-in-law", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The woman is the mother of Shashank's granddaughter. Hence, the woman is the daughter-in-law of Shashank."}, {"question": "If A + B means B is the brother of A; A x B means B is the husband of A; A - B means A is the mother of B and A % B means A is the father of B, which of the following relations shows that Q is the grandmother of T?", "opta": "Q - P + R % T", "optb": "P x Q % R - T", "optc": "P x Q % R + T", "optd": "P + Q % R - T", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Q - P \u2192 Q is the mother of P\nP + R \u2192 R is the brother of P\nHence, \u2192 q is the mother of R\nR % T \u2192 R is the father of T.\nHence, Q is the grandmother of T."}, {"question": "A3P means A is the mother of P\nA4P means A is the brother of P\nA9P means A is the husband of P\nA5P means A is the daughter of P\n\nWhich of the following means that K is the mother-in-law of M?", "opta": "M9N3K4J", "optb": "M9N5K3J", "optc": "K5J9M3N", "optd": "K3J9N4M", "ans": "B", "explanation": "M9N \u2192 M is the husband of N\nN5K \u2192 N is the daughter of K\nHence, \u2192 M is the son-in-law of K\nK3J \u2192 K is the mother of J\nHence, \u2192 K is a lady\nHence, \u2192 K is the mother-in-law of M."}, {"question": "Pointing to a photograph Anjali said, \"He is the son of the only son of my grandfather.\" How is the man in the photograph related to Anjali?", "opta": "Brother", "optb": "Uncle", "optc": "Son", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The man in the photograph is son of Anjali's grandfather's son i.e., the son of Anjali's father. Hence, the boy is the brother of Anjali."}, {"question": "Pointing to a person, Deepak said, \"His only brother is the father of my daughter's father\". How is the person related to Deepak?", "opta": "Father", "optb": "Grandfather", "optc": "Uncle", "optd": "Brother-in-law", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Father of Deepak's daughter's father \u2192 Deepak's father.\nHence, the person in the brother of Deepak's father.\nTherefore, the person is the uncle of Deepak."}, {"question": "P is the mother of K; K is the sister of D; D is the father of J. How is P related to J?", "opta": "Mother", "optb": "Grandmother", "optc": "Aunt", "optd": "Data inadequate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "P is the mother of K\nK is the sister of D\nD is the father of J.\nTherefore, J is the nephew or niece of K and P is the grandmother of J."}, {"question": "If P $ Q means P is the father of Q; P # Q means P is the mother of Q and P * Q means P is the sister of Q, then N # L $ P * Q shows which of the relation of Q to N?", "opta": "Grand son", "optb": "Grand daughter", "optc": "Nephew", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As the sex of Q is not known, hence, data is inadequate."}, {"question": "If A $ B means A is the brother of B; A @ B means A is the wife of B; A # B means A is the daughter of B and A * B means A is the father of B, which of the following indicates that U is the father-in-law of P?", "opta": "P @ Q $ T # U * W", "optb": "P @ W $ Q * T # U", "optc": "P @ Q $ W * T # U", "optd": "P @ Q $ T # W * U", "ans": "A", "explanation": "P @ Q \u2192 P is the wife of Q ...(1)\nQ $ T \u2192 Q is the brother of T ...(2)\nT # U \u2192 T is the daughter of U\nHence, \u2192 Q is the son of U ...(3)\nU * W \u2192 U is the father of W.\nFrom (1) and (3), U is the father-in-law of P."}, {"question": "Introducing a man, a woman said, \"He is the only son of the mother of my mother.\" How is the woman related to the man?", "opta": "Mother", "optb": "Sister", "optc": "Niece", "optd": "Maternal aunt", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The man is the only son of the mother of the woman. Hence, the man is the maternal uncle of the woman. So, the woman is the niece of the man."}, {"question": "Pointing to Gopi, Nalni says, \"I am the daughter of the only son of his grandfather.\" How Nalni is related to Gopi?", "opta": "Niece", "optb": "Daughter", "optc": "Sister", "optd": "Cannot be determined", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Nalni is the daughter of the only son of Gopi's grandfather. Hence, it's clear that Nalni is the sister of Gopi."}, {"question": "A's son B is married with C whose sister D is married to E the brother of B. How D is related to A?", "opta": "Sister", "optb": "Daughter's-in-law", "optc": "Sister-in-law", "optd": "Cousin", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since E is the brother of B\nTherefore, A is the father of E\nbut D is the wife of E.\nHence, D is the daughter-in-law of A."}, {"question": "Pointing to a lady a person said, \"The son of her only brother is the brother of my wife.\" How is the lady related to the person?", "opta": "Maternal aunt", "optb": "Grandmother", "optc": "Sister of father-in-law", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Brother of person's wife \u2192 brother-in-law of the person. Hence, the son of lady's brother is brother-in-law of the person.\nTherefore, the brother of the lady is the father-in-law of the person. Hence, the lady is the sister of the person's father-in-law."}, {"question": "B5D means B is the father of D.\nB9D means B is the sister of D.\nB4D means B is the brother of D.\nB3D means B is the wife of D.\n\nWhich of the following means F is the mother of K?", "opta": "F3M5K", "optb": "F5M3K", "optc": "F9M4N3K", "optd": "F3M5N3K", "ans": "A", "explanation": "F3M \u2192 F is the wife of M\nM5K \u2192 M is the father of K\nTherefore, F is the mother of K."}, {"question": "A $ B means A is the father of B; A # B means A is the sister of B; A * B means A is the daughter of B and A @ B means A is the brother of B. Which of the following indicates that M is the wife of Q?", "opta": "Q $ R # T @ M", "optb": "Q $ R @ T # M", "optc": "Q $ R * T # M", "optd": "Q $ R @ T * M", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Q $ R \u2192 Q is the father of R\nR @ T \u2192 R is the brother of T\nHence, \u2192 Q is the father of T\nT * M \u2192 T is the daughter of M\nHence, \u2192 M is the mother of T\nHence, M is the wife of Q."}, {"question": "If A $ B means A is the brother of B; B * C means B is the son of C; C @ D means C is the wife of D and A # D means A is the son of D, how C is related to A?", "opta": "Maternal grandmother", "optb": "Maternal aunt", "optc": "Aunt", "optd": "Mother", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A $ B \u2192 A is the brother of B\nB * C \u2192 B is the son of C\nHence, \u2192 A is the son of C\nC @ D \u2192 C is the wife of D\nHence, \u2192 C is the mother of A."}, {"question": "Pointing to a girl Sandeep said, \"She is the daughter of the only sister of my father.\" How is sandeep related to the girl?", "opta": "Uncle", "optb": "Cousin", "optc": "Father", "optd": "Grandfather", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The girl is the daughter of the sister of Sandeep's father. Hence, the girl is the cousin or Sandeep is the cousin of the girl."}, {"question": "Pointing to a boy in the photograph Reena said, \"He is the only son of the only child of my grandfather.\" How Reena is related to that boy?", "opta": "Mother", "optb": "Sister", "optc": "Aunt", "optd": "Cannot be determined", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The boy in the photograph is the only son of Reena's grandfather's only son; i.e., the boy is the only son of Reena's father.\nHence, the boy is the brother of Reena or Reena is the sister of the boy."}, {"question": "A * B means A is the sister of B\nA $ B means B is the mother of A\nA + B means A is the brother of B\nA = B means B is the father of A.\n\nWhich of the following means M is the maternal uncle of N?", "opta": "M = P + Q * N", "optb": "N + P = Q * M", "optc": "N * P $ Q * M", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If M x N means M is the daughter of N; M + N means M is the father of N; M % N means M is the mother of N and M - N means M is the brother of N then P % Q + R - T x K indicates which relation of P to K?", "opta": "Daughter-in-law", "optb": "Sister-in-law", "optc": "Aunt", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "P % Q \u2192 P is the mother of Q\nQ + R \u2192 Q is the father of R\nR - T \u2192 R is the brother of T\nHence, \u2192 Q is the father of T\nT x K \u2192 T is the daughter of K\nHence, \u2192 Q is the husband of K.\nTherefore, P is the mother-in-law of K."}, {"question": "If P + Q means P is the brother of Q; P x Q means P is the father of Q and P - Q means P is the sister of Q, which of the following relations shows that I is the niece of K?", "opta": "K + Y + Z - I", "optb": "K + Y x I - Z", "optc": "Z - I x Y + K", "optd": "K x Y + I - Z", "ans": "B", "explanation": "K + Y \u2192 K is the brother of Y\nY x I \u2192 Y is the father of I\nHence, \u2192 K is the uncle of I\nand I - Z \u2192 I is the sister of Z\nHence, \u2192 I is the niece of K."}, {"question": "Pointing towards a girl, Abhisek says, \"This girl is the daughter of only a child of my father.\" What is the relation of Abhisek's wife to that girl?", "opta": "Daughter", "optb": "Mother", "optc": "Aunt", "optd": "Sister", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Only the child of my father means 'Abhisek' himself. This means the girl is the daughter od Abhisek. Hence, Abhisek's wife is the mother of the girl."}, {"question": "If A $ B means B is the father of A; A # B means B is the mother of A; A * B means B is the sister of A and A @ B means B is the husband of A, which of the following indicates that N is the grandmother of P?", "opta": "P * Q # M $ N", "optb": "P @ Q $ M # N", "optc": "P # Q $ N * M", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Anupam said to a lady sitting in a car, \"The only daughter of the brother of my wife is the sister-in-law of the brother of your sister.\" How the husband of the lady is related to Anupam?", "opta": "Maternal uncle", "optb": "Uncle", "optc": "Father", "optd": "Son-in-law", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Anupam's son-in-law is the brother of the lady who was sitting in the car. Hence, the husband is also the son-in-law of Anupam."}, {"question": "If P + Q means P is the brother of Q; P x Q means P is the wife of Q and P % Q means P is the daughter of Q then which of the following means D is the uncle of A?", "opta": "A % B x C + D", "optb": "A x B + C % D", "optc": "A + C % B x D", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A is the son of C; C and Q are sisters; Z is the mother of Q and P is the son of Z. Which of the following statements is true?", "opta": "P and A are cousins", "optb": "P is the maternal uncle of A", "optc": "Q is the maternal grandfather of A", "optd": "C and P are sisters", "ans": "B", "explanation": "C and Q are sisters and A is the son of C. Hence, C is the mother of A or Z is the mother Q.\nHence, Z is the maternal grandmother of A. P is the son of Z. Hence, P is the maternal uncle of A."}, {"question": "M is the father of N who is the son of V. In order to know the relation of M to P, which of the statement/statements is/are necessary?\n\nP is the brother of V.\nThe daughter of N is the granddaughter of V.", "opta": "Only (1)", "optb": "Only (2)", "optc": "Either (1) or (2)", "optd": "(1) and (2) both", "ans": "A", "explanation": "M is the father of N and N is the son of V.\nHence, V is the mother of N.\nFrom (1), P is the brother of V\nTherefore, M is the brother-in-law of P because V is the wife of M.\nFrom (2), the daughter of N, is the granddaughter of V. From this we do not get any relation of M to P."}, {"question": "If X + Y means X is the daughter of Y; X - Y means X is the brother of Y; X % Y means X is the father of Y and X x Y means X is the sister of Y. Which of the following means I is the niece of J?", "opta": "J - N % C x I", "optb": "I x C - N % J", "optc": "J + M x C % I", "optd": "I x C + N - J", "ans": "D", "explanation": "I x C \u2192 I is the sister of C\nC + N \u2192 C is the daughter of N\nand N - J \u2192 N is the brother of I.\nHence, I is niece of J."}, {"question": "Statements:\nStandard of living among the middle class society is constantly going up since part of few years.\nIndian Economy is observing remarkable growth.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the standard of living among the middle class society is constantly going up so Indian Economy is observing remarkable growth."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe meteorological Department has issued a statement mentioning deficient rainfall during monsoon in many parts of the country.\nThe Government has lowered the revised estimated GDP growth from the level of earlier estimates.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe staff of Airport Authorities called off the strike they were observing in protest against privatization.\nThe staff of Airport Authorities went on strike anticipating a threat to their jobs.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nA huge truck overturned on the middle of the road last night.\nThe police had cordoned of entire area in the locality this morning for half of the day.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since a huge truck overturned on the middle of the road last night, so, the police had cordoned off the entire area in the locality last morning for half of the day."}, {"question": "Statements:\nImportance of Yoga and exercise is being realized by all sections of the society.\nThere is an increasing awareness about health in the society particularly among middle ages group of people.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As the awareness about health in the society is increasing particularly among middle-aged group of people, the importance of Yoga and exercise is being realized by all sections of the society."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe prices of food grains and other essential commodities in the open market have risen sharply during the past three months.\nThe political party in opposition has given a call for general strike to protest against the government's economic policy.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the prices of food grains and other essential commodities in the open market have been raised sharply during the past three months, so the political party in opposition has given a call for general strike to protest against the government's economic policy."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has decided to hold a single entrance test for admission to all the medical colleges in India.\nThe State Government has debarred students from other States to apply for the seats in the medical colleges in the State.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nLarge number of Primary Schools in the rural areas is run by only one teacher.\nThere has been a huge dropout from the primary schools in rural areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since large numbers of primary schools in the rural areas are run by only one teacher so there has been a huge dropout from the Primary Schools in rural areas."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe employees of the biggest bank in the country have given an indefinite strike call starting from the third of the next month.\nThe employees of the Central Government have withdrawn their week long demonstrations.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of the different causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nPolice resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unlawful gathering of large number of people.\nThe citizens' forum called a general strike in protest against the police atrocities.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "As, police resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unlawful gathering of large number of people, the citizens forum called a general strike against the police atrocities."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe farmers have decided against selling their Kharif crops to the Government agencies.\nThe Government has reduced the procurement price of Kharif crops starting from the last month to the next six months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the government has reduced the procurement price of Kharif crops starting from the last months to the next six months, therefore, the farmers have decided against selling their Kharif crops to the Government agencies."}, {"question": "Statements:\nMany people visited the religious place during the week-end.\nFew people visited the religious place during the week days.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are the effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nAll the schools in the area had to be kept closed for most part of the week.\nMany parents have withdrawn their children from the local schools.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe literacy rate in the district has been increasing for the last four years.\nThe district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As the district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive, therefore, the literacy in the district has been increasing for the last four years."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe car manufacturing companies have recently increased the prices of mid-sized cars.\nThe Government recently increased the duty on mid-sized cars.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the government has recently increased the duty on mid-sized cars, therefore, the car manufacturing companies have recently increased the prices of mid-sized cars."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe university officers have decided to conduct last examination every year in March/April in order to announce the result at proper time.\nIn past the result was declared late by the University due to the lack of number of examiners.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since in the past the result was declared late by university, it has decided to conduct the examination in March/April in order to announce the result at proper time."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe State Government has announced special tax package for the new industries to be set-up in the State.\nLast year the State Government had hiked the taxes for all industrial activities in the State.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because due to hike of taxes last year the State Government has announced special tax package the new industries to be set up in the State."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe government has allowed private airline companies in India to operate to overseas destinations.\nThe national air carrier has increased its flights to overseas destinations.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the Government has allowed private airline companies in India to operate to overseas, so the national air carrier has increased its flights to overseas destinations."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has imported large quantities of sugar as per trade agreement with other countries.\nThe prices of sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the Government has imported large quantities of sugar as per trade agreement with other countries, therefore, the prices of the sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nMany people in the area are reported to be suffering from Malaria.\nPrivate Medical Practitioners in the area have decided to close their clinics for few days.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes. Because spreading malaria or to be suffering from malaria may be due to mosquitoes or dirtiness. But the decision of private medical practitioners to close the clinics may be due to other causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nRural and semi-urban areas in the country have been suffering due to load-shedding for quite some time.\nIf the Government is not able to overcome the power crisis, load-shedding will be extended even to the urban areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "If certain preventive measures are practiced at the rural and semi urban areas the problem will be solved. But if the same is not practiced even at the cities the problem may roll into the city also, so the two effects are of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has increased rates of petrol and diesel by 10% from the immediate effect.\nOil producing countries have decided to increase 10% of production on crude oil from the last quarter.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both statements I and II are the effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe vegetable prices in the local market have increases manifold during the past few days.\nIncessant rains have created flood like situation in most rural parts of the State.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The transportation gets effect due to the flood created by incessant rains in the most rural parts of State.\nTherefore, on account of this, it is possible to increase the vegetable prices in the local market."}, {"question": "Statements:\nPolice had resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unruly mob from the civic headquarters.\nThe civic administration has recently hiked the property tax of the residential buildings by about 30 percent.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are the effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe government has decided to give tax benefits for small savings for investments and benefit accruals. However, all withdrawals of such savings are to be taxed.\nPeople have been investing more in small savings than in equity market to avail maximum tax benefits.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThere was a huge rush of people to the temple last Sunday the 15th of the month.\nThe temple authority had decided to close down the temple for repairs from 17th of the month.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the temple authority had decided to close down the temple for repairs from 17th of the month, hence, there was a huge rush of people to the temple last Sunday the 15th of the month."}, {"question": "Statements:\nLarge number of people living in the low lying areas has been evacuated during the last few days to safer places.\nThe Government has rushed in relief supplies to the people living in the affected areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Reserve Bank of India has recently put restrictions on few small banks in the country.\nThe small banks in the private and co-operative sector in India are not in a  position to withstand the competitions of the bigger banks in the public sector.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As, the small banks in the private and co-operation sector in India are not in a position to withstand the competitions of the bigger banks in the public sector, therefore, the Reserve Bank of India has recently  put restrictions on few small banks in the country."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe prices of petrol and diesel in the domestic market have remained unchanged for the past few months.\nThe crude oil prices in the International market have gone up substantially in the last few months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Both are independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe performance of Indian sports persons in the recently held Olympics could not reach the level of expectation the country had on them.\nThe performance of Indian sports person in the last Asian games was far better than any previous games.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are effects of some common cause."}, {"question": "Statements:\nLarge numbers of people have fallen sick after consuming sweets from a particular shop in the locality.\nMajor part of the locality is flooded and has become inaccessible to outsides.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both statements I and II are the effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe life today is too fast, demanding all full of variety in all aspects which at times leads to stressful situation.\nNumber of suicide cases among teenagers is on increase.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "E", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of cell phones inside the college premises.\nMajority of the teachers of the college signed a joint petition to the university complaining the disturbances  caused by cell phone ring tones inside the classrooms.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the teachers of the colleges complained to the university about the disturbances caused by cell phone ring-tones inside the class-rooms, the university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of cell phones inside the college premises."}, {"question": "Statements:\nMajority of people residing in the locality have decided to protest against the municipality authority's decision to allow construction of a shopping mall in the locality.\nMany shopping malls have been opened all over the city in the recent time.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since in the recent time, many shopping malls have been opened all over the city, therefore, majority of the people residing in the locality have decided to protest against the municipality authority's decision to allow construction of a shopping mall in the locality."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has reduced the prices of petroleum products by five percent a week after increasing the prices by ten percent. \nThe rate of inflation dropped marginally during the last week.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\nPolice authority has recently increased vigil during the evening hours in the locality.\nThere has been considerable reduction in the incidents of petty crimes in the locality.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since police authority has recently increased vigil during the evening hours in the locality therefore, the petty crimes have reduced considerably."}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe committee appointed by the Government on the fee structure of the professional courses has drastically reduced the fees of various courses in comparison to those charged in the last year.\nThe parents of aspiring students seeking admission to professional courses had launched a severe agitation protesting against the high fees charged by the professional institutes and the admission process was delayed considerably.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes.", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the parents of aspiring students seeking admission to professional courses had launched a severe agitation protesting against the high fess changed by the professional institutes.\nSo, the committee was appointed by the Government on the fee structure of professional courses has drastically reduced the fess of previous course."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "L10", "optb": "K15", "optc": "I15", "optd": "K8", "ans": "D", "explanation": "How the number is obtained?\n2 + 4 = 6\n5 + 9 = 14\nSimilarly,\n3 + 5 = 8\nTherefore, the answer is K8."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "1", "optb": "4", "optc": "3", "optd": "6", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(5 + 4 + 7)/2 = 8\n(6 + 9 + 5)/2 = 10\n(3 + 7 + 2)/2 = 6."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "18", "optb": "12", "optc": "9", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(12 + 18 + 30)/10 = 6\n(16 + 24 + 40)/10 = 8\nSimilarly, (45 + 18 + 27)/10 = 9."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "25", "optb": "37", "optc": "41", "optd": "47", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(5 x 3) + 4 = 19\nand (6 x 4) + 5 = 29\nTherefore, (7 x 5) + 6 = 41"}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "45", "optb": "41", "optc": "32", "optd": "40", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(15 x 2 - 3) = 27,\n(31 x 2 - 6) = 56\nand (45 x 2 - 9) = 81"}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "115", "optb": "130", "optc": "135", "optd": "140", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(5 x 6 x 8) + (7 x 4 x 9) = 492\nand (7 x 5 x 4) + (6 x 8 x 9) = 572\nTherefore (4 x 3 x 5) + (7 x 2 x 5) = 130."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "92", "optb": "72", "optc": "62", "optd": "99", "ans": "D", "explanation": "21 + 31 = 52\nand 39 + 46 = 85\nTherefore, 16 + 83 = 99."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(18 x 12)/3 = 72\nand (32 x 16)/4 = 128\nTherefore, (24 x 14)/? = 112\n(336/?) = 112\n? = (336/112)\n? = 3."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "36", "optb": "48", "optc": "38", "optd": "30", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(0 + 2 + 6 + 4) - 2 = 10\nand (6 + 2 + 10 + 8) - 2 = 24\nTherefore, (4 + 14 + 12 + 10) - 2 = 38."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "41", "optb": "64", "optc": "35", "optd": "61", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(1)3 = 1, (2)3 = 8, (3)3 = 27\nTherefore, (4)3 = 64."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "13", "optb": "14", "optc": "12", "optd": "15", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Sum of numbers in lower half of the circle = 11 + 9 + 3 + 7 = 30\nSum of numbers in upper half of the circle = ? + 4 + 5 + 6 = ? + 15\nUpper half = Lower half\n30 = ? + 15 \n? = 30 - 15\n? = 15.\nThrefore, 15 is the answer."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "262", "optb": "622", "optc": "631", "optd": "824", "ans": "B", "explanation": "915 - 364 = 551\nand 789 - 543 = 246\nSimilarly, 863 - 241 = 622."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "45", "optb": "29", "optc": "39", "optd": "37", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "184", "optb": "210", "optc": "241", "optd": "425", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(12)2 - (8)2 = 80\nand (16)2 - (7)2 = 207\nTherefore (25)2 - (21)2 = 184."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "25", "optb": "59", "optc": "48", "optd": "73", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(2)3 + (1)3 + (3)3 = 36\nand (0)3 + (4)3 + (3)3 = 91\nTherefore, (4)3 + (2)3 + (1)3 = 73."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "0", "optb": "2", "optc": "11", "optd": "12", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(6 + 5) - (7 + 4) = 0\nand (7 + 6) - (8 + 4) = 1\nTherefore (11 + 2) - (2 + 0) = 11."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "64", "optb": "144", "optc": "169", "optd": "25", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The numbers are squared in ascending order\nIn first circle,\n(3)2 = 9\n(4)2 = 16\n(5)2 = 25\n(6)2 = 36.\nIn second circle,\n(4)2 = 16\n(5)2 = 25\n(6)2 = 36\n(7)2 = 49.\nIn third circle,\n(6)2 = 36\n(7)2 = 49\n(8)2 = 64\n(9)2 = 81."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "8", "optb": "12", "optc": "16", "optd": "20", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(4 x 6) % 3 = 8\n(6 x 10) % 5 = 12\n(4 x 8) % 2 = 16."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "3", "optb": "5", "optc": "4", "optd": "6", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(7 x 3) + 8 = 29\n(4 x 3) + 7 = 19\n(5 x ?) + 6 = 31\n? = 5."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "94", "optb": "76", "optc": "16", "optd": "73", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(4)2 + (2)2 + (1)2 = 21\nand (5)2 + (3)2 + (8)2 = 98\nTherefore (6)2 + (7)2 + (3)2 = 94."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "75", "optb": "26", "optc": "25", "optd": "20", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(2)2 + (4)2 = 20\nand (3)2 + (9)2 = 90\nTherefore (1)2 + (5)2 = 26."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "18", "optb": "24", "optc": "36", "optd": "58", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(7 x 3) = 21 and (9 x 3) = 27\nand (4 x 9) = 36 and (2 x 9) = 18\nTherefore (9 x 6) = 54 and (4 x 6) = 24."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "60", "optb": "30", "optc": "20", "optd": "45", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(16 + 13) = (14 + 15)\nand (28 + 12) = (10 + 30)\nTherefore (29 + 16) = (15 + 30)."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "15", "optb": "19", "optc": "20", "optd": "18", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(3 x 4) + 3 = 15\nand (7 x 5) + 3 = 38\nTherefore (3 x 5) + 3 = 18."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "11", "optb": "14", "optc": "10", "optd": "12", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(15 - 12) + (10 - 9) = 4\n(28 - 12) + (16 - 20) = 12\nSimilarly, (23 -11) + (15- 16) = 11."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "25", "optb": "625", "optc": "125", "optd": "50", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All numbers are cubed,\n(7)3 = 343\n(1)3 = 1\n(3)3 = 27\nSimilarly, (5)3 = 125."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "9", "optb": "6", "optc": "15", "optd": "14", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(4 + 9 + 2) = (3 + 5 + 7) = (8 + 1 + 6)\nTotal in each case = 15."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "30", "optb": "13", "optc": "70", "optd": "118", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(15 + 12)/9 = 3\nand (44 + 28)/9 = 8\nTherefore, (64 + 53)/9 = 13."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "40", "optb": "38", "optc": "44", "optd": "39", "ans": "B", "explanation": "9 + (2)2 = 13\n13 + (3)2 = 22\n22 + (4)2 = 38."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "60", "optb": "46", "optc": "86", "optd": "75", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(30 - 24) x 8 = 48\nand (23 - 12) x 8 = 88\nTherefore, (92 - 86) x 8 = 48."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "5", "optb": "6", "optc": "8", "optd": "9", "ans": "D", "explanation": "93 - (27 + 3) = 63\n79 - (38 + 4) = 37\nTherefore, 67 - (16 + X) = 42\nX = 9"}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "3", "optb": "2", "optc": "7", "optd": "6", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Putting the position of the letters in reverse order\nP = 11, S = 8, V = 5 and Y = 2."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "9", "optb": "5", "optc": "7", "optd": "3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "5 x 8 x 10 = 400\nand 6 x 9 x 7 = 378\nTherefore 5 x 7 x ? = 315\n? = 9."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "8", "optb": "32", "optc": "4", "optd": "16", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(16)2 = 256\nTherefore, (2)2 = 4."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "1/2", "optb": "2/3", "optc": "3/4", "optd": "4/5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I row, 1 + (1/2) = 3/2\nFrom II row, 2 + (2/3) = 8/3\nFrom III row, 3 + ? = 19/5\n? = (19/5) - 3\n? = (4/5)."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "262", "optb": "622", "optc": "631", "optd": "824", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(915 - 364) = 551\n(789 - 543) = 246\n(863 - 241) = 622."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "12", "optb": "13", "optc": "11", "optd": "10", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(4 x 8) + 1 = 33\n(5 x 9) + 1 = 46\nSimilarly, (7 x 11) + 1 = 78."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "20", "optb": "26", "optc": "25", "optd": "75", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(2)2 + (4)2 = 20\n(3)2 + (9)2 = 90\nTherefore, (1)2 + (5)2 = 26."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "4", "optb": "6", "optc": "9", "optd": "8", "ans": "B", "explanation": "3 x 5 x 4 = 60\nand 5 x 7 x 4 = 140\nTherefore, 4 x 4 x ? = 96\n? = (96/16) = 6."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "2", "optb": "4", "optc": "6", "optd": "8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(4 x 7) % 4 = 7\nand (6 x 2) % 3 = 4\nTherefore, (6 x 2) % 2 = 6."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "14", "optb": "22", "optc": "32", "optd": "320", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(5 x 6 x 4)/10 = 12\nand (6 x 7 x 5)/10 = 21\nTherefore (4 x 8 x 10)/10 = 32."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "18", "optb": "90", "optc": "108", "optd": "28", "ans": "C", "explanation": "13 + 15 = 28\n36 + 54 = 90\nTherefore, 45 + 63 = 108."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "8", "optb": "9", "optc": "10", "optd": "11", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(3 x 4 - 8) = 4\n(2 x 5 - 4) = 6\n(4 x 5 - 9) = 11."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "60", "optb": "50", "optc": "25", "optd": "21", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "47", "optb": "45", "optc": "37", "optd": "35", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(3 x 3) + (5 x 6) = 39\nand (4 x 4) + (5 x 7) = 51\nTherefore, (3 x 4) + (5 x 5) = 37."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(2)2 = 4\n(8)2 = 64\n(5)2 = 25\n(1)2 = 1."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "6", "optb": "7", "optc": "8", "optd": "9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(10 + 9 + 14 + 7)/2 = 20\nand (11 + 16 + 10 + 13)/2 = 25\nTherefore, (15 + ? + 12 + 10)/2 = 22\nHence 37 + ? = 44\n? = 44 - 37\n? = 7."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "33", "optb": "38", "optc": "32", "optd": "37", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(5 x 6) + 2 = 32\n(7 x 6) + 2 = 44\n(7 x 5) + 2 = 37."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "6", "optb": "7", "optc": "8", "optd": "9", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(5 + 3)/2 = 4\nand (6 + 8)/2 = 7\nTherefore (8 + 4)/2 = 6."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "660", "optb": "670", "optc": "610", "optd": "690", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(1)2 + (5)2 + (4)2 + (3)2 = 51 x 10 = 510\nand (3)2 + (4)2 + (6)2 + (2)2 = 65 x 10 = 650\nSimilarly (0)2 + (1)2 + (2)2 + (8)2 = 69 x 10 = 690."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "18", "optb": "20", "optc": "21", "optd": "19", "ans": "B", "explanation": "1 + 2 + 3 + 4 = 10\nand 1 + 3 + 5 + 8 = 17\nSimilarly, 1 + 4 + 6 + 9 = 20."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "80", "optb": "114", "optc": "108", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(4 + 8) x 9 = 108\n(5 + 4) x 12 = 108."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "8", "optb": "14", "optc": "10", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "For first triangle,\n10 - 4 = 6\n18 - 10 = 8\n18 - 4 = 14\nFor second triangle,\n14 - 8 = 6\n22 - 14 = 8\n22 - 8 = 14\nFor third triangle,\n11 - 5 = 6\n15 - 11 = 4\n15 - 5 = 10."}, {"question": "Which one will replace the question mark ?", "opta": "11", "optb": "19", "optc": "15", "optd": "22", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(2 x 2 - 1) = 3\nand (5 x 4 - 5) = 15\n(5 x 5 - 3) = 22."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Chicken", "optb": "Snake", "optc": "Swan", "optd": "Crocodile", "opte": "Frog", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All except Chicken can live in water."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Cap", "optb": "Turban", "optc": "Helmet", "optd": "Veil", "opte": "Hat", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Veil cover the head, while veil covers the face."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Kiwi", "optb": "Eagle", "optc": "Emu", "optd": "Ostrich", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Eagle are flightless birds."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Rigveda", "optb": "Yajurveda", "optc": "Atharvaveda", "optd": "Ayurveda", "opte": "Samveda", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Ayurveda are names of holy scriptures, the four Vedas. Ayurveda is a branch of medicine."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Curd", "optb": "Butter", "optc": "Oil", "optd": "Cheese", "opte": "Cream", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All except Oil are products obtained from milk."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Potassium", "optb": "Silicon", "optc": "Zirconium", "optd": "Gallium", "opte": "Germanium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All except Potassium are metals used in semiconductor devices."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Tea", "optb": "Cinchona", "optc": "Rubber", "optd": "Cardamom", "opte": "Chalk", "ans": "E", "explanation": "All except Chalk are obtained from crops."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Hangar", "optb": "Platform", "optc": "Dock", "optd": "Park", "opte": "Bus stand", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Park are halting places of various transport means."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Sparrow", "optb": "Swan", "optc": "Parrot", "optd": "Koel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Swan is the only water bird in the group."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Tall", "optb": "Huge", "optc": "Thin", "optd": "Sharp", "opte": "Small", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Sharp are related to dimension."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Pear", "optb": "Apple", "optc": "Litchi", "optd": "Guava", "opte": "Orange", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Orange is the only citrus fruit in the group."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Dagger", "optb": "Hammer", "optc": "Knife", "optd": "Sword", "opte": "Blade", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Hammer are sharp-edged and have a cutting action."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Kanpur", "optb": "Allahabad", "optc": "Varanasi", "optd": "Mathura", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Mathura are cities situated on the banks of Ganga river."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Oyster", "optb": "Clam", "optc": "Scallop", "optd": "Mussel", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All except Scallop live in shells."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Deck", "optb": "Quay", "optc": "Stern", "optd": "Bow", "opte": "Mast", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Quay are parts Of a ship."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Producer", "optb": "Director", "optc": "Investor", "optd": "Financier", "opte": "Entrepreneur", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Director spend money."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Tricycle", "optb": "Trident", "optc": "Trifle", "optd": "Tricolour", "opte": "Trilogy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In all except Trifle, 'tri' indicates 'three'."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Chameleon", "optb": "Crocodile", "optc": "Alligator", "optd": "Locust", "opte": "Salamander", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Locust are reptiles, while locust is an insect."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Calendar", "optb": "Year", "optc": "Date", "optd": "Month", "opte": "Day", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All others are parts of a calendar."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Mumbai", "optb": "Cochin", "optc": "Kandla", "optd": "Mysore", "opte": "Vishakhapatnam", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Mysore are harbours."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Cumin", "optb": "Groundnut", "optc": "Cinnamon", "optd": "Pepper", "opte": "Clove", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Groundnut are spices."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Biscuits", "optb": "Chocolate", "optc": "Cake", "optd": "Bread", "opte": "Pastry", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Chocolate are baked items."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Sweep", "optb": "Wipe", "optc": "Scrub", "optd": "Wash", "opte": "Stain", "ans": "E", "explanation": "All except Stain are terms related to cleaning."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Coat", "optb": "Shirt", "optc": "Blouse", "optd": "Trousers", "opte": "Sweater", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Trousers are garments which cover the upper part of the body."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Asia", "optb": "Argentina", "optc": "Africa", "optd": "Australia", "opte": "Antarctica", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Argentina are continents, while Argentina is a country."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Japan", "optb": "India", "optc": "Sri Lanka", "optd": "New Zealand", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except India are islands, while India is a peninsula."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Spectacles", "optb": "Goggles", "optc": "Binoculars", "optd": "Microphone", "opte": "Telescope", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Microphone are related to eyes."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Shehnai", "optb": "Bagpipe", "optc": "Flute", "optd": "Sitar", "opte": "Harmonica", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Sitar are wind instruments, while sitar is a string instrument."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Cheetah", "optb": "Lion", "optc": "Bear", "optd": "Tiger", "opte": "Leopard", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All except Bear belong to the cat family."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Sheep", "optb": "Gazelle", "optc": "Ibex", "optd": "Shrew", "opte": "Tapir", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Gazelle are animals found in the mountains."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Flood", "optb": "Hurricane", "optc": "Avalanche", "optd": "Earthquake", "opte": "Explosion", "ans": "E", "explanation": "All except Explosion are natural calamities."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Ant", "optb": "Bee", "optc": "Moth", "optd": "Midge", "opte": "Spider", "ans": "E", "explanation": "All except Spider are insects having six legs."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Flute", "optb": "Guitar", "optc": "Sitar", "optd": "Violin", "opte": "Veena", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All except Flute are string instruments."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Treachery", "optb": "Fraud", "optc": "Deceit", "optd": "Swindle", "opte": "Morbid", "ans": "E", "explanation": "All except Morbid are synonyms of 'deceit'."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Lima", "optb": "Algiers", "optc": "New York", "optd": "Tokyo", "opte": "Beijing", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All except New York are capital cities."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Reader", "optb": "Writer", "optc": "Printer", "optd": "Publisher", "opte": "Reporter", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All except Reader are persons involved in the preparation of a journal, newspaper or magazine."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Arrow", "optb": "Axe", "optc": "Knife", "optd": "Dagger", "opte": "Sword", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All except Arrow are used while holding in hand."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Feathers", "optb": "Tentacles", "optc": "Scales", "optd": "Pseudopodia", "opte": "Flagella", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All except Feathers are organs for movement in different organisms."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Dog", "optb": "Horse", "optc": "Goat", "optd": "Cat", "opte": "Fox", "ans": "E", "explanation": "All except Fox are domestic animals, while fox is a wild animal."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "House", "optb": "Cottage", "optc": "School", "optd": "Palace", "opte": "Hut", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All except School are dwelling places."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Physics", "optb": "Chemistry", "optc": "Geography", "optd": "Botany", "opte": "Zoology", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All except Geography are branches of Science."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Football", "optb": "Volleyball", "optc": "Cricket", "optd": "Chess", "opte": "Hockey", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Chess are outdoor games."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Trunk", "optb": "Tree", "optc": "Fruit", "optd": "Leaf", "opte": "Flower", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All others are parts of a tree."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Giraffe", "optb": "Hyena", "optc": "Deer", "optd": "Rhinoceros", "opte": "Zebra", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Hyena is the only flesh-eating animal in the group."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Poland", "optb": "Greece", "optc": "Spain", "optd": "Italy", "opte": "Korea", "ans": "E", "explanation": "All except Korea are European countries, while Korea is an Asian country."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Bajra", "optb": "Mustard", "optc": "Rice", "optd": "Wheat", "opte": "Barley", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All except Mustard are foodgrains, while mustard is an oilseed."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Cot", "optb": "Sheet", "optc": "Quilt", "optd": "Pillow", "opte": "Blanket", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All except Cot are parts of bed-spread."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Assassinate", "optb": "Kill", "optc": "Kidnap", "optd": "Stab", "opte": "Murder", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All except Kidnap are actions of killing."}, {"question": "Choose the word which is different from the rest.", "opta": "Doe", "optb": "Bitch", "optc": "Sorceress", "optd": "Drone", "opte": "Mare", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All except Drone are females."}, {"question": "How many cubes having red, green and black colours on at least one side of the cube will be formed ?", "opta": "16", "optb": "12", "optc": "10", "optd": "4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Such cubes are related to the corners of the cuboid. Since the number of corners of the cuboid is 4.\nHence, the number of such small cubes is 4."}, {"question": "How many small cubes will be formed ?", "opta": "6", "optb": "12", "optc": "16", "optd": "24", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Number of small cubes = l x b x h = 6 x 4 x 1 = 24"}, {"question": "How many cubes will have 4 coloured sides and two non-coloured sides ?", "opta": "8", "optb": "4", "optc": "16", "optd": "10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Only 4 cubes situated at the corners of the cuboid will have 4 coloured and 2 non-coloured sides."}, {"question": "How many cubes will have green colour on two sides and rest of the four sides having no colour ?", "opta": "12", "optb": "10", "optc": "8", "optd": "4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "There are 16 small cubes attached to the outer walls of the cuboid.\nTherefore remaining inner small cubes will be the cubes having two sides green coloured.\nSo the required number = 24 - 16 = 8"}, {"question": "How many cubes will remain if the cubes having black and green coloured are removed ?", "opta": "4", "optb": "8", "optc": "12", "optd": "16", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Number of small cubes which are Black and Green is 8 in all.\nHence, the number of remaining cubes are = 24 - 8 = 16"}, {"question": "Question:  In which year was Rahul born ?\nStatements:\n\nRahul at present is 25 years younger to his mother.\nRahul's brother, who was born in 1964, is 35 years younger to his mother.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From both I and II, we find that Rahul is (35 - 25) = 10 years older than his brother, who was born in 1964. So, Rahul was born in 1954."}, {"question": "Question:  What will be the total weight of 10 poles, each of the same weight ?\nStatements:\n\nOne-fourth of the weight of each pole is 5 kg.\nThe total weight of three poles is 20 kilograms more than the total weight of two poles.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that weight of each pole = (4x5) kg = 20 kg.So, total weight of 10 poles = (20 x 10) kg = 200 kg.From II, we conclude that:Weight of each pole = (weight of 3 poles) - (weight of 2 poles) = 20 kg.So, total weight of 10 pojes = (20 x 10) kg = 200 kg."}, {"question": "Question:  How many children does M have ?\nStatements:\n\nH is the only daughter of X who is wife of M.\nK and J are brothers of M.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that H is the only daughter of M. But this does not indicate that M has no son. The information given in II is immaterial."}, {"question": "Question:  How much was the total sale of the company ?\nStatements:\n\nThe company sold 8000 units of product A each costing Rs. 25.\nThis company has no other product line.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, total sale of product A = Rs. (8000 x 25) = Rs. 200000.From II, we know that the company deals only in product A.This implies that sale of product A is the total sale of the company, which is Rs. 200000."}, {"question": "Question:  The last Sunday of March, 2006 fell on which date ?\nStatements:\n\nThe first Sunday of that month fell on 5th.\nThe last day of that month was Friday.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that 5th, 12th, 19th and 26th of March, 2006 were Sundays.So, the last Sunday fell on 26th.From II, we conclude that 31st March, 2006 was Friday. Thus, 26th March, 2006 was the last Sunday of the month."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the code for 'sky' in the code language ?\nStatements:\n\nIn the code language, 'sky is clear' is written as 'de ra fa'.\nIn the same code language, 'make it clear' is written as 'de ga jo'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The only word common to I and II is 'clear' and as such, only the code for 'clear' can be ascertained from the given information."}, {"question": "Question:  How many children are there between P and Q in a row of children ?\nStatements:\n\nP is fifteenth from the left in the row.\nQ is exactly in the middle and there are ten children towards his right.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From II, Q being in the middle, there are 10 children to his right as well as to his left. So, Q is 11th from the left. From I, P is 15th from the left.Thus, from both I and II, we conclude that there are 3 children between P and Q."}, {"question": "Question:  How is T related to K?\nStatements:\n\nR's sister J has married Ts brother L, who is the only son of his parents.\nK is the only daughter of L and J.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we know that L is T's brother and J's husband. Since L is the only son of his parents, T is L's sister.From II, we know that K is L's daughter.Thus, from I and II, we conclude that T is the sister of K's father i.e. T is K's aunt."}, {"question": "Question:  How is J related to P ?\nStatements:\n\nM is brother of P and T is sister of P.\nP's mother is married to J's husband who has one son and two daughters.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From II, we know that P's mother is married to J's husband, which means that J is P's mother."}, {"question": "Question:  How is X related to Y ?\nStatements:\n\nY and Z are children of D who is wife of X.\nR's sister X is married to Ys father.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Y is the child of D who is wife of X i.e. X is Y's father.From II, X is married to Y's father. This implies that X is Y's mother."}, {"question": "Question:  Who is to the immediate right of P among five persons P, Q, R, S and T facing North ?\nStatements:\n\nR is third to the left of Q and P is second to the right of R.\nQ is to the immediate left of T who is second to the right of P.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we have the order: R, -, P, Q.From II, we have the order: P, Q, T.Clearly, each one of the above two orders indicates that Q is to the immediate right of P."}, {"question": "Question:  On which date of the month was Anjali born in February 2004 ?\nStatements:\n\nAnjali was born on an even date of the month.\nAnjali's birth date was a prime number.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I and II, we conclude that Anjali was born in February 2004 on a date which is an even prime number. Since the only even prime number is 2, so Anjali was born on 2nd February, 2004."}, {"question": "Question:  How is X related to Y?\nStatements:\n\nY says, \"I have only one brother\".\nX says, \"I have only one sister\".", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statements in I and II do not provide any clue regarding relation between X and Y."}, {"question": "Question:  How is F related to P?\nStatements:\n\nP has two sisters M and N.\nF's mother is sister of M's father.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I and II, we conclude that P is M's brother and so M's father is P's father. So, F is the child of the sister of P's father i.e. F's mother is P's aunt or F is P's cousin."}, {"question": "Question:  B is the brother of A. How is A related to B ?\nStatements:\n\nA is the sister of C.\nE is the husband of A.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "B is A's brother means A is either brother or sister of B. Now, each one of I and II individually indicates that A is a female, which means that A is B's sister."}, {"question": "Question:  How many children are there in the row of children facing North ?\nStatements:\n\nVishakha who is fifth from the left end is eighth to the left of Ashish who is twelfth from the right end.\nRohit is fifth to the left of Nisha who is seventh from the right end and eighteenth from the left end.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since 8th to the left of 12th from the right is 20th from the right, so from I, we know that Vishakha is 5th from left and 20th from right i.e. there are 4 children to the left and 19 to the right of Vishakha. So, there are (4 + 1 + 19) i.e. 24 children in the row.From II, Nisha is 7th from right and 18th from left end of the row.So, there are (6 + 1 + 17) = 24 children in the row."}, {"question": "Question:  How many doctors are practising in this town ?\nStatements:\n\nThere is one doctor per seven hundred residents.\nThere are 16 wards with each ward having as many doctors as the number of wards.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From I, total number of doctors in town = (1/700 x N) , where N = total number of residents in town. But, the value of N is not known.From II, total number of doctors in town= (Number of wards in town) x (Number of doctors in each ward)= 16 x 16 = 256."}, {"question": "Question:  On which day of the week was birthday of Sahil ?\nStatements:\n\nSahil celebrated his birthday the very next day on which Arun celebrated his birthday.\nThe sister of Sahil was born on the third day of the week and two days after Sahil was born.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "I does not mention the day of the week on the birthday of either Arun or Sahil.According to II, Sahil's sister was born on Wednesday and Sahil was born two days before Wednesday i.e. on Monday."}, {"question": "Question:  How many pages of book X did Robert read on Sunday ?\nStatements:\n\nThe book has 300 pages out of which two-thirds were read by him before Sunday.\nRobert read the last 40 pages of the book on the morning of Monday.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I and II, we find that Robert read (300 x 2/3) i.e. 200 pages before Sunday and the last 40 pages on Monday.This means that he read [300 - (200 + 40)] i.e. 60 pages on Sunday."}, {"question": "Question:  How is Tanya related to the man in the photograph ?\nStatements:\n\nMan in the photograph is the only son of Tanya's grandfather.\nThe man in the photograph has no brothers or sisters and his father is Tanya's grandfather.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that the man is the only son of Tanya's grandfather i.e. he is Tanya's father or Tanya is the man's daughter.From II, we conclude that the man's father is Tanya's grandfather. Since the man has no brothers or sisters, so he is Tanya's father or Tanya is the man's daughter."}, {"question": "Question:  Among T, V, B, E and C, who is the third from the top when arranged in the descending order of their weights ?\nStatements:\n\nB is heavier than T and C and is less heavier than V who is not the heaviest.\nC is heavier than only T.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From I, we have: B > T, B > C, V > B. Thus, V is heavier than each one of B, T and C. But V is not the heaviest. So, E is the heaviest.Thus, we have the order. E>V>B>T>C or E>V>B>C>T. Clearly, B is third from the top."}, {"question": "Question:  Which word in the code language means 'flower' ?\nStatements:\n\n'de fu la pane' means 'rose flower is beautiful' and 'la quiz' means 'beautiful tree'.\n'de la chin' means 'red rose flower' and 'pa chin' means 'red tea'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From the two statements given in I, the code for the only common word 'beautiful' can be determined.From the two statements given in II, the code for the only common word 'red' can be determined.In I and II, the common words are 'rose and 'flower' and the common code words are 'de' and 'la'. So, the code for 'flower' is either 'de' or 'la'."}, {"question": "Question:  How many students in a class play football ?\nStatements:\n\nOnly boys play football.\nThere are forty boys and thirty girls in the class.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "It is not mentioned whether all the boys or a proportion of them play football."}, {"question": "Question:  Who is C's partner in a game of cards involving four players A, B, C and D ?\nStatements:\n\nD is sitting opposite to A.\nB is sitting right of A and left of D.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Clearly, each of the given statements shows that B is sitting opposite to C or B is the partner of C."}, {"question": "Question:  On a T.V. channel, four serials A, B, C and D were screened, one on eacn day, on four consecutive days but not necessarily in that order. On which day was the serial C screened ?\nStatements:\n\nThe first serial was screened on 23rd, Tuesday and was followed by serial D.\nSerial A was not screened on 25th and one serial was screened between serials A and B.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we know that the serials were screened on 23rd, 24th, 25th and 26th.Clearly, D was screened second i.e. on 24th, Wednesday.From II, we know that one serial was screened between A and B.So, A and B were screened first and third, i.e. on 23rd and 25th. But, A was not screened on 25th.So, A was screened on 23rd and B on 25th. Thus, C was screened on 26th, Friday."}, {"question": "Question:  How is Sulekha related to Nandini ?\nStatements:\n\nSulekha's husband is the only son of Nandini's mother.\nSulekha's brother and Nandini's husband are cousins.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Sulekha is the wife of Nandini's mother's only son i.e. Nandini's brother. Thus, Sulekha is Nandini's sister-in-law.From II, we conclude that Sulekha is the cousin of Nandini's husband, which implies that Sulekha is Nandini's sister-in-law."}, {"question": "Question:  Can Ritesh retire from office X in January 2006, with full pension benefits ?\nStatements:\n\nRitesh will complete 30 years of service in office X in April 2000 and desires to retire.\nAs per office X rules, an employee has to complete minimum 30 years of service and attain age of 60. Ritesh has 3 years to complete age of 60.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the facts given in I and II contain two conditions to be fulfilled to get retirement and also indicate that Ritesh fulfills only one condition out of them."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the code for 'or' in the code language?\nStatements:\n\n'nik sa te' means 'right or wrong', 'ro da nik' means 'he is right' and 'fe te ro' means 'that is wrong'.\n'pa nik la' means 'that right man', 'sa ne pa' means 'this or that' and 'ne ka re' means 'tell this there'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "I. In 'right or wrong' and 'he is right', the common word is 'right' and the common code word is 'nik'. So 'nik' means 'right'. In 'right or wrong' and 'that is wrong', the common word is 'wrong' and the common code word is 'te'. So, 'te' means 'wrong'.Thus, in 'right or wrong', 'sa' is the code for 'or'. II. In 'that right man' and 'this or that', the common word is 'that' and the common code word is 'pa'. So, 'pa' means 'that'. In 'this or that' and 'tell this there', the common word is 'this' and the common code word is 'ne'. So, 'ne' means 'this'. Thus, in 'this or that', 'sa' is the code for 'or'."}, {"question": "Question:  Madan is elder than Kamal and Sharad is younger than Arvind. Who among them is the youngest ?\nStatements:\n\nSharad is younger than Madan.\nArvind is younger than Kamal.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As given, we have: M > K, A > S.From II, K > A. Thus, we have: M > K > A > S.So, Sharad is the youngest. From I, M > S. Thus, we have: M>K>A>S or M>A>K>S or M>A>S>K."}, {"question": "Question:  On which date in August was Kapil born ?\nStatements:\n\nKapil's mother remembers that Kapil was born before nineteenth but after fifteenth.\nKapil's brother remembers that Kapil was born before seventeenth but after twelfth.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Kapil was born on any one of the dates among 16th, 17th and 18th.From II, we conclude that Kapil was born on any one of the dates among 13th, 14th, 15th and 16th.Thus, from both I and II, we conclude that Kapil was born on 16th August."}, {"question": "Question:  What is Gagan's age ?\nStatements:\n\nGagan, Vimal and Kunal are all of the same age.\nTotal age of Vimal, Kunal and Anil is 32 years and Anil is as old as Vimal and Kunal together.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "As given in I and II, we have: G = V = K, V + K + A = 32 and A = V + K.Putting V + K = A in V + K + A = 32, we have: 2A = 32 or A = 16.Thus, V + K = 16 and V = K. So, V = K = 8. Thus, G = 8."}, {"question": "Question:  In a certain code, '13' means 'stop smoking' and '59' means 'injurious habit'. What do '9' and '5' mean respectively in that code ?\nStatements:\n\n'157' means 'stop bad habit'.\n'839' means 'smoking is injurious'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'59' means 'injurious habit' and '157' means 'stop bad habit' (from I). Thus, the common code number '5' stands for common word 'habit'. So, '9' represents 'injurious'. Hence, I is sufficient.Also, '59' means 'injurious habit' and '839' means 'smoking is injurious'. Thus, the common code number '9' stands for common word 'injurious'. So, '5' represents 'habit'. Thus, II is also sufficient.,"}, {"question": "Question:  How much money do Vivek and Suman have together ?\nStatements:\n\nSuman has 20 rupees less than what Tarun has.\nVivek has 30 rupees more than what Tarun has.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I, we have: S = T - 20.From II, we have: V = T + 30.Thus, from both I and II, we have: V + S = (T + 30) + (T - 20) = (2 T + 10).So, to get the required amount, we need to know the amount that Tarun has."}, {"question": "Question:  Among Monika, Anita, Sonal, Ratna and Tanvy, who came last for the programme ?\nStatements:\n\nMonika came after Anita but not after Tanvy.\nRatna came after Tanvy but not after Sonal.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we have the order : A, M, T.From II, we have the order: T, R, S.Combining the above two, we get the order: A, M, T, R, S.Thus, Sonal came last for the programme."}, {"question": "Question:  Who among P, Q, R, S and T is the lightest?\nStatements:\n\nR is heavier than Q and T but lighter than S.\nS is not the heaviest.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I, we have: R>Q, R>T, S>R i.e. S>R>Q>T or S>R>T>Q.From II, S is not the heaviest. So, P is the heaviest. Thus, we have: P > S > R > Q > T or P > S > R > T > Q. Hence, either T or Q is the lightest."}, {"question": "Question:  How is T related to K?\nStatements:\n\nK has two sons; one of the sons is A.\nThe mother of T has only two sons - Aand B.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From II, we know that T's mother has only two sons, A and B. This implies that T is the sister of both A and B. But, from I, A is also K's son. So, T is the daughter of K."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the shortest distance between Devipur and Durgapur ?\nStatements:\n\nDurgapur is 20 kms away from Rampur.\nDevipur is 15 kms away from Rampur.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, the distance of each village from Rampur is given in I and II. But nothing about their relative positions is mentioned. So, the distance between the two villages cannot be calculated."}, {"question": "Question:  How is A related to D ?\nStatements:\n\nB is the brother of A.\nB is D's son.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I and II, we conclude that A is either son or daughter of D."}, {"question": "Question:  Manoj, Prabhakar, Akash and Kamal are four friends. Who among them is the heaviest ?\nStatements:\n\nPrabhakar is heavier than Manoj and Kamal but lighter than Akash.\nManoj is lighter than Prabhakar and Akash but heavier than Kamal.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From I, we have: P > M, P > K, A > P.Thus, A > P > M > K or A > P > K > M. So, Akash is the heaviest.From II, we have: P > M, A > M, M > K.Thus, A > P > M > K or P > A > M > K. So, either Akash or Prabhakar is the heaviest."}, {"question": "Question:  Vinod's and Javed's salaries are in the proportion of 4 : 3 respectively. What is Vinod's salary ?\nStatements:\n\nJaved's salary is 75% that of Vinod's salary.\nJaved's salary is Rs 4500.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Statement I is merely an interpretation of the information contained in the question.However, Vinod's salary can be ascertained from II as follows : Let Vinod's and Javed's salaries be 4x and 3x respectively. Then, 3x = 4500 or x = 1500. Therefore Vinod's salary = 4x = Rs. 6000."}, {"question": "Question:  What is Nitin's rank from the top in a class of forty students ?\nStatements:\n\nThere are ten students between Nitin and Deepak.\nDeepak is twentieth from the top.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since there are ten students between Nitin and Deepak, so Nitin may be eleven ranks above or below Deepak. Thus, Nitin may be 9th or 31st from the top."}, {"question": "Question:  Which direction is Sunny facing now ?\nStatements:\n\nIf Sunny turns to his right and again turns to his right, he will be facing North.\nIf Sunny walks some distance and turns left and again walks some distance, then his face will be towards left of Dinesh who is facing South.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Sunny is facing South, since a person facing South shall face North on turning to his right, twice.From II, we know that after walking, Sunny shall face towards left of Dinesh facing South i.e. East and a person walking southwards shall face East on turning to 'his left.Thus, Sunny is facing South."}, {"question": "Question:  T studies in which of the schools B, C, D, E and F ?\nStatements:\n\nT does not study in the same school as either R or J.\nR and J study in schools D and F respectively.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As given in I and II, R studies in school D and J studies in school F. So, T does not study in school D or school F. Thus, T studies in any one of the schools B, C or E."}, {"question": "Question:  How is Divya related to Shaloo ?\nStatements:\n\nDivya's mother is sister of Shaloo's father.\nShaloo is the daughter of Divya's grandfather's only child.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Divya's mother is Shaloo's aunt or Divya is Shaloo's cousin.Now, Divya's grandfather's only child is Divya's parent. So, from II, we conclude that Shaloo and Divya are daughters of the same parents i.e. Divya is Shaloo's sister."}, {"question": "Question:  How many New Year's greeting cards were sold this year in your shop ?\nStatements:\n\nLast year 2935 cards were sold.\nThe number of cards sold this year was 1.2 times that of last year.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From both I and II, we find that the number of cards sold this year = (2935 x 1.2) = 3522."}, {"question": "Question:  On which day in April is Gautam's birthday?\nStatements:\n\nGautam was born exactly 28 years after his mother was born.\nHis mother will be 55 years 4 months and 5 days on August 18 this year.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the birthday of Gautam's mother can be found out from II and then Gautam's birthday can be determined using the fact given in I."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the code for 'is' in the code language ?\nStatements:\n\nIn the code language, 'shi tu ke' means 'pen is blue'.\nIn the same code language, 'ke si re' means 'this is wonderful'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "In I and II, the common word is 'is' and the common code word is 'ke'. So, 'ke' is the code for 'is'."}, {"question": "Question:  Among A, B, C, D and E, who is in the middle while standing in a row ?\nStatements:\n\nC, who is third to the left of D, is to the immediate right of A and second to the left of E.\nC is second to the left of E, who is not at any of the ends and who is third to the right of A. D is at one of the ends.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From each one of I and II, we get the order : A, C, B, E, D. Clearly, B is in the middle."}, {"question": "Question:  Among A, B, C, D, E and F, who is the heaviest ?\nStatements:\n\nA and D are heavier than B, E and F but none of them is the heaviest.\nA is heavier than D but lighter than C.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that since none of A and D is the heaviest and each one of B, E and F is lighter than both A and D, so C is the heaviest."}, {"question": "Which symbol will be on the face opposite to the face with symbol * ?", "opta": "@", "optb": "$", "optc": "8", "optd": "+", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The symbols of the adjacent faces to the face with symbol * are @, -, + and $. Hence the required symbol is 8."}, {"question": "Two positions of dice are shown below. How many points will appear on the opposite to the face containing 5 points?", "opta": "3", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In these two positions one of the common face having 1 point is in the same position. Therefore according to rule (2). There will be 4 points on the required face."}, {"question": "Which digit will appear on the face opposite to the face with number 4?", "opta": "3", "optb": "5", "optc": "6", "optd": "2/3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Here the common faces with number 3, are in same positions. Hence 6 is opposite to 2 and 5 is opposite to 1. Therefore 4 is opposite to 3."}, {"question": "Two positions of a dice are shown below. Which number will appear on the face opposite to the face with the number 5?", "opta": "2/6", "optb": "2", "optc": "6", "optd": "4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "According to the rule no. (3), common faces with number 3, are in same positions. Hence the number of the opposite face to face with number 5 will be 6."}, {"question": "How many points will be on the face opposite to in face which contains 2 points?", "opta": "1", "optb": "5", "optc": "4", "optd": "6", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In first two positions of dice one common face containing 5 is same. Therefore according to rule no. (3) the face opposite to the face which contains 2 point, will contains 6 points."}, {"question": "Which number is on the face opposite to 6?", "opta": "4", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As the numbers 2, 3, 4 and 5 are adjacent to 6. Hence the number on the face opposite to 6 is 1."}, {"question": "Two positions of a dice are shown below. When number '1' is on the top. What number will be at the bottom?", "opta": "3", "optb": "5", "optc": "2", "optd": "6", "ans": "B", "explanation": "According to the rule (2) when 'one' is at the top, then 5 will be at the bottom."}, {"question": "Two positions of a cube with its surfaces numbered are shown below. When the surface 4 touch the bottom, what surface will be on the top?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "5", "optd": "6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In these 2 positions one common face with number 1 is in the same position. Hence according to the rule number (3), 2 is opposite 6 and 3 is opposite to 5. Therefore opposite to 4 is 1."}, {"question": "Here two positions of dice are shown. If there are two dots in the bottom, then how many dots will be on the top?", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "5", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Here the common faces with 4 dots are in same positions.\nHence 2 will be opposite to 5."}, {"question": "Two positions of dice are shown below. How many points will be on the top when 2 points are at the bottom?", "opta": "6", "optb": "5", "optc": "4", "optd": "1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In these 2 positions of a dice, one common face having points 3 is in the same position. Hence according to rule (3), there will be 4 points on the required face."}, {"question": "Here 4 positions of a cube are shown. Which sign will be opposite to '+' ?", "opta": "%", "optb": "-", "optc": "x", "optd": "$", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From position I and III common face with % is in the same position. Hence according to rule (3) opposite is X."}, {"question": "Two positions of a cubical block are shown. When 5 is at the top which number will be at bottom?", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In these 2 positions one common face with number 3, is in same position. Hence according to rule (3), 1 is opposite to 6 and 4 is opposite to 2. Therefore 5 is opposite to 3."}, {"question": "From the four positions of a dice given below, find the color which is opposite to yellow ?", "opta": "Violet", "optb": "Red", "optc": "Rose", "optd": "Blue", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The colours adjacent to yellow are orange, blue, red and rose. Hence violet will be opposite to yellow."}, {"question": "When the digit 5 is on the bottom then which number will be on its upper surface?", "opta": "1", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the rule no. (3), common faces with number 2 are in same positions. Hence when the digit 5 is on the bottom then 1 will on the upper surface."}, {"question": "How many points will be on the face opposite to the face which contains 3 points?", "opta": "2", "optb": "4", "optc": "5", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The adjacent faces to the face which 3 points have 2, 1, 4 and 6 points. Hence on the face which is opposite to the face which contains 3 points, there will be 5 points."}, {"question": "Observe the dots on the dice (one to six dots) in the following figures. How many dots are contained on the face opposite to the containing four dots?", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "5", "optd": "6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Here one of the two common faces (5) is in the same position, then according to the rule no (2) the remaining face with the 4 dots will be opposite to face with dots 2."}, {"question": "Two positions of a dice are shown below. When 3 points are at the bottom, how many points will be at the top?", "opta": "2", "optb": "5", "optc": "4", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "According to the rule (2) when 3 points are at the bottom then 4 points will be at the top."}, {"question": "From the positions of a cube are shown below, Which letter will be on the face opposite to face with 'A'?", "opta": "D", "optb": "B", "optc": "C", "optd": "F", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The letters of the adjacent faces to the face with letter A, are B, F, C and E. Hence D is the letter of the face opposite to the face with letters (A)."}, {"question": "One morning Udai and Vishal were talking to each other face to face at a crossing. If Vishal's shadow was exactly to the left of Udai, which direction was Udai facing?", "opta": "East", "optb": "West", "optc": "North", "optd": "South", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Y is in the East of X which is in the North of Z. If P is in the South of Z, then in which direction of Y, is P?", "opta": "North", "optb": "South", "optc": "South-East", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "P is in South-West of Y."}, {"question": "If South-East becomes North, North-East becomes West and so on. What will West become?", "opta": "North-East", "optb": "North-West", "optc": "South-East", "optd": "South-West", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It is clear from the diagrams that new name of West will become South-East."}, {"question": "A man walks 5 km toward south and then turns to the right. After walking 3 km he turns to the left and walks 5 km. Now in which direction is he from the starting place?", "opta": "West", "optb": "South", "optc": "North-East", "optd": "South-West", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Hence required direction is South-West."}, {"question": "Rahul put his timepiece on the table in such a way that at 6 P.M. hour hand points to North. In which direction the minute hand will point at 9.15 P.M. ?", "opta": "South-East", "optb": "South", "optc": "North", "optd": "West", "ans": "D", "explanation": "At 9.15 P.M., the minute hand will point towards west."}, {"question": "Rasik walked 20 m towards north. Then he turned right and walks 30 m. Then he turns right and walks 35 m. Then he turns left and walks 15 m. Finally he turns left and walks 15 m. In which direction and how many metres is he from the starting position?", "opta": "15 m West", "optb": "30 m East", "optc": "30 m West", "optd": "45 m East", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Two cars start from the opposite places of a main road, 150 km apart. First car runs for 25 km and takes a right turn and then runs 15 km. It then turns left and then runs for another 25 km and then takes the direction back to reach the main road. In the mean time, due to minor break down the other car has run only 35 km along the main road. What would be the distance between two cars at this point?", "opta": "65 km", "optb": "75 km", "optc": "80 km", "optd": "85 km", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Starting from the point X, Jayant walked 15 m towards west. He turned left and walked 20 m. He then turned left and walked 15 m. After this he turned to his right and walked 12 m. How far and in which directions is now Jayant from X?", "opta": "32 m, South", "optb": "47 m, East", "optc": "42 m, North", "optd": "27 m, South", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "One evening before sunset Rekha and Hema were talking to each other face to face. If Hema's shadow was exactly to the right of Hema, which direction was Rekha facing?", "opta": "North", "optb": "South", "optc": "East", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In the evening sun sets in West. Hence then any shadow falls in the East. Since Hema's shadow was to the right of Hema. Hence Rekha was facing towards South."}, {"question": "A boy rode his bicycle Northward, then turned left and rode 1 km and again turned left and rode 2 km. He found himself 1 km west of his starting point. How far did he ride northward initially?", "opta": "1 km", "optb": "2 km", "optc": "3 km", "optd": "5 km", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The boy rode 2 km. Northward."}, {"question": "K is 40 m South-West of L. If M is 40 m South-East of L, then M is in which direction of K?", "opta": "East", "optb": "West", "optc": "North-East", "optd": "South", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Hence M is in the East of K."}, {"question": "A man walks 2 km towards North. Then he turns to East and walks 10 km. After this he turns to North and walks 3 km. Again he turns towards East and walks 2 km. How far is he from the starting point?", "opta": "10 km", "optb": "13 km", "optc": "15 km", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "The length and breadth of a room are 8 m and 6 m respectively. A cat runs along all the four walls and finally along a diagonal order to catch a rat. How much total distance is covered by the cat?", "opta": "10", "optb": "14", "optc": "38", "optd": "48", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "One morning sujata started to walk towards the Sun. After covering some distance she turned to right then again to the right and after covering some distance she again turns to the right. Now in which direction is she facing?", "opta": "North", "optb": "South", "optc": "North-East", "optd": "South-West", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Hence finally Sujata will face towards North."}, {"question": "Some boys are sitting in three rows all facing North such that A is in the middle row. P is just to the right of A but in the same row. Q is just behind of P while R is in the North of A. In which direction of R is Q?", "opta": "South", "optb": "South-West", "optc": "North-East", "optd": "South-East", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Q is in South-East of R."}, {"question": "One morning after sunrise, Vimal started to walk. During this walking he met Stephen who was coming from opposite direction. Vimal watch that the shadow of Stephen to the right of him (Vimal). To Which direction Vimal was facing?", "opta": "East", "optb": "West", "optc": "South", "optd": "Data inadequate", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Sun rises in the east. So the shadow of a man will always falls towards the west. Since the shadow of Stephen is to the right of Vimal. Hence Vimal is facing towards South."}, {"question": "Golu started from his house towards North. After covering a distance of 8 km. he turned towards left and covered a distance of 6 km. What is the shortest distance now from his house?", "opta": "10 km.", "optb": "16 km.", "optc": "14 km", "optd": "2 km.", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "P started from his house towards west. After walking a distance of 25 m. He turned to the right and walked 10 m. He then again turned to the right and walked 15 m. After this he is to turn right at 135o and to cover 30 m. In which direction should he go?", "opta": "West", "optb": "South", "optc": "South-West", "optd": "South-East", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Hence he should go in the South-West direction."}, {"question": "X started to walk straight towards south. After walking 5 m he turned to the left and walked 3 m. After this he turned to the right and walked 5 m Now to which direction X is facing?", "opta": "North-East", "optb": "South", "optc": "North", "optd": "South-West", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Hence X will face in the end towards South."}, {"question": "Hemant in order to go to university started from his house in the east and came to a crossing. The road to the left ends in a theatre, straight ahead is the hospital. In which direction is the university?", "opta": "North", "optb": "South", "optc": "East", "optd": "West", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Therefore university is in North."}, {"question": "After walking 6 km, I turned to the right and then walked 2 km. After then I turned to the left and walked 10 km. In the end, I was moving towards the North. From which direction did I start my journey?", "opta": "North", "optb": "South", "optc": "East", "optd": "West", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The journey was started from the South."}, {"question": "Ravi left home and cycled 10 km towards South, then turned right and cycled 5 km and then again turned right and cycled 10 km. After this he turned left and cycled 10 km. How many kilometers will he have to cycle to reach his home straight?", "opta": "10 km", "optb": "15 km", "optc": "20 km", "optd": "25 km", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Reena walked from A to B in the East 10 feet. Then she turned to the right and walked 3 feet. Again she turned to the right and walked 14 feet. How far is she from A?", "opta": "4 feet", "optb": "5 feet", "optc": "24 feet", "optd": "27 feet", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "One morning after sunrise Nivedita and Niharika were talking to each other face to face at Dalphin crossing. If Niharika's shadow was exactly to the right of Nivedita, Which direction Niharika was facing?", "opta": "North", "optb": "South", "optc": "East", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In the morning sun rises in the East. Hence then any shadow falls in the West. Since Nikharia's shadow was exactly to the right of Nivedita. Hence Nikharia is facing towards North."}, {"question": "If A x B means A is to the south of B; A + B means A is to the north of B; A % B means A is to the east of B; A - B means A is to the west of B; then in P % Q + R - S, S is in which direction with respect to Q?", "opta": "South-West", "optb": "South-East", "optc": "North-East", "optd": "North-West", "ans": "B", "explanation": "According to P % Q + R - S\n\nS is in the South-East of Q."}, {"question": "One morning after sunrise, Suresh was standing facing a pole. The shadow of the pole fell exactly to his right. To which direction was he facing?", "opta": "East", "optb": "South", "optc": "West", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Sun rises in the east in the morning. Since the shadow of Suresh falls to his right. So he is facing South."}, {"question": "A child went 90 m in the East to look for his father, then he turned right and went 20 m. After this he turned right and after going 30 m he reached to his uncle's house. His father was not there. From there he went 100 m to his north and met his father. How far did he meet his father from the starting point?", "opta": "80 m", "optb": "100 m", "optc": "140 m", "optd": "260 m", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Four friends A, B, C and D live in a same locality. The house of B is in the east of A's house but in the north of C's house. The house of C is in the west of D's house. D's house is in which direction of A's house?", "opta": "South-East", "optb": "North-East", "optc": "East", "optd": "Data is inadequate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Therefore, D's house is in the South-East direction of A."}, {"question": "Umesh directly went from P, to Q which is 9 feet distant. Then he turns to the right and walked 4 feet. After this he turned to the right and walked a distance which is equal from P to Q. Finally he turned to the right and walked 3 feet. How far is he now from P?", "opta": "6 feet", "optb": "5 feet", "optc": "1 feet", "optd": "0 feet", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Shyam walks 5 km towards East and then turns left and walks 6 km. Again he turns right and walks 9 km. Finally he turns to his right and walks 6 km. How far is he from the starting point?", "opta": "26 km", "optb": "21 km", "optc": "14 km", "optd": "9 km", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Amit started walking positioning his back towards the sun. After some time, he turned left, then turned right and towards the left again. In which direction is he going now?", "opta": "North or South", "optb": "East or West", "optc": "North or West", "optd": "South or West", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If he starts walking the morning then finally he will face towards South and if he starts in the evening then finally he will face towards North."}, {"question": "Rohit walked 25 m towards south. Then he turned to his left and walked 20 m. He then turned to his left and walked 25 m. He again turned to his right and walked 15 m. At what distance is he from the starting point and in which direction?", "opta": "35 m East", "optb": "35 m North", "optc": "30 m West", "optd": "45 m East", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Village Q is to the North of the village P. The village R is in the East of Village Q. The village S is to the left of the village P. In which direction is the village S with respect to village R?", "opta": "West", "optb": "South-West", "optc": "South", "optd": "North-West", "ans": "B", "explanation": "S is to the South-West of R."}, {"question": "Radha moves towards South-East a distance of 7 km, then she moves towards West and travels a distance of 14 km. From here she moves towards North-West a distance of 7 km and finally she moves a distance of 4 km towards east. How far is she now from the starting point?", "opta": "3 km", "optb": "4 km", "optc": "10 km", "optd": "11 km", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Sundar runs 20 m towards East and turns to right and runs 10 m. Then he turns to the right and runs 9 m. Again he turns to right and runs 5 m. After this he turns to left and runs 12 m and finally he turns to right and 6 m. Now to which direction is Sundar facing?", "opta": "East", "optb": "West", "optc": "North", "optd": "South", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Therefore, it is clear that Sundar will face towards North."}, {"question": "Sachin walks 20 km towards North. He turns left and walks 40 km. He again turns left and walks 20 km. Finally he moves 20 km after turning to the left. How far is he from his starting position?", "opta": "20 km.", "optb": "30 km.", "optc": "50 km.", "optd": "60 km.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Required distance = 40 - 20 = 20 km."}, {"question": "From his house, Lokesh went 15 km to the North. Then he turned west and covered 10 km. Then he turned south and covered 5 km. Finally turning to the east, he covered 10 km. In which direction is he from his house?", "opta": "East", "optb": "West", "optc": "North", "optd": "South", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Therefore, it is clear that he is in the North from his house."}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Key2. Door3. Lock\n4. Room5. Switch on", "opta": "5, 1, 2, 4, 3", "optb": "4, 2, 1, 5, 3", "optc": "1, 3, 2, 4, 5", "optd": "1, 2, 3, 5, 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nKeyLockDoorRoomSwitch on\n13245"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Word2. Paragraph3. Sentence\n4. Letters5. Phrase", "opta": "4, 1, 5, 2, 3", "optb": "4, 1, 3, 5, 2", "optc": "4, 2, 5, 1, 3", "optd": "4, 1, 5, 3, 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nLettersWordPhraseSentenceParagraph\n41532"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Police2. Punishment3. Crime\n4. Judge5. Judgement", "opta": "3, 1, 2, 4, 5", "optb": "1, 2, 4, 3, 5", "optc": "5, 4, 3, 2, 1", "optd": "3, 1, 4, 5, 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nCrimePoliceJudgeJudgementPunishment\n31452"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Family2. Community3. Member\n4. Locality5. Country", "opta": "3, 1, 2, 4, 5", "optb": "3, 1, 2, 5, 4", "optc": "3, 1, 4, 2, 5", "optd": "3, 1, 4, 5, 2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nMemberFamilyCommunityLocalityCountry\n31245"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Poverty2. Population3. Death\n4. Unemployment5. Disease", "opta": "2, 3, 4, 5, 1", "optb": "3, 4, 2, 5, 1", "optc": "2, 4, 1, 5, 3", "optd": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nPopulationUnemploymentPovertyDiseaseDeath\n24153"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Leaf2. Fruit3. Stem\n4. Root5. Flower", "opta": "3, 4, 5, 1, 2", "optb": "4, 3, 1, 5, 2", "optc": "4, 1, 3, 5, 2", "optd": "4, 3, 1, 2, 5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nRootStemLeafFlowerFruit\n43152"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Nation2. Village3. City\n4. District5. State", "opta": "2, 3, 4, 5, 1", "optb": "2, 3, 4, 1, 5", "optc": "1, 3, 5, 4, 2", "optd": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nVillageCityDistrictStateNation\n23451"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Caste2. Family3. Newly married Couple\n4. Clan5. Species", "opta": "2, 3, 1, 4, 5", "optb": "3, 4, 5, 1, 2", "optc": "3, 2, 1, 4, 5", "optd": "4, 5, 3, 2, 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nNewly married CoupleFamilyCasteClanSpecies\n32145"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Cut2. Put on3. Mark\n4. Measure5. Tailor", "opta": "3, 1, 5, 4, 2", "optb": "2, 4, 3, 1, 5", "optc": "1, 3, 2, 4, 5", "optd": "4, 3, 1, 5, 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nMeasureMarkCutTailorPut on\n43152"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. House2. Street3. Room\n4. Town5. District", "opta": "3, 2, 1, 4, 5", "optb": "3, 1, 4, 2, 5", "optc": "3, 1, 2, 4, 5", "optd": "3, 1, 2, 5, 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nRoomHouseStreetTownDistrict\n31245"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Wall2. Clay3. House\n4. Room5. Bricks", "opta": "5, 2, 1, 4, 3", "optb": "2, 5, 4, 1, 3", "optc": "2, 5, 1, 4, 3", "optd": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nClayBricksWallRoomHouse\n25143"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Probation2. Interview3. Selection\n4. Appointment5. Advertisement6. Application", "opta": "5, 6, 3, 2, 4, 1", "optb": "5, 6, 4, 2, 3, 1", "optc": "5, 6, 2, 3, 4, 1", "optd": "6, 5, 4, 2, 3, 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nAdvertisementApplicationInterviewSelectionAppointmentProbation\n562341"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Elephant2. Cat3. Mosquito\n4. Tiger5. Whale", "opta": "5, 3, 1, 2, 4", "optb": "3, 2, 4, 1, 5", "optc": "1, 3, 5, 4, 2", "optd": "2, 5, 1, 4, 3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nMosquitoCatTigerElephantWhale\n32415"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Yarn2. Plant3. Saree\n4. Cotton5. Cloth", "opta": "2, 4, 5, 1, 3", "optb": "2, 4, 3, 5, 1", "optc": "2, 4, 1, 5, 3", "optd": "2, 4, 5, 3, 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nPlantCottonYarnClothSaree\n24153"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Infant2. Old3. Adult\n4. Adolescent5. Child", "opta": "5, 4, 3, 2, 1", "optb": "3, 4, 2, 1, 5", "optc": "2, 3, 4, 5, 1", "optd": "1, 5, 4, 3, 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nInfantChildAdolescentAdultOld\n15432"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Leaves2. Branch3. Flower\n4. Tree5. Fruit", "opta": "4, 3, 1, 2, 5", "optb": "4, 2, 5, 1, 3", "optc": "4, 3, 2, 1, 5", "optd": "4, 2, 1, 3, 5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nTreeBranchLeavesFlowerFruit\n42135"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Tree2. Seed3. Flowers\n4. Fruit5. Plant", "opta": "5, 2, 1, 3, 4", "optb": "2, 5, 1, 4, 3", "optc": "2, 5, 1, 3, 4", "optd": "2, 5, 3, 1, 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nSeedPlantTreeFlowersFruit\n25134"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Adult2. Child3. Infant\n4. Boy5. Adolescent", "opta": "1, 3, 4, 5, 2", "optb": "2, 3, 5, 4, 1", "optc": "2, 3, 4, 1, 5", "optd": "3, 2, 4, 5, 1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nInfantChildBoyAdolescentAdult\n32451"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Protect2. Pressure3. Relief\n4. Rain5. Flood", "opta": "2, 4, 3, 1, 5", "optb": "2, 4, 5, 1, 3", "optc": "2, 5, 4, 1, 3", "optd": "3, 2, 4, 5, 1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nPressureRainFloodProtectRelief\n24513"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Presentation2. Recommendation3. Arrival\n4. Discussion5. Introduction", "opta": "5, 3, 4, 1, 2", "optb": "3, 5, 4, 2, 1", "optc": "3, 5, 1, 4, 2", "optd": "5, 3, 1, 2, 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nArrivalIntroductionPresentationDiscussionRecommendation\n35142"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Income2. Status3. Education\n4. Well-being5. Job", "opta": "3, 1, 5, 2, 4", "optb": "1, 3, 2, 5, 4", "optc": "1, 2, 5, 3, 4", "optd": "3, 5, 1, 2, 4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nEducationJobIncomeStatusWell-being\n35124"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Heel2. Shoulder3. Skull4. Neck5. Knee\n6. Chest7. Thigh8. Stomach9. Face10. Hand", "opta": "3, 4, 7, 9, 2, 5, 8, 10, 6, 1", "optb": "3, 9, 4, 2, 10, 6, 8, 7, 5, 1", "optc": "2, 4, 7, 10, 1, 5, 8, 9, 6, 3", "optd": "4, 7, 10, 1, 9, 6, 2, 5, 8, 3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nSkullFaceNeckShoulderHandChestStomachThighKneeHeel\n39421068751"}, {"question": "Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n\n\n1. Rainbow2. Rain3. Sun\n4. Happy5. Child", "opta": "4, 2, 3, 5, 1", "optb": "2, 3, 1, 5, 4", "optc": "4, 5, 1, 2, 3", "optd": "2, 1, 4, 5, 3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The correct order is :\n\n\nRainSunRainbowChildHappy\n23154"}, {"question": "A, P, R, X, S and Z are sitting in a row. S and Z are in the centre. A and P are at the ends. R is sitting to the left of A. Who is to the right of P ?", "opta": "A", "optb": "X", "optc": "S", "optd": "Z", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The seating arrangement is as follows:\n\nTherefore, right of P is X."}, {"question": "There are 8 houses in a line and in each house only one boy lives with the conditions as given below:\n\nJack is not the neighbour Siman.\nHarry is just next to the left of Larry.\nThere is at least one to the left of Larry.\nPaul lives in one of the two houses in the middle.\nMike lives in between Paul and Larry.\n\nIf at least one lives to the right of Robert and Harry is not between Taud and Larry, then which one of the following statement is not correct ?", "opta": "Robert is not at the left end.", "optb": "Robert is in between Simon and Taud.", "optc": "Taud is in between Paul and Jack.", "optd": "There are three persons to the right of Paul.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A, B, C, D and E are sitting on a bench. A is sitting next to B, C is sitting next to D, D is not sitting with E who is on the left end of the bench. C is on the second position from the right. A is to the right of B and E. A and C are sitting together. In which position A is sitting ?", "opta": "Between B and D", "optb": "Between B and C", "optc": "Between E and D", "optd": "Between C and E", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Therefore, A is sitting in between B and C."}, {"question": "120, 99, 80, 63, 48, ?", "opta": "35", "optb": "38", "optc": "39", "optd": "40", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is - 21, - 19, - 17, - 15,.....So, missing term = 48 - 13 = 35."}, {"question": "589654237, 89654237, 8965423, 965423, ?", "opta": "58965", "optb": "65423", "optc": "89654", "optd": "96542", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The digits are removed one by one from the beginning and the end in order alternatelyso as to obtain the subsequent terms of the series."}, {"question": "3, 10, 101,?", "opta": "10101", "optb": "10201", "optc": "10202", "optd": "11012", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Each term in the series is obtained by adding 1 to the square of the preceding term.So, missing term = (101)2 + 1 = 10202."}, {"question": "In the series 2, 6, 18, 54, ...... what will be the 8th term ?", "opta": "4370", "optb": "4374", "optc": "7443", "optd": "7434", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, 2 x 3 = 6, 6 x 3 = 18, 18 x 3 = 54,.....So, the series is a G.P. in which a = 2, r = 3.Therefore 8th term = ar8-1 = ar7 = 2 x 37 = (2 x 2187) = 4374."}, {"question": "125,80,45,20,?", "opta": "5", "optb": "8", "optc": "10", "optd": "12", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is - 45, - 35, - 25, .....So, missing term = 20 - 15 = 5."}, {"question": "1, 1, 4, 8, 9, 27, 16, ?", "opta": "32", "optb": "64", "optc": "81", "optd": "256", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The series consists of squares and cubes of consecutive natural numbers i.e. 12, 13, 22, 23, 32, 33, 42, .....So, missing term = 43 = 64."}, {"question": "1, 2, 3, 6, 9, 18, ?, 54", "opta": "18", "optb": "27", "optc": "36", "optd": "81", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is x 2, x 3/2, x 2, x 3/2, x 2,.....So, missing term = 18 x 3/2 = 27."}, {"question": "6, 13, 25, 51, 101, ?", "opta": "201", "optb": "202", "optc": "203", "optd": "205", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is x 2 + 1, x 2 - 1, x 2 + 1, x 2 - 1,.....So, missing term = 101 x 2 + 1 = 203."}, {"question": "5,6,9, 15, ?, 40", "opta": "21", "optb": "25", "optc": "27", "optd": "33", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 1, + 3, + 6,....., i.e. + 1, + (1, + 2), + (1 + 2 + 3),.....So, missing term = 15 + (1 + 2 + 3 + 4) = 25."}, {"question": "1, 3, 4, 8, 15, 27, ?", "opta": "37", "optb": "44", "optc": "50", "optd": "55", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The sum of any three consecutive terms of the series gives the next term.So, missing number = 8 + 15 + 27 = 50."}, {"question": "3, 4, 7, 7, 13, 13, 21, 22, 31, 34, ?", "opta": "42", "optb": "43", "optc": "51", "optd": "52", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of two series :I. 3, 7, 13, 21, 31, ? and II. 4, 7, 13, 22, 34The pattern in I is + 4, + 6, + 8, + 10,.....The pattern in II is + 3, + 6, + 9, + 12,.....So, missing term = 31 + 12 = 43."}, {"question": "198, 194, 185, 169, ?", "opta": "92", "optb": "112", "optc": "136", "optd": "144", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is - 4, - 9, - 16,.....i.e. - 22, - 32, - 42,.....So, missing pattern = 169 - 52 = 169 - 25 = 144."}, {"question": "2, 3, 5,7,11,?, 17", "opta": "12", "optb": "13", "optc": "14", "optd": "15", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the given series consists of prime numbers starting from 2. So, the missingterm is the prime number after 11, which is 13."}, {"question": "6, 12, 21, ?, 48", "opta": "33", "optb": "38", "optc": "40", "optd": "45", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is + 6, + 9, + 12, + 15, .....So, missing term = 21 + 12 = 33."}, {"question": "Which term of the series 5, 10, 20, 40, ..... is 1280?", "opta": "10th", "optb": "9th", "optc": "8th", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, 5 x 2 = 10, 10 x 2 = 20, 20 x 2 = 40,.....So, the series is a G.P. in which a = 5 and r = 2.Let 1280 be the rath term of the series.Then, 5x2n-1 = 1280  2n-1 = 256 = 28  n - 1 = 8  n = 9."}, {"question": "2, 5, 9, ?, 20, 27", "opta": "14", "optb": "16", "optc": "18", "optd": "24", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is + 3, + 4, + 5, + 6,.....So, missing term = 9 + 5 = 14."}, {"question": "2, 3, 3, 5, 10, 13, ?, 43, 172, 177", "opta": "23", "optb": "38", "optc": "39", "optd": "40", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 1, x 1, + 2, x 2, + 3, x 3, + 4, x 4, + 5.So, missing term = 13 x 3 = 39."}, {"question": "9, 27, 31, 155, 161, 1127, ?", "opta": "316", "optb": "1135", "optc": "1288", "optd": "2254", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is x 3, + 4, x 5, + 6, x 7,.....So, missing term = 1127 + 8 = 1135."}, {"question": "2, 1, 2, 4, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 8, 10, 11, ?", "opta": "9", "optb": "10", "optc": "11", "optd": "12", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of three series :I. 1st, 4th, 7th, 10th, 13th terms i.e. 2, 4, 6, 8, ?II. 2nd, 5th, 8th, 11th terms i.e. 1, 4, 7, 10III. 3rd, 6th, 9th, 12th terms i.e. 2, 5, 8, 11Clearly, I consists of consecutive even numbers. So, the missing term is 10."}, {"question": "Which of the following will not be a number of the series 1, 8, 27, 64, 125,.....?", "opta": "256", "optb": "512", "optc": "729", "optd": "1000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The given series consists of cubes of natural numbers only. 256 is not the cube ofany natural number."}, {"question": "13, 32, 24, 43, 35, ?, 46, 65, 57, 76", "opta": "45", "optb": "52", "optc": "54", "optd": "55", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of two series:I. 13, 24, 35, 46, 57 and II. 32, 43, ?, 65, 76The pattern in both I and II is + 11. So, missing term = 43 + 11 = 54."}, {"question": "22, 24, 28, ?, 52, 84", "opta": "36", "optb": "38", "optc": "42", "optd": "46", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is + 2, + 4, + 8, + 16,.....So, missing term = 28 + 8 = 36."}, {"question": "3, 15, ?, 63, 99, 143", "opta": "27", "optb": "35", "optc": "45", "optd": "56", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The terms of the given series are (22 - 1), (42 - 1),....., (82 - 1), (102 - 1), (122 - 1).So, missing term = (62 - 1) - (36 - 1) = 35."}, {"question": "90, 180, 12, 50, 100, 200, ?, 3, 50, 4, 25, 2, 6, 30, 3", "opta": "150", "optb": "175", "optc": "225", "optd": "250", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, 90 = 30 x 3, 180 = 6 x 30, 12 = 2 x 6, 50 = 25 x 2, 100 = 4 x 25, 200 = 50 x 4.So, missing term = 3 x 50 = 150."}, {"question": "48, 24, 96, 48, 192, ?", "opta": "76", "optb": "90", "optc": "96", "optd": "98", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is \u00f7 2, x 4, \u00f7 2, x 4, .....So, missing term = 192 \u00f7 2 = 96."}, {"question": "2,15,41,80,?", "opta": "111", "optb": "120", "optc": "121", "optd": "132", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 13, + 26, + 39,.....So, missing term = 80 + 52 = 132."}, {"question": "6, 11, 21, 36, 56, ?", "opta": "42", "optb": "51", "optc": "81", "optd": "91", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 5, + 10, + 15, + 20, ...So, missing term = 56 + 25 = 81."}, {"question": "563, 647, 479, 815, ?", "opta": "672", "optb": "386", "optc": "279", "optd": "143", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 84, - 168, + 336,.....i.e. + 84, - (84 x 2), + (84 x 22), .....So, missing term = 815 - (84 x 23) = 815 - 672 = 143."}, {"question": "13, 35, 57, 79, 911, ?", "opta": "1110", "optb": "1112", "optc": "1113", "optd": "1315", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The terms of the given series are numbers formed by joining together consecutiveodd numbers in order i.e. 1 and 3, 3 and 5, 5 and 7, 7 and 9, 9 and 11, .....So, missing term = number formed by joining 11 and 13 = 1113."}, {"question": "1, 4, 10, 22, 46, ?", "opta": "64", "optb": "86", "optc": "94", "optd": "122", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 3, + 6, + 12, + 24,.....So, missing term = 46 + 48 = 94."}, {"question": "66, 36, 18, ?", "opta": "3", "optb": "6", "optc": "8", "optd": "9", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Each term in the series is the product of the digits of the preceding term.So, missing term = 1 x 8 = 8."}, {"question": "In the series 3, 9, 15, ...... what will be the 21st term?", "opta": "117", "optb": "121", "optc": "123", "optd": "129", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Clearly, 3 + 6 = 9, 9 + 6 = 15,.....So, the series is an A.P. in which a = 3 and d = 6.Therefore 21st term = a + (21 - 1) d = a + 20d = 3 + 20 x 6 = 123."}, {"question": "28, 33, 31, 36, ?, 39", "opta": "32", "optb": "34", "optc": "38", "optd": "40", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 5, - 2, + 5, - 2,.....So, missing term = 36 - 2 = 34."}, {"question": "1, 9, 25, 49, 81, ?", "opta": "100", "optb": "112", "optc": "121", "optd": "144", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The series consists of squares of consecutive odd numbersi.e. 12, 32, 52, 72, 92,.....So, missing term = 112 = 121."}, {"question": "1, 9, 25, 49, ?, 121", "opta": "64", "optb": "81", "optc": "91", "optd": "100", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given series consists of squares of consecutive odd numbersi.e. 12, 32, 52, 72,.....So, missing term = 92 = 81."}, {"question": "2,2,5, 13,28,?", "opta": "49", "optb": "50", "optc": "51", "optd": "52", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 0, + 3, + 8, + 15, ..... i.e. + (l2 - 1), + (22 - 1), + (32 - 1), + (42 - 1), .....So, missing term = 28 + (52 - 1) = 28 + 24 = 52."}, {"question": "0, 2, 8, 14, ?, 34", "opta": "20", "optb": "23", "optc": "24.", "optd": "25", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 2, + 6, + 6, + 10, + 10,.....So, missing term = 14 + 10 = 24."}, {"question": "1, 5, 14, 30, 55, 91, ?", "opta": "130", "optb": "140", "optc": "150", "optd": "160", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 4, + 9, + 16, + 25, + 36, ..... i.e. + 22, + 32, + 42, + 52, + 62,.....So, missing term = 91 + 72 = 91 + 49 = 140."}, {"question": "In the series 10, 17, 24, 31, 38,.....which of the following will be a number of the series ?", "opta": "48", "optb": "346", "optc": "574", "optd": "1003", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The given series consists of numbers each of which, on dividing by 7, leaves aremainder 3. No other number except 346 satisfies the property."}, {"question": "240, ?, 120, 40, 10, 2", "opta": "180", "optb": "240", "optc": "420", "optd": "480", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is \u00f7 1, \u00f7 2, \u00f7 3, \u00f7 4, \u00f7 5.So, missing term = 240 \u00f7 1 = 240."}, {"question": "2,3,8,27, 112,?", "opta": "226", "optb": "339", "optc": "452", "optd": "565", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is x 1 + 1, x 2 + 2, x 3 + 3, x 4 + 4,.....So, missing term = 112 x 5 + 5 = 565."}, {"question": "6, 17, 39, 72, ?", "opta": "83", "optb": "94", "optc": "116", "optd": "127", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The pattern is + 11, + 22, + 33, .....So, missing term = 72 + 44 = 116."}, {"question": "20, 20, 19, 16, 17, 13, 14, 11, ?, ?", "opta": "10, 10", "optb": "10, 11", "optc": "13, 14", "optd": "13, 16", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Let the missing terms of the series be x1 and x2.Thus, the sequence 20, 20, 19, 16, 17, 13, 14, 11, xv x2 is a combination of two series :I. 20, 19, 17, 14, x1 and II. 20, 16, 13, 11, x2The pattern in I is - 1, - 2, - 3,......So, missing term, x1 = 14 - 4 = 10.The pattern in II is - 4, - 3, - 2,......So, missing term, x2 = 11 - 1 = 10."}, {"question": "24, 60, 120, 210, ?", "opta": "300", "optb": "336", "optc": "420", "optd": "525", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 36, + 60, + 90,.....i.e. + [6 x (6 + 0)], + [6 x (6 + 4)], + [6 x (6 + 9)],...So, missing term = 210 + [6 x (6 + 15)] = 210 + 126 = 336."}, {"question": "625, 5, 125, 25, 25, ?, 5", "opta": "5", "optb": "25", "optc": "125", "optd": "625", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The given sequence is a combination of two series :I. 625, 125, 25, 5 and II. 5, 25, ?The pattern in I is \u00f7 5, while that in II is x 5. So, missing term = 25 x 5 = 125."}, {"question": "10, 100, 200, 310, ?", "opta": "400", "optb": "410", "optc": "420", "optd": "430", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The pattern is + 90 + 100, + 110,.....So, missing term = 310 + 120 = 430."}, {"question": "11, 10, ?, 100, 1001, 1000, 10001", "opta": "101", "optb": "110", "optc": "111", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The pattern is - 1, x 10 + 1, - 1, x 10 + 1, - 1, x 10 + 1, .....So, missing term = 10 x 10 + 1 = 101."}, {"question": "2, 7, 27, 107, 427, ?", "opta": "1262", "optb": "1707", "optc": "4027", "optd": "4207", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The pattern is + 5, + 20, + 80, + 320, ...... i.e. + (5 x 12), + (5 x 22), + (5 x 42), + (5 x 82),.....So, missing term = 427 + (5 x 162) = 427 + 1280 = 1707."}, {"question": "Statements: Some actors are singers. All the singers are dancers.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nSome actors are dancers.\nNo singer is actor.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: All the harmoniums are instruments. All the instruments are flutes.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nAll the flutes are instruments.\nAll the harmoniums are flutes.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: Some mangoes are yellow. Some tixo are mangoes.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nSome mangoes are green.\nTixo is a yellow.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: Some ants are parrots. All the parrots are apples.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nAll the apples are parrots.\nSome ants are apples.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: Some papers are pens. All the pencils are pens.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nSome pens are pencils.\nSome pens are papers.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: All the actors are girls. All the girls are beautiful.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nAll the actors are beautiful.\nSome girls are actors.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: All the windows are doors. No door is a wall.\r\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nSome windows are walls.\nNo wall is a door.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: All cups are books. All books are shirts.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nSome cups are not shirts.\nSome shirts are cups.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: Some cows are crows. Some crows are elephants.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nSome cows are elephants.\nAll crows are elephants.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: All the pencils are pens. All the pens are inks.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nAll the pencils are inks.\nSome inks are pencils.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: Some dogs are bats. Some bats are cats.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nSome dogs are cats.\nSome cats are dogs.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: All the trucks are flies. Some scooters are flies.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nAll the trucks are scooters.\nSome scooters are trucks.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All buildings are chalks. No chalk is toffee.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nNo building is toffee\nAll chalks are buildings.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Statements: All cars are cats. All fans are cats.\n\n\nConclusions:\n\nAll cars are fans.\nSome fans are cars.", "opta": "Only (1) conclusion follows", "optb": "Only (2) conclusion follows", "optc": "Either (1) or (2) follows", "optd": "Neither (1) nor (2) follows", "opte": "Both (1) and (2) follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Travelers, Train and Bus ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Bus and Train are different from each other but some travelers travel by bus and some travel by train."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Profit, Dividend and Bonus ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Bonus and Dividend are different from each other. But both these are parts of profit."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Women, Mothers and Engineers ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All mothers are women and some mothers and some women may be engineers."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Factory, Product and Machinery ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Product and Machinery are different from each other but both are found in Factory."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Author, Lawyer and Singer ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All the three are different professions."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Judge, Thieves and Criminals ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All the thieves are criminals while judge is different from these."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between India, Haryana and World ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Haryana is in India and India is in the World."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Pigeon, Bird and Dog ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All the pigeons are birds while dog is different from these."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Earth, Sea and Sun ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Sea is a part of Earth while Sun is different from these two."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Hockey, Football and Cricket ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All these three games are different from each other."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Iron, Lead and Nitrogen ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All these three elements are different from each other"}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Examination, Questions and Practice ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Some questions are asked in examination and some in practice but examination and practice are different from each other."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Bulb, Lamp and Light ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Bulb and Lamp are different from each other but light is obtained from both."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Lion, Dog and Snake ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All the three are different from each other."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Moon, Sun and Earth ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "All the three are different from each other."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Hospital, Nurse and Patient ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Hospital consists of nurse and patient but nurse and patient are of two different nature."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Mercury, Zinc and Metal ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Mercury and Zinc both are different from one another but belong to metal."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Teacher, Writer and Musician ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A teacher may or may not be a writer and musician. Similarly a musician may or may not be a teacher and writer and so a writer may or may not be a teacher and musician."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Boys, Girls and Students ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Tall man, Black haired people and Indians ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Furniture, Chairs and Tables ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Chairs and tables both are furniture but no chair is table."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Elephant, Carnivorous and Tiger ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Tiger is carnivorous but Elephant is different from these two."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Vegetables, Tomato and Fruits ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Class, Blackboard and School ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Blackboard is in class and class is in the school."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Rabi-Crop, Paddy and Wheat ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Wheat and Paddy are different from each other but Wheat is the Rabi-Crop."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Ass, Pet and Horse ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Ass and Horse are different from each other but both are pet."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Page, Chapter and Book ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Page is in Chapter and Chapter is in book."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Parents, Mother and Father ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Father and mother are parents but father and mother are two opposite sexes."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Men, Rodents and Living beings ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Men and Rodents are different from one another but both these belong to living beings."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Elephants, Wolves and Animals ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Elephant and Wolves bear no relationship to each other while both are animals."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between dogs, pet animals and animals ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Some dogs are pet animals but dogs and pet both are animals."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Teacher, Parents and Guardians ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Sailor, Ship and Ocean ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As ship is in the ocean in the same way sailor is in the ship."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Gold, Metal and Zinc ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Gold and Zinc are different from each other but both are metal."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Professors, Doctors and Men ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Some doctors may be professors and vice-versa.\nSome professors may be men and vice-versa.\nSome doctors may be men and vice-versa.\nSome doctors may be men and professors as well."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Teacher, Men and Women ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Men and Women are different from each other but some men may be teachers and some women may be teachers."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Oil, Wick and Lamp ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Oil and Wick are different from each other but they both are used in lamp."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Football, Player and Field ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Football, Players and Field all are different."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Sweets, Rasagulla and Apple ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Rasagulla is one of the sweets while apple is different from these."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Mammal, Cow and Bat ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Cow and Bat are different from each other but both are mammal."}, {"question": "Which of the following diagrams indicates the best relation between Paper, Stationery and Ink ?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Paper and Ink are different from one another but both these belong to stationery."}, {"question": "A train always has", "opta": "Rails", "optb": "Driver", "optc": "Guard", "optd": "Engine", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always found in 'Bravery'?", "opta": "Experience", "optb": "Power", "optc": "Courage", "optd": "Knowledge", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A song always has", "opta": "Word", "optb": "Chorus", "optc": "Musician", "optd": "Tymbal", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Yesterday I saw an ice cube which had already melted due to heat of a nearby furnace.", "opta": "Always", "optb": "Never", "optc": "Often", "optd": "Sometimes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the ice cube had already melted due to the heat of a nearby furnace so after this ice cannot remain as ice cube."}, {"question": "What is found necessarily in milk?", "opta": "Cream", "optb": "Curd", "optc": "Water", "optd": "Whiteness", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always with 'Bargain'?", "opta": "Exchange", "optb": "Sumptuousness", "optc": "Triviality", "optd": "Eloquence", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following a 'Drama' must have?", "opta": "Actors", "optb": "Story", "optc": "Sets", "optd": "Director", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A boy is sitting at the back seat of a car. When the driver suddenly starts moving the car (in forward direction), the boy experiences a backward force?", "opta": "Always", "optb": "Never", "optc": "Often", "optd": "Sometimes", "ans": "A", "explanation": "When a car suddenly starts the lower part of the boy's body will be in the motion while his upper will be at rest.\nHence he will always experience backward force:"}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always found in 'Wonder'?", "opta": "Crowd", "optb": "Lumber", "optc": "Astonishment", "optd": "Rustic", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Disclosure always involves", "opta": "Agents", "optb": "Display", "optc": "Exposition", "optd": "Secrets", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A bulb always has", "opta": "Glass", "optb": "Current", "optc": "Filament", "optd": "Light", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A mirror always", "opta": "Retracts", "optb": "Distorts", "optc": "Refracts", "optd": "Reflects", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A lotus flower always has", "opta": "Mud", "optb": "Petals", "optc": "Root", "optd": "Water", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India a widow can marry her brother-in-law although a man cannot marry the sister of his dead wife:", "opta": "Always", "optb": "Never", "optc": "Often", "optd": "Sometimes", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As there is no such tradition hence this will happen sometimes."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always found in 'Remedy of fault'?", "opta": "Punishment", "optb": "Remedy", "optc": "Fault", "optd": "Scolding", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A car always has", "opta": "Driver", "optb": "Wheels", "optc": "Bonnet", "optd": "Bumper", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Danger always involves", "opta": "Enemy", "optb": "Attack", "optc": "Fear", "optd": "Help", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A disease always has", "opta": "Cure", "optb": "Germs", "optc": "Cause", "optd": "Patient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Management always involves", "opta": "Regulation", "optb": "Counsel", "optc": "Exhortation", "optd": "Coercion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always found in 'Phrase'?", "opta": "Nomenclature", "optb": "Manifestation", "optc": "Pictorial effect", "optd": "Glossary", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If we are going early in the morning towards the south the sun will be visible at our left:", "opta": "Always", "optb": "Never", "optc": "Often", "optd": "Sometimes", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Early in the morning the sun is in the direction of east. If we are going towards the south, our face will be in the direction of South and our left hand will be in the direction of east.\nHence if we go early in the morning towards the south the sun will always be visible at our left."}, {"question": "My ten years old niece is taller than my twelve years old son:", "opta": "Always", "optb": "Never", "optc": "Often", "optd": "Sometimes", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is always in worry?", "opta": "Difficulty", "optb": "Unrest", "optc": "Non-Cooperation", "optd": "Poignancy", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always associated with 'tree'?", "opta": "Flowers", "optb": "Leaves", "optc": "Fruits", "optd": "Roots", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always associated with 'justice'?", "opta": "Hypocrisy", "optb": "Legitimate", "optc": "Magnanimity", "optd": "Diminutiveness", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A camera always has", "opta": "Reels", "optb": "Flash", "optc": "Stand", "optd": "Lens", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is found necessarily in a race?", "opta": "Judge", "optb": "Spectators", "optc": "Competitor", "optd": "Prize", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is found necessarily in game?", "opta": "Players", "optb": "Spectators", "optc": "Referee", "optd": "Victory", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always found in factories?", "opta": "Chimney", "optb": "Workers", "optc": "Electricity", "optd": "Sellers", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A hill always has", "opta": "Trees", "optb": "Height", "optc": "Animals", "optd": "Water", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is always in 'Sentiment'?", "opta": "Cruelty", "optb": "Insight", "optc": "Neutrality", "optd": "Emotion", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Controversy always involves", "opta": "Dislike", "optb": "Injustice", "optc": "Disagreement", "optd": "Passion", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is found necessarily in newspaper?", "opta": "Date", "optb": "Advertisement", "optc": "News", "optd": "Editor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}